<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="2.0">
    <book code="JOB" style="id">Job</book>
    <para style="mt1">Job</para>
	<chapter number="1" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />A man there hath been in the land of Uz--Job his name--and that man hath been perfect and upright--both fearing God, and turning aside from evil.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />And there are borne to him seven sons and three daughters,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />and his substance is seven thousand sheep, and three thousand camels, and five hundred pairs of oxen, and five hundred she-asses, and a service very abundant; and that man is greater than any of the sons of the east.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />And his sons have gone and made a banquet--the house of each [in] his day--and have sent and called to their three sisters to eat and to drink with them;</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />and it cometh to pass, when they have gone round the days of the banquet, that Job doth send and sanctify them, and hath risen early in the morning, and caused to ascend burnt-offerings-- the number of them all--for Job said, `Perhaps my sons havesinned, yet blessed God in their heart.' Thus doth Job all the days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />And the day is, that sons of God come in to station themselves by Jehovah, and there doth come also the Adversary in their midst.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And Jehovah saith unto the Adversary, `Whence comest thou?' And the Adversary answereth Jehovah and saith, `From going to and fro in the land, and from walking up and down on it.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And Jehovah saith unto the Adversary, `Hast thou set thy heart against My servant Job because there is none like him in the land, a man perfect and upright, fearing God, and turning aside from evil?'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />And the Adversary answereth Jehovah and saith, `For nought is Job fearing God?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Hast not Thou made a hedge for him, and for his house, and for all that he hath--round about?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />The work of his hands Thou hast blessed, and his substance hath spread in the land, and yet, put forth, I pray Thee, Thy hand, and strike against anything that he hath--if not: to Thy face he doth bless Thee!'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And Jehovah saith unto the Adversary, `Lo, all that he hath [is] in thy hand, only unto him put not forth thy hand.' And the Adversary goeth out from the presence of Jehovah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And the day is, that his sons and his daughters are eating, and drinking wine, in the house of their brother, the first-born.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />And a messenger hath come in unto Job and saith, `The oxen have been plowing, and the she-asses feeding by their sides,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />and Sheba doth fall, and take them, and the young men they have smitten by the mouth of the sword, and I am escaped--only I alone--to declare [it] to thee.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />While this [one] is speaking another also hath come and saith, `Fire of God hath fallen from the heavens, and burneth among the flock, and among the young men, and consumeth them, and I am escaped--only I alone--to declare [it] to thee.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />While this [one] is speaking another also hath come and saith, `Chaldeans made three heads, and rush on the camels, and take them, and the young men they have smitten by the mouth of the sword, and I am escaped--only I alone--to declare [it] to thee.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />While this [one] is speaking another also hath come and saith, `Thy sons and thy daughters are eating, and drinking wine, in the house of their brother, the first-born.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />And lo, a great wind hath come from over the wilderness, and striketh against the four corners of the house, and it falleth on the young men, and they are dead, and I am escaped--only I alone--to declare [it] to thee.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />And Job riseth, and rendeth his robe, and shaveth his head, and falleth to the earth, and doth obeisance,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />and he saith, `Naked came I forth from the womb of my mother, and naked I turn back thither: Jehovah hath given and Jehovah hath taken: let the name of Jehovah be blessed.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />In all this Job hath not sinned, nor given folly to God.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And the day is, that sons of God come in to station themselves by Jehovah, and there doth come also the Adversary in their midst to station himself by Jehovah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />And Jehovah saith unto the Adversary, `Whence camest thou?' And the Adversary answereth Jehovah and saith, `From going to and fro in the land, and from walking up and down in it.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />And Jehovah saith unto the Adversary, `Hast thou set thy heart unto My servant Job because there is none like him in the land, a man perfect and upright, fearing God and turning aside from evil? and still he is keeping hold on his integrity, and thou dost move Me against him to swallow him up for nought!'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />And the Adversary answereth Jehovah and saith, `A skin for a skin, and all that a man hath he doth give for his life.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Yet, put forth, I pray Thee, Thy hand, and strike unto his bone and unto his flesh--if not: unto Thy face he doth bless Thee!'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />And Jehovah saith unto the Adversary, `Lo, he [is] in thy hand; only his life take care of.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And the Adversary goeth forth from the presence of Jehovah, and smiteth Job with a sore ulcer from the sole of his foot unto his crown.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And he taketh to him a potsherd to scrape himself with it, and he is sitting in the midst of the ashes.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />And his wife saith to him, `Still thou art keeping hold on thine integrity: bless God and die.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />And he saith unto her, `As one of the foolish women speaketh, thou speakest; yea, the good we receive from God, and the evil we do not receive.' In all this Job hath not sinned with his lips.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />And three of the friends of Job hear of all this evil that hath come upon him, and they come in each from his place--Eliphaz the Temanite, and Bildad the Shuhite, and Zophar the Naamathite--and they are met together to come in to bemoan him, and to comfort him;</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />and they lift up their eyes from afar and have not discerned him, and they lift up their voice and weep, and rend each his robe, and sprinkle dust on their heads--heavenward.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And they sit with him on the earth seven days and seven nights, and there is none speaking unto him a word when they have seen that the pain hath been very great.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />After this hath Job opened his mouth, and revileth his day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />And Job answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Let the day perish in which I am born, And the night that hath said: `A man-child hath been conceived.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />That day--let it be darkness, Let not God require it from above, Nor let light shine upon it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Let darkness and death-shade redeem it, Let a cloud tabernacle upon it, Let them terrify it as the most bitter of days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />That night--let thick darkness take it, Let it not be united to days of the year, Into the number of months let it not come.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Lo! that night--let it be gloomy, Let no singing come into it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Let the cursers of day mark it, Who are ready to wake up Leviathan.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Let the stars of its twilight be dark, Let it wait for light, and there is none, And let it not look on the eyelids of the dawn.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Because it hath not shut the doors Of the womb that was mine! And hide misery from mine eyes.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Why from the womb do I not die? From the belly I have come forth and gasp!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Wherefore have knees been before me? And what [are] breasts, that I suck?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />For now, I have lain down, and am quiet, I have slept--then there is rest to me,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />With kings and counsellors of earth, These building wastes for themselves.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Or with princes--they have gold, They are filling their houses [with] silver.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />(Or as a hidden abortion I am not, As infants--they have not seen light.)</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />There the wicked have ceased troubling, And there rest do the wearied in power.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Together prisoners have been at ease, They have not heard the voice of an exactor,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Small and great [are] there the same. And a servant [is] free from his lord.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Why giveth He to the miserable light, and life to the bitter soul?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Who are waiting for death, and it is not, And they seek it above hid treasures.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Who are glad--unto joy, They rejoice when they find a grave.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />To a man whose way hath been hidden, And whom God doth shut up?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />For before my food, my sighing cometh, And poured out as waters [are] my roarings.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />For a fear I feared and it meeteth me, And what I was afraid of doth come to me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />I was not safe--nor was I quiet--Nor was I at rest--and trouble cometh!</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Eliphaz the Temanite answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Hath one tried a word with thee? --Thou art weary! And to keep in words who is able?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Lo, thou hast instructed many, And feeble hands thou makest strong.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />The stumbling one do thy words raise up, And bowing knees thou dost strengthen.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />But now, it cometh in unto thee, And thou art weary; It striketh unto thee, and thou art troubled.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Is not thy reverence thy confidence? Thy hope--the perfection of thy ways?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Remember, I pray thee, Who, being innocent, hath perished? And where have the upright been cut off?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />As I have seen--ploughers of iniquity, And sowers of misery, reap it!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />From the breath of God they perish, And from the spirit of His anger consumed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />The roaring of a lion, And the voice of a fierce lion, And teeth of young lions have been broken.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />An old lion is perishing without prey, And the whelps of the lioness do separate.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And unto me a thing is secretly brought, And receive doth mine ear a little of it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />In thoughts from visions of the night, In the falling of deep sleep on men,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Fear hath met me, and trembling, And the multitude of my bones caused to fear.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And a spirit before my face doth pass, Stand up doth the hair of my flesh;</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />It standeth, and I discern not its aspect, A similitude [is] over-against mine eyes, Silence! and a voice I hear:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />`Is mortal man than God more righteous? Than his Maker is a man cleaner?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Lo, in His servants He putteth no credence, Nor in His messengers setteth praise.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Also--the inhabitants of houses of clay, (Whose foundation [is] in the dust, They bruise them before a moth.)</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />From morning to evening are beaten down, Without any regarding, for ever they perish.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Hath not their excellency been removed with them? They die, and not in wisdom!</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Pray, call, is there any to answer thee? And unto which of the holy ones dost thou turn?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />For provocation slayeth the perverse, And envy putteth to death the simple,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />I--I have seen the perverse taking root, And I mark his habitation straightway,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Far are his sons from safety, And they are bruised in the gate, And there is no deliverer.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Whose harvest the hungry doth eat, And even from the thorns taketh it, And the designing swallowed their wealth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />For sorrow cometh not forth from the dust, Nor from the ground springeth up misery.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />For man to misery is born, And the sparks go high to fly.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Yet I--I inquire for God, And for God I give my word,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Doing great things, and there is no searching. Wonderful, till there is no numbering.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Who is giving rain on the face of the land, And is sending waters on the out-places.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />To set the low on a high place, And the mourners have been high [in] safety.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Making void thoughts of the subtile, And their hands do not execute wisdom.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Capturing the wise in their subtilty, And the counsel of wrestling ones was hastened,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />By day they meet darkness, And as night--they grope at noon.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And He saveth the wasted from their mouth, And from a strong hand the needy,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />And there is hope to the poor, And perverseness hath shut her mouth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Lo, the happiness of mortal man, God doth reprove him: And the chastisement of the Mighty despise not,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />For He doth pain, and He bindeth up, He smiteth, and His hands heal.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />In six distresses He delivereth thee, And in seven evil striketh not on thee.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />In famine He hath redeemed thee from death, And in battle from the hands of the sword.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />When the tongue scourgeth thou art hid, And thou art not afraid of destruction, When it cometh.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />At destruction and at hunger thou mockest, And of the beast of the earth, Thou art not afraid.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />(For with sons of the field [is] thy covenant, And the beast of the field Hath been at peace with thee.)</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />And thou hast known that thy tent [is] peace, And inspected thy habitation, and errest not,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />And hast known that numerous [is] Thy seed, And thine offspring as the herb of the earth;</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Thou comest in full age unto the grave, As the going up of a stalk in its season.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />Lo, this--we searched it out--it [is] right, hearken; And thou, know for thyself!</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Job answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />O that my provocation were thoroughly weighed, And my calamity in balances They would lift up together!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />For now, than the sands of the sea it is heavier, Therefore my words have been rash.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />For arrows of the Mighty [are] with me, Whose poison is drinking up my spirit. Terrors of God array themselves [for] me!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Brayeth a wild ass over tender grass? Loweth an ox over his provender?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Eaten is an insipid thing without salt? Is there sense in the drivel of dreams?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />My soul is refusing to touch! They [are] as my sickening food.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />O that my request may come, That God may grant my hope!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />That God would please--and bruise me, Loose His hand and cut me off!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />And yet it is my comfort, (And I exult in pain--He doth not spare,) That I have not hidden The sayings of the Holy One.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />What [is] my power that I should hope? And what mine end That I should prolong my life?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Is my strength the strength of stones? Is my flesh brazen?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Is not my help with me, And substance driven from me?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />To a despiser of his friends [is] shame, And the fear of the Mighty he forsaketh.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />My brethren have deceived as a brook, As a stream of brooks they pass away.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />That are black because of ice, By them doth snow hide itself.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />By the time they are warm they have been cut off, By its being hot they have been Extinguished from their place.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Turn aside do the paths of their way, They ascend into emptiness, and are lost.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Passengers of Tema looked expectingly, Travellers of Sheba hoped for them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />They were ashamed that one hath trusted, They have come unto it and are confounded.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Surely now ye have become the same! Ye see a downfall, and are afraid.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Is it because I said, Give to me? And, By your power bribe for me?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />And, Deliver me from the hand of an adversary? And, From the hand of terrible ones ransom me?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Shew me, and I--I keep silent, And what I have erred, let me understand.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />How powerful have been upright sayings, And what doth reproof from you reprove?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />For reproof--do you reckon words? And for wind--sayings of the desperate.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />Anger on the fatherless ye cause to fall, And are strange to your friend.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />And, now, please, look upon me, Even to your face do I lie?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />Turn back, I pray you, let it not be perverseness, Yea, turn back again--my righteousness [is] in it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />Is there in my tongue perverseness? Discerneth not my palate desirable things?</para>
	<chapter number="7" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Is there not a warfare to man on earth? And as the days of an hireling his days?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />As a servant desireth the shadow, And as a hireling expecteth his wage,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />So I have been caused to inherit months of vanity, And nights of misery they numbered to me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />If I lay down then I said, `When do I rise!' And evening hath been measured, And I have been full of tossings till dawn.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Clothed hath been my flesh [with] worms, And a clod of dust, My skin hath been shrivelled and is loathsome,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />My days swifter than a weaving machine, And they are consumed without hope.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Remember Thou that my life [is] a breath, Mine eye turneth not back to see good.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />The eye of my beholder beholdeth me not. Thine eyes [are] upon me--and I am not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Consumed hath been a cloud, and it goeth, So he who is going down to Sheol cometh not up.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />He turneth not again to his house, Nor doth his place discern him again.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Also I--I withhold not my mouth--I speak in the distress of my spirit, I talk in the bitterness of my soul.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />A sea -[monster] am I, or a dragon, That thou settest over me a guard?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />When I said, `My bed doth comfort me,' He taketh away in my talking my couch.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />And thou hast affrighted me with dreams, And from visions thou terrifiest me,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And my soul chooseth strangling, Death rather than my bones.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />I have wasted away--not to the age do I live. Cease from me, for my days [are] vanity.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />What [is] man that Thou dost magnify him? And that Thou settest unto him Thy heart?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />And inspectest him in the mornings, In the evenings dost try him?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />How long dost Thou not look from me? Thou dost not desist till I swallow my spittle.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />I have sinned, what do I to Thee, O watcher of man? Why hast Thou set me for a mark to Thee, And I am for a burden to myself--and what?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Thou dost not take away my transgression, And cause to pass away mine iniquity, Because now, for dust I lie down: And Thou hast sought me--and I am not!</para>
	<chapter number="8" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Bildad the Shuhite answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Till when dost thou speak these things? And a strong wind--sayings of thy mouth?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Doth God pervert judgment? And doth the Mighty One pervert justice?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />If thy sons have sinned before Him, And He doth send them away, By the hand of their transgression,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />If thou dost seek early unto God, And unto the Mighty makest supplication,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />If pure and upright thou [art], Surely now He waketh for thee, And hath completed The habitation of thy righteousness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And thy beginning hath been small, And thy latter end is very great.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />For, ask I pray thee of a former generation, And prepare to a search of their fathers,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />(For of yesterday we [are], and we know not, For a shadow [are] our days on earth.)</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Do they not shew thee--speak to thee, And from their heart bring forth words?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />`Doth a rush wise without mire? A reed increase without water?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />While it [is] in its budding--uncropped, Even before any herb it withereth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />So [are] the paths of all forgetting God, And the hope of the profane doth perish,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Whose confidence is loathsome, And the house of a spider his trust.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />He leaneth on his house--and it standeth not: He taketh hold on it--and it abideth not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Green he [is] before the sun, And over his garden his branch goeth out.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />By a heap his roots are wrapped, A house of stones he looketh for.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />If [one] doth destroy him from his place, Then it hath feigned concerning him, I have not seen thee!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Lo, this [is] the joy of his way, And from the dust others spring up.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Lo, God doth not reject the perfect, Nor taketh hold on the hand of evil doers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />While he filleth with laughter thy mouth, And thy lips with shouting,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Those hating thee do put on shame, And the tent of the wicked is not!</para>
	<chapter number="9" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Job answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Truly I have known that [it is] so, And what--is man righteous with God?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />If he delight to strive with Him--He doth not answer him one of a thousand.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Wise in heart and strong in power--Who hath hardened toward Him and is at peace?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Who is removing mountains, And they have not known, Who hath overturned them in His anger.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Who is shaking earth from its place, And its pillars move themselves.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Who is speaking to the sun, and it riseth not, And the stars He sealeth up.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Stretching out the heavens by Himself, And treading on the heights of the sea,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Making Osh, Kesil, and Kimah, And the inner chambers of the south.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Doing great things till there is no searching, And wonderful, till there is no numbering.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Lo, He goeth over by me, and I see not, And He passeth on, and I attend not to it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Lo, He snatches away, who bringeth it back? Who saith unto Him, `What dost Thou?'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />God doth not turn back His anger, Under Him bowed have proud helpers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />How much less do I--I answer Him? Choose out my words with Him?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Whom, though I were righteous, I answer not, For my judgment I make supplication.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Though I had called and He answereth me, I do not believe that He giveth ear [to] my voice.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Because with a tempest He bruiseth me, And hath multiplied my wounds for nought.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />He permitteth me not to refresh my spirit, But filleth me with bitter things.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />If of power, lo, the Strong One; And if of judgment--who doth convene me?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />If I be righteous, Mine mouth doth declare me wicked, Perfect I am! --it declareth me perverse.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Perfect I am! --I know not my soul, I despise my life.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />It is the same thing, therefore I said, `The perfect and the wicked He is consuming.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />If a scourge doth put to death suddenly, At the trial of the innocent He laugheth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Earth hath been given Into the hand of the wicked one. The face of its judges he covereth, If not--where, who [is] he?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />My days have been swifter than a runner, They have fled, they have not seen good,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />They have passed on with ships of reed, As an eagle darteth on food.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />Though I say, `I forget my talking, I forsake my corner, and I brighten up!'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />I have been afraid of all my griefs, I have known that Thou dost not acquit me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />I--I am become wicked; why [is] this? [In] vain I labour.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />If I have washed myself with snow-water, And purified with soap my hands,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />Then in corruption Thou dost dip me, And my garments have abominated me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />But if a man like myself--I answer him, We come together into judgment.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />If there were between us an umpire, He doth place his hand on us both.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />He doth turn aside from off me his rod, And His terror doth not make me afraid,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" />I speak, and do not fear Him, But I am not right with myself.</para>
	<chapter number="10" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />My soul hath been weary of my life, I leave off my talking to myself, I speak in the bitterness of my soul.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />I say unto God, `Do not condemn me, Let me know why Thou dost strive [with] me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Is it good for Thee that Thou dost oppress? That Thou despisest the labour of Thy hands, And on the counsel of the wicked hast shone?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Eyes of flesh hast Thou? As man seeth--seest Thou?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />As the days of man [are] Thy days? Thy years as the days of a man?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />That Thou inquirest for mine iniquity, And for my sin seekest?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />For Thou knowest that I am not wicked, And there is no deliverer from Thy hand.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Thy hands have taken pains about me, And they make me together round about, And Thou swallowest me up!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Remember, I pray Thee, That as clay Thou hast made me, And unto dust Thou dost bring me back.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Dost Thou not as milk pour me out? And as cheese curdle me?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Skin and flesh Thou dost put on me, And with bones and sinews dost fence me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Life and kindness Thou hast done with me. And Thy inspection hath preserved my spirit.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And these Thou hast laid up in Thy heart, I have known that this [is] with Thee.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />If I sinned, then Thou hast observed me, And from mine iniquity dost not acquit me,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />If I have done wickedly--woe to me, And righteously--I lift not up my head, Full of shame--then see my affliction,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />And it riseth--as a lion Thou huntest me. And Thou turnest back--Thou shewest Thyself wonderful in me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Thou renewest Thy witnesses against me, And dost multiply Thine anger with me, Changes and warfare [are] with me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />And why from the womb Hast Thou brought me forth? I expire, and the eye doth not see me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />As I had not been, I am, From the belly to the grave I am brought,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Are not my days few? Cease then, and put from me, And I brighten up a little,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Before I go, and return not, Unto a land of darkness and death-shade,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />A land of obscurity as thick darkness, Death-shade--and no order, And the shining [is] as thick darkness.'</para>
	<chapter number="11" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Zophar the Naamathite answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Is a multitude of words not answered? And is a man of lips justified?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Thy devices make men keep silent, Thou scornest, and none is causing blushing!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />And thou sayest, `Pure [is] my discourse, And clean I have been in Thine eyes.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />And yet, O that God had spoken! And doth open His lips with thee.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />And declare to thee secrets of wisdom, For counsel hath foldings. And know thou that God forgetteth for thee, [Some] of thine iniquity.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />By searching dost thou find out God? Unto perfection find out the Mighty One?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Heights of the heavens! --what dost thou? Deeper than Sheol! --what knowest thou?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Longer than earth [is] its measure, And broader than the sea.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />If He pass on, and shut up, and assemble, Who then dost reverse it?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />For he hath known men of vanity, And He seeth iniquity, And one doth not consider [it]!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And empty man is bold, And the colt of a wild ass man is born.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />If thou--thou hast prepared thy heart, And hast spread out unto Him thy hands,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />If iniquity [is] in thy hand, put it far off, And let not perverseness dwell in thy tents.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />For then thou liftest up thy face from blemish, And thou hast been firm, and fearest not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />For thou dost forget misery, As waters passed away thou rememberest.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />And above the noon doth age rise, Thou fliest--as the morning thou art.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />And thou hast trusted because their is hope, And searched--in confidence thou liest down,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />And thou hast rested, And none is causing trembling, And many have entreated thy face;</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />And the eyes of the wicked are consumed, And refuge hath perished from them, And their hope [is] a breathing out of soul!</para>
	<chapter number="12" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Job answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Truly--ye [are] the people, And with you doth wisdom die.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />I also have a heart like you, I am not fallen more than you, And with whom is there not like these?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />A laughter to his friend I am: `He calleth to God, and He answereth him,' A laughter [is] the perfect righteous one.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />A torch--despised in the thoughts of the secure Is prepared for those sliding with the feet.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />At peace are the tents of spoilers, And those provoking God have confidence, He into whose hand God hath brought.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And yet, ask, I pray thee, [One of] the beasts, and it doth shew thee, And a fowl of the heavens, And it doth declare to thee.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Or talk to the earth, and it sheweth thee, And fishes of the sea recount to thee:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />`Who hath not known in all these, That the hand of Jehovah hath done this?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />In whose hand [is] the breath of every living thing, And the spirit of all flesh of man.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Doth not the ear try words? And the palate taste food for itself?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />With the very aged [is] wisdom, And [with] length of days understanding.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />With Him [are] wisdom and might, To him [are] counsel and understanding.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Lo, He breaketh down, and it is not built up, He shutteth against a man, And it is not opened.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Lo, He keepeth in the waters, and they are dried up, And he sendeth them forth, And they overturn the land.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />With Him [are] strength and wisdom, His the deceived and deceiver.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Causing counsellors to go away a spoil, And judges He maketh foolish.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />The bands of kings He hath opened, And He bindeth a girdle on their loins.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Causing ministers to go away a spoil And strong ones He overthroweth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Turning aside the lip of the stedfast, And the reason of the aged He taketh away.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Pouring contempt upon princes, And the girdle of the mighty He made feeble.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Removing deep things out of darkness, And He bringeth out to light death-shade.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Magnifying the nations, and He destroyeth them, Spreading out the nations, and He quieteth them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Turning aside the heart Of the heads of the people of the land, And he causeth them to wander In vacancy--no way!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />They feel darkness, and not light, He causeth them to wander as a drunkard.</para>
	<chapter number="13" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Lo, all--hath mine eye seen, Heard hath mine ear, and it attendeth to it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />According to your knowledge I have known--also I. I am not fallen more than you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Yet I for the Mighty One do speak, And to argue for God I delight.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />And yet, ye [are] forgers of falsehood, Physicians of nought--all of you,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />O that ye would keep perfectly silent, And it would be to you for wisdom.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Hear, I pray you, my argument, And to the pleadings of my lips attend,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />For God do ye speak perverseness? And for Him do ye speak deceit?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />His face do ye accept, if for God ye strive?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Is [it] good that He doth search you, If, as one mocketh at a man, ye mock at Him?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />He doth surely reprove you, if in secret ye accept faces.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Doth not His excellency terrify you? And His dread fall upon you?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Your remembrances [are] similes of ashes, For high places of clay your heights.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Keep silent from me, and I speak, And pass over me doth what?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Wherefore do I take my flesh in my teeth? And my soul put in my hand?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Lo, He doth slay me--I wait not! Only, my ways unto His face I argue.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Also--He [is] to me for salvation, For the profane cometh not before Him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Hear ye diligently my word, And my declaration with your ears.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Lo, I pray you, I have set in order the cause, I have known that I am righteous.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Who [is] he that doth strive with me? For now I keep silent and gasp.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Only two things, O God, do with me: Then from Thy face I am not hidden.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Thy hand put far off from me, And Thy terror let not terrify me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />And call Thou, and I--I answer, Or--I speak, and answer Thou me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />How many iniquities and sins have I? My transgression and my sin let me know.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Why dost Thou hide Thy face? And reckonest me for an enemy to Thee?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />A leaf driven away dost Thou terrify? And the dry stubble dost Thou pursue?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />For Thou writest against me bitter things, And causest me to possess iniquities of my youth:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />And puttest in the stocks my feet, And observest all my paths, On the roots of my feet Thou settest a print,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />And he, as a rotten thing, weareth away, As a garment hath a moth consumed him.</para>
	<chapter number="14" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Man, born of woman! Of few days, and full of trouble!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />As a flower he hath gone forth, and is cut off, And he fleeth as a shadow and standeth not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Also--on this Thou hast opened Thine eyes, And dost bring me into judgment with Thee.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Who giveth a clean thing out of an unclean? not one.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />If determined are his days, The number of his months [are] with Thee, His limit Thou hast made, And he passeth not over;</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Look away from off him that he may cease, Till he enjoy as an hireling his day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />For there is of a tree hope, if it be cut down, That again it doth change, That its tender branch doth not cease.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />If its root becometh old in the earth, And its stem doth die in the dust,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />From the fragrance of water it doth flourish, And hath made a crop as a plant.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />And a man dieth, and becometh weak, And man expireth, and where [is] he?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Waters have gone away from a sea, And a river becometh waste and dry.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And man hath lain down, and riseth not, Till the wearing out of the heavens they awake not, Nor are roused from their sleep.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />O that in Sheol Thou wouldest conceal me, Hide me till the turning of Thine anger, Set for me a limit, and remember me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />If a man dieth--doth he revive? All days of my warfare I wait, till my change come.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Thou dost call, and I--I answer Thee; To the work of Thy hands Thou hast desire.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />But now, my steps Thou numberest, Thou dost not watch over my sin.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Sealed up in a bag [is] my transgression, And Thou sewest up mine iniquity.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />And yet, a falling mountain wasteth away, And a rock is removed from its place.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Stones have waters worn away, Their outpourings wash away the dust of earth, And the hope of man Thou hast destroyed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Thou prevailest [over] him for ever, and he goeth, He is changing his countenance, And Thou sendest him away.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Honoured are his sons, and he knoweth not; And they are little, and he attendeth not to them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Only--his flesh for him is pained, And his soul for him doth mourn.'</para>
	<chapter number="15" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Eliphaz the Temanite answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Doth a wise man answer [with] vain knowledge? And fill [with] an east wind his belly?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />To reason with a word not useful? And speeches--no profit in them?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Yea, thou dost make reverence void, And dost diminish meditation before God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />For thy mouth teacheth thine iniquity, And thou chooseth the tongue of the subtile.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Thy mouth declareth thee wicked, and not I, And thy lips testify against thee.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />The first man art thou born? And before the heights wast thou formed?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Of the secret counsel of God dost thou hear? And withdrawest thou unto thee wisdom?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />What hast thou known, and we know not? Understandest thou--and it is not with us?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Both the gray-headed And the very aged [are] among us--Greater than thy father [in] days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Too few for thee are the comforts of God? And a gentle word [is] with thee,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />What--doth thine heart take thee away? And what--are thine eyes high?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />For thou turnest against God thy spirit? And hast brought out words from thy mouth:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />What [is] man that he is pure, And that he is righteous, one born of woman?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Lo, in His holy ones He putteth no credence, And the heavens have not been pure in His eyes.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Also--surely abominable and filthy Is man drinking as water perverseness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />I shew thee--hearken to me--And this I have seen and declare:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Which the wise declare--And have not hid--from their fathers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />To them alone was the land given, And a stranger passed not over into their midst:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />`All days of the wicked he is paining himself, And few years have been laid up for the terrible one.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />A fearful voice [is] in his ears, In peace doth a destroyer come to him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />He believeth not to return from darkness, And watched [is] he for the sword.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />He is wandering for bread--`Where [is] it?' He hath known that ready at his hand Is a day of darkness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Terrify him do adversity and distress, They prevail over him As a king ready for a boaster.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />For he stretched out against God his hand, And against the Mighty he maketh himself mighty.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />He runneth unto Him with a neck, With thick bosses of his shields.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />For he hath covered his face with his fat, And maketh vigour over [his] confidence.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />And he inhabiteth cities cut off, houses not dwelt in, That have been ready to become heaps.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />He is not rich, nor doth his wealth rise, Nor doth he stretch out on earth their continuance.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />He turneth not aside from darkness, His tender branch doth a flame dry up, And he turneth aside at the breath of His mouth!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />Let him not put credence in vanity, He hath been deceived, For vanity is his recompence.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />Not in his day is it completed, And his bending branch is not green.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />He shaketh off as a vine his unripe fruit, And casteth off as an olive his blossom.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />For the company of the profane [is] gloomy, And fire hath consumed tents of bribery.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" />To conceive misery, and to bear iniquity, Even their heart doth prepare deceit.</para>
	<chapter number="16" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Job answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />I have heard many such things, Miserable comforters [are] ye all.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Is there an end to words of wind? Or what doth embolden thee that thou answerest?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />I also, like you, might speak, If your soul were in my soul's stead. I might join against you with words, And nod at you with my head.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />I might harden you with my mouth, And the moving of my lips might be sparing.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />If I speak, my pain is not restrained, And I cease--what goeth from me?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Only, now, it hath wearied me; Thou hast desolated all my company,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And Thou dost loathe me, For a witness it hath been, And rise up against me doth my failure, In my face it testifieth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />His anger hath torn, and he hateth me, He hath gnashed at me with his teeth, My adversary sharpeneth his eyes for me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />They have gaped on me with their mouth, In reproach they have smitten my cheeks, Together against me they set themselves.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />God shutteth me up unto the perverse, And to the hands of the wicked turneth me over.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />At ease I have been, and he breaketh me, And he hath laid hold on my neck, And he breaketh me in pieces, And he raiseth me to him for a mark.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Go round against me do his archers. He splitteth my reins, and spareth not, He poureth out to the earth my gall.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />He breaketh me--breach upon breach, He runneth upon me as a mighty one.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Sackcloth I have sewed on my skin, And have rolled in the dust my horn.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />My face is foul with weeping, And on mine eyelids [is] death-shade.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Not for violence in my hands, And my prayer [is] pure.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />O earth, do not thou cover my blood! And let there not be a place for my cry.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Also, now, lo, in the heavens [is] my witness, And my testifier in the high places.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />My interpreter [is] my friend, Unto God hath mine eye dropped:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />And he reasoneth for a man with God, And a son of man for his friend.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />When a few years do come, Then a path I return not do I go.</para>
	<chapter number="17" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />My spirit hath been destroyed, My days extinguished--graves [are] for me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />If not--mockeries [are] with me. And in their provocations mine eye lodgeth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Place, I pray Thee, my pledge with Thee; Who is he that striketh hand with me?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />For their heart Thou hast hidden From understanding, Therefore Thou dost not exalt them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />For a portion he sheweth friendship, And the eyes of his sons are consumed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />And he set me up for a proverb of the peoples, And a wonder before them I am.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And dim from sorrow is mine eye, And my members as a shadow all of them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Astonished are the upright at this, And the innocent against the profane Stirreth himself up.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />And the righteous layeth hold [on] his way, And the clean of hands addeth strength, And- -dumb are they all.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Return, and come in, I pray you, And I find not among you a wise man.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />My days have passed by, My devices have been broken off, The possessions of my heart!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Night for day they appoint, Light [is] near because of darkness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />If I wait--Sheol [is] my house, In darkness I have spread out my couch.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />To corruption I have called: --`Thou [art] my father.' `My mother' and `my sister' --to the worm.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And where [is] now my hope? Yea, my hope, who doth behold it?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />[To] the parts of Sheol ye go down, If together on the dust we may rest.</para>
	<chapter number="18" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Bildad the Shuhite answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />When do ye set an end to words? Consider ye, and afterwards do we speak.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Wherefore have we been reckoned as cattle? We have been defiled in your eyes!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />(He is tearing himself in his anger.) For thy sake is earth forsaken? And removed is a rock from its place?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Also, the light of the wicked is extinguished. And there doth not shine a spark of his fire.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />The light hath been dark in his tent, And his lamp over him is extinguished.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Straitened are the steps of his strength, And cast him down doth his own counsel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />For he is sent into a net by his own feet, And on a snare he doth walk habitually.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Seize on the heel doth a gin, Prevail over him do the designing.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Hidden in the earth is his cord, And his trap on the path.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Round about terrified him have terrors, And they have scattered him--at his feet.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Hungry is his sorrow, And calamity is ready at his side.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />It consumeth the parts of his skin, Consume his parts doth death's first-born.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Drawn from his tent is his confidence, And it causeth him to step to the king of terrors.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />It dwelleth in his tent--out of his provender, Scattered over his habitation is sulphur.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />From beneath his roots are dried up, And from above cut off is his crop.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />His memorial hath perished from the land, And he hath no name on the street.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />They thrust him from light unto darkness, And from the habitable earth cast him out.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />He hath no continuator, Nor successor among his people, And none is remaining in his dwellings.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />At this day westerns have been astonished And easterns have taken fright.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Only these [are] tabernacles of the perverse, And this the place God hath not known.</para>
	<chapter number="19" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Job answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Till when do ye afflict my soul, And bruise me with words?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />These ten times ye put me to shame, ye blush not. Ye make yourselves strange to me--</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />And also--truly, I have erred, With me doth my error remain.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />If, truly, over me ye magnify yourselves, And decide against me my reproach;</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Know now, that God turned me upside down, And His net against me hath set round,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Lo, I cry out--violence, and am not answered, I cry aloud, and there is no judgment.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />My way He hedged up, and I pass not over, And on my paths darkness He placeth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Mine honour from off me He hath stripped, And He turneth the crown from my head.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />He breaketh me down round about, and I go, And removeth like a tree my hope.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />And He kindleth against me His anger, And reckoneth me to Him as His adversaries.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Come in do His troops together, And they raise up against me their way, And encamp round about my tent.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />My brethren from me He hath put far off, And mine acquaintances surely Have been estranged from me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Ceased have my neighbours And my familiar friends have forgotten me,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Sojourners of my house and my maids, For a stranger reckon me: An alien I have been in their eyes.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />To my servant I have called, And he doth not answer, With my mouth I make supplication to him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />My spirit is strange to my wife, And my favours to the sons of my [mother's] womb.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Also sucklings have despised me, I rise, and they speak against me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Abominate me do all the men of my counsel, And those I have loved, Have been turned against me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />To my skin and to my flesh Cleaved hath my bone, And I deliver myself with the skin of my teeth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Pity me, pity me, ye my friends, For the hand of God hath stricken against me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Why do you pursue me as God? And with my flesh are not satisfied?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Who doth grant now, That my words may be written? Who doth grant that in a book they may be graven?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />With a pen of iron and lead--For ever in a rock they may be hewn.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />That--I have known my Redeemer, The Living and the Last, For the dust he doth rise.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />And after my skin hath compassed this [body], Then from my flesh I see God:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />Whom I--I see on my side, And mine eyes have beheld, and not a stranger, Consumed have been my reins in my bosom.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />But ye say, `Why do we pursue after him?' And the root of the matter hath been found in me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />Be ye afraid because of the sword, For furious [are] the punishments of the sword, That ye may know that [there is] a judgment.</para>
	<chapter number="20" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Zophar the Naamathite answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Therefore my thoughts cause me to answer, And because of my sensations in me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />The chastisement of my shame I hear, And the spirit of mine understanding Doth cause me to answer:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />This hast thou known from antiquity? Since the placing of man on earth?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />That the singing of the wicked [is] short, And the joy of the profane for a moment,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Though his excellency go up to the heavens, And his head against a cloud he strike--</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />As his own dung for ever he doth perish, His beholders say: `Where [is] he?'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />As a dream he fleeth, and they find him not, And he is driven away as a vision of the night,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />The eye hath not seen him, and addeth not. And not again doth his place behold him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />His sons do the poor oppress, And his hands give back his wealth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />His bones have been full of his youth, And with him on the dust it lieth down.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Though he doth sweeten evil in his mouth, Doth hide it under his tongue,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Hath pity on it, and doth not forsake it, And keep it back in the midst of his palate,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />His food in his bowels is turned, The bitterness of asps [is] in his heart.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Wealth he hath swallowed, and doth vomit it. From his belly God driveth it out.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Gall of asps he sucketh, Slay him doth the tongue of a viper.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />He looketh not on rivulets, Flowing of brooks of honey and butter.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />He is giving back [what] he laboured for, And doth not consume [it]; As a bulwark [is] his exchange, and he exults not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />For he oppressed--he forsook the poor, A house he hath taken violently away, And he doth not build it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />For he hath not known ease in his belly. With his desirable thing he delivereth not himself.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />There is not a remnant to his food, Therefore his good doth not stay.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />In the fulness of his sufficiency he is straitened. Every perverse hand doth meet him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />It cometh to pass, at the filling of his belly, He sendeth forth against him The fierceness of His anger, Yea, He raineth on him in his eating.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />He fleeth from an iron weapon, Pass through him doth a bow of brass.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />One hath drawn, And it cometh out from the body, And a glittering weapon from his gall proceedeth. On him [are] terrors.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />All darkness is hid for his treasures, Consume him doth a fire not blown, Broken is the remnant in his tent.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />Reveal do the heavens his iniquity, And earth is raising itself against him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />Remove doth the increase of his house, Poured forth in a day of His anger.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />This [is] the portion of a wicked man from God. And an inheritance appointed him by God.</para>
	<chapter number="21" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Job answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Hear ye diligently my word, And this is your consolation.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Bear with me, and I speak, And after my speaking--ye may deride.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />I--to man [is] my complaint? and if [so], wherefore May not my temper become short?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Turn unto me, and be astonished, And put hand to mouth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Yea, if I have remembered, then I have been troubled. And my flesh hath taken fright.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Wherefore do the wicked live? They have become old, Yea, they have been mighty in wealth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Their seed is established, Before their face with them, And their offspring before their eyes.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Their houses [are] peace without fear, Nor [is] a rod of God upon them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />His bullock hath eaten corn, and doth not loath. His cow bringeth forth safely, And doth not miscarry.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />They send forth as a flock their sucklings, And their children skip,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />They lift [themselves] up at timbrel and harp, And rejoice at the sound of an organ.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />They wear out in good their days, And in a moment [to] Sheol go down.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />And they say to God, `Turn aside from us, And the knowledge of Thy ways We have not desired.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />What [is] the Mighty One that we serve Him? And what do we profit when we meet with Him?'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Lo, not in their hand [is] their good, (The counsel of the wicked Hath been far from me.)</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />How oft is the lamp of the wicked extinguished, And come on them doth their calamity? Pangs He apportioneth in His anger.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />They are as straw before wind, And as chaff a hurricane hath stolen away,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />God layeth up for his sons his sorrow, He giveth recompense unto him--and he knoweth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />His own eyes see his destruction, And of the wrath of the Mighty he drinketh.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />For what [is] his delight in his house after him, And the number of his months cut off?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />To God doth [one] teach knowledge, And He the high doth judge?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />This [one] dieth in his perfect strength, Wholly at ease and quiet.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />His breasts have been full of milk, And marrow his bones doth moisten.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />And this [one] dieth with a bitter soul, And have not eaten with gladness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Together--on the dust they lie down, And the worm doth cover them over.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />Lo, I have known your thoughts, And the devices against me ye do wrongfully.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />For ye say, `Where [is] the house of the noble? And where the tent--The tabernacles of the wicked?'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />Have ye not asked those passing by the way? And their signs do ye not know?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />That to a day of calamity is the wicked spared. To a day of wrath they are brought.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />Who doth declare to his face his way? And [for] that which he hath done, Who doth give recompence to him?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />And he--to the graves he is brought. And over the heap a watch is kept.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />Sweet to him have been the clods of the valley, And after him every man he draweth, And before him there is no numbering.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />And how do ye comfort me [with] vanity, And in your answers hath been left trespass?</para>
	<chapter number="22" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Eliphaz the Temanite answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />To God is a man profitable, Because a wise man to himself is profitable?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Is it a delight to the Mighty One That thou art righteous? is it gain, That thou makest perfect thy ways?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Because of thy reverence Doth He reason [with] thee? He entereth with thee into judgment:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Is not thy wickedness abundant? And there is no end to thine iniquities.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />For thou takest a pledge of thy brother for nought, And the garments of the naked Thou dost strip off.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Thou causest not the weary to drink water, And from the hungry thou withholdest bread.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />As to the man of arm--he hath the earth, And the accepted of face--he dwelleth in it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Widows thou hast sent away empty, And the arms of the fatherless are bruised.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Therefore round about thee [are] snares, And trouble thee doth fear suddenly.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Or darkness--thou dost not see, And abundance of waters doth cover thee.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Is not God high [in] heaven? And see the summit of the stars, That they are high.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And thou hast said, `What--hath God known? Through thickness doth He judge?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Thick clouds [are] a secret place to Him, And He doth not see;' And the circle of the heavens He walketh habitually,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />The path of the age dost thou observe, That men of iniquity have trodden?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Who have been cut down unexpectedly, A flood is poured out on their foundation.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Those saying to God, `Turn aside from us,' And what doth the Mighty One to them?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />And he hath filled their houses [with] good: (And the counsel of the wicked Hath been far from me.)</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />See do the righteous and they rejoice, And the innocent mocketh at them,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />`Surely our substance hath not been cut off, And their excellency hath fire consumed.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Acquaint thyself, I pray thee, with Him, And be at peace, Thereby thine increase [is] good.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Receive, I pray thee, from His mouth a law, And set His sayings in thy heart.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />If thou dost return unto the Mighty Thou art built up, Thou puttest iniquity far from thy tents.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />So as to set on the dust a defence, And on a rock of the valleys a covering.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />And the Mighty hath been thy defence, And silver [is] strength to thee.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />For then on the Mighty thou delightest thyself, And dost lift up unto God thy face,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />Thou dost make supplication unto Him, And He doth hear thee, And thy vows thou completest.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />And thou decreest a saying, And it is established to thee, And on thy ways hath light shone.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />For they have made low, And thou sayest, `Lift up.' And the bowed down of eyes he saveth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />He delivereth the not innocent, Yea, he hath been delivered By the cleanness of thy hands.</para>
	<chapter number="23" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Job answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Also--to-day [is] my complaint bitter, My hand hath been heavy because of my sighing.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />O that I had known--and I find Him, I come in unto His seat,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />I arrange before Him the cause, And my mouth fill [with] arguments.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />I know the words He doth answer me, And understand what He saith to me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />In the abundance of power doth He strive with me? No! surely He putteth [it] in me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />There the upright doth reason with Him, And I escape for ever from my judge.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Lo, forward I go--and He is not, And backward--and I perceive him not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />[To] the left in His working--and I see not, He is covered [on] the right, and I behold not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />For He hath known the way with me, He hath tried me--as gold I go forth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />On His step hath my foot laid hold, His way I have kept, and turn not aside,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />The command of His lips, and I depart not. Above my allotted portion I have laid up The sayings of His mouth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And He [is] in one [mind], And who doth turn Him back? And His soul hath desired-- and He doth [it].</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />For He doth complete my portion, And many such things [are] with Him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Therefore, from His presence I am troubled, I consider, and am afraid of Him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />And God hath made my heart soft, And the Mighty hath troubled me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />For I have not been cut off before darkness, And before me He covered thick darkness.</para>
	<chapter number="24" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Wherefore from the Mighty One Times have not been hidden, And those knowing Him have not seen His days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />The borders they reach, A drove they have taken violently away, Yea, they do evil.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />The ass of the fatherless they lead away, They take in pledge the ox of the widow,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />They turn aside the needy from the way, Together have hid the poor of the earth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Lo, wild asses in a wilderness, They have gone out about their work, Seeking early for prey, A mixture for himself--food for young ones.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />In a field his provender they reap, And the vineyard of the wicked they glean.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />The naked they cause to lodge Without clothing. And there is no covering in the cold.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />From the inundation of hills they are wet, And without a refuge--have embraced a rock.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />They take violently away From the breast the orphan, And on the poor they lay a pledge.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Naked, they have gone without clothing, And hungry--have taken away a sheaf.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Between their walls they make oil, Wine-presses they have trodden, and thirst.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Because of enmity men do groan, And the soul of pierced ones doth cry, And God doth not give praise.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />They have been among rebellious ones of light, They have not discerned His ways, Nor abode in His paths.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />At the light doth the murderer rise, He doth slay the poor and needy, And in the night he is as a thief.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And the eye of an adulterer Hath observed the twilight, Saying, `No eye doth behold me.' And he putteth the face in secret.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />He hath dug in the darkness--houses; By day they shut themselves up, They have not known light.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />When together, morning [is] to them death shade, When he discerneth the terrors of death shade.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Light he [is] on the face of the waters, Vilified is their portion in the earth, He turneth not the way of vineyards.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Drought--also heat--consume snow-waters, Sheol [those who] have sinned.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Forget him doth the womb, Sweeten [on] him doth the worm, No more is he remembered, And broken as a tree is wickedness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Treating evil the barren [who] beareth not, And [to] the widow he doth no good,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />And hath drawn the mighty by his power, He riseth, and none believeth in life.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />He giveth to him confidence, and he is supported, And his eyes [are] on their ways.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />High they were [for] a little, and they are not, And they have been brought low. As all [others] they are shut up, And as the head of an ear of corn cut off.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />And if not now, who doth prove me a liar, And doth make of nothing my word?</para>
	<chapter number="25" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Bildad the Shuhite answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />The rule and fear [are] with Him, Making peace in His high places.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Is their [any] number to His troops? And on whom ariseth not His light?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />And what? is man righteous with God? And what? is he pure--born of a woman?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Lo--unto the moon, and it shineth not, And stars have not been pure in His eyes.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />How much less man--a grub, And the son of man--a worm!</para>
	<chapter number="26" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Job answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />What--thou hast helped the powerless, Saved an arm not strong!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />What--thou hast given counsel to the unwise, And wise plans in abundance made known.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />With whom hast thou declared words? And whose breath came forth from thee?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />The Rephaim are formed, Beneath the waters, also their inhabitants.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Naked [is] Sheol over-against Him, And there is no covering to destruction.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Stretching out the north over desolation, Hanging the earth upon nothing,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Binding up the waters in His thick clouds, And the cloud is not rent under them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Taking hold of the face of the throne, Spreading over it His cloud.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />A limit He hath placed on the waters, Unto the boundary of light with darkness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Pillars of the heavens do tremble, And they wonder because of His rebuke.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />By His power He hath quieted the sea, And by His understanding smitten the proud.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />By His Spirit the heavens He beautified, Formed hath His hand the fleeing serpent.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Lo, these [are] the borders of His way, And how little a matter is heard of Him, And the thunder of His might Who doth understand?</para>
	<chapter number="27" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Job addeth to lift up his simile, and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />God liveth! He turned aside my judgment, And the Mighty--He made my soul bitter.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />For all the while my breath [is] in me, And the spirit of God in my nostrils.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />My lips do not speak perverseness, And my tongue doth not utter deceit.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Pollution to me--if I justify you, Till I expire I turn not aside mine integrity from me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />On my righteousness I have laid hold, And I do not let it go, My heart doth not reproach me while I live.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />As the wicked is my enemy, And my withstander as the perverse.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />For what [is] the hope of the profane, When He doth cut off? When God doth cast off his soul?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />His cry doth God hear, When distress cometh on him?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />On the Mighty doth he delight himself? Call God at all times?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />I shew you by the hand of God, That which [is] with the Mighty I hide not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Lo, ye--all of you--have seen, And why [is] this--ye are altogether vain?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />This [is] the portion of wicked man with God, And the inheritance of terrible ones From the Mighty they receive.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />If his sons multiply--for them [is] a sword. And his offspring [are] not satisfied [with] bread.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />His remnant in death are buried, And his widows do not weep.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />If he heap up as dust silver, And as clay prepare clothing,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />He prepareth--and the righteous putteth [it] on, And the silver the innocent doth apportion.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />He hath built as a moth his house, And as a booth a watchman hath made.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Rich he lieth down, and he is not gathered, His eyes he hath opened, and he is not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Overtake him as waters do terrors, By night stolen him away hath a whirlwind.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Take him up doth an east wind, and he goeth, And it frighteneth him from his place,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />And it casteth at him, and doth not spare, From its hand he diligently fleeth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />It clappeth at him its hands, And it hisseth at him from his place.</para>
	<chapter number="28" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Surely there is for silver a source, And a place for the gold they refine;</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Iron from the dust is taken, And [from] the firm stone brass.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />An end hath he set to darkness, And to all perfection he is searching, A stone of darkness and death-shade.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />A stream hath broken out from a sojourner, Those forgotten of the foot, They were low, from man they wandered.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />The earth! from it cometh forth bread, And its under-part is turned like fire.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />A place of the sapphire [are] its stones, And it hath dust of gold.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />A path--not known it hath a ravenous fowl, Nor scorched it hath an eye of the kite,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Nor trodden it have the sons of pride, Not passed over it hath the fierce lion.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Against the flint he sent forth his hand, He overturned from the root mountains.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Among rocks, brooks he hath cleaved, And every precious thing hath his eye seen.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />From overflowing floods he hath bound, And the hidden thing bringeth out [to] light.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And the wisdom--whence is it found? And where [is] this, the place of understanding?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Man hath not known its arrangement, Nor is it found in the land of the living.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />The deep hath said, `It [is] not in me,' And the sea hath said, `It is not with me.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Gold is not given for it, Nor is silver weighed--its price.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />It is not valued with pure gold of Ophir, With precious onyx and sapphire,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Not equal it do gold and crystal, Nor [is] its exchange a vessel of fine gold.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Corals and pearl are not remembered, The acquisition of wisdom [is] above rubies.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Not equal it doth the topaz of Cush, With pure gold it is not valued.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />And the wisdom--whence doth it come? And where [is] this, the place of understanding?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />It hath been hid from the eyes of all living. And from the fowl of the heavens It hath been hidden.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Destruction and death have said: `With our ears we have heard its fame.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />God hath understood its way, And He hath known its place.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />For He to the ends of the earth doth look, Under the whole heavens He doth see,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />To make for the wind a weight, And the waters He meted out in measure.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />In His making for the rain a limit, And a way for the brightness of the voices,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />Then He hath seen and declareth it, He hath prepared it, and also searched it out,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />And He saith to man: --`Lo, fear of the Lord, that [is] wisdom, And to turn from evil [is] understanding.'</para>
	<chapter number="29" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Job addeth to lift up his simile, and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Who doth make me as [in] months past, As [in] the days of God's preserving me?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />In His causing His lamp to shine on my head, By His light I walk [through] darkness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />As I have been in days of my maturity, And the counsel of God upon my tent.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />When yet the Mighty One [is] with me. Round about me--my young ones,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />When washing my goings with butter, And the firm rock [is] with me rivulets of oil.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />When I go out to the gate by the city, In a broad place I prepare my seat.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Seen me have youths, and they, been hidden, And the aged have risen--they stood up.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Princes have kept in words, And a hand they place on their mouth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />The voice of leaders hath been hidden, And their tongue to the palate hath cleaved.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />For the ear heard, and declareth me happy, And the eye hath seen, and testifieth [to] me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />For I deliver the afflicted who is crying, And the fatherless who hath no helper.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />The blessing of the perishing cometh on me, And the heart of the widow I cause to sing.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Righteousness I have put on, and it clotheth me, As a robe and a diadem my justice.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Eyes I have been to the blind, And feet to the lame [am] I.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />A father I [am] to the needy, And the cause I have not known I search out.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />And I break the jaw-teeth of the perverse, And from his teeth I cast away prey.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />And I say, `With my nest I expire, And as the sand I multiply days.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />My root is open unto the waters, And dew doth lodge on my branch.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />My honour [is] fresh with me, And my bow in my hand is renewed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />To me they have hearkened, Yea, they wait, and are silent for my counsel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />After my word they change not, And on them doth my speech drop,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />And they wait as [for] rain for me, And their mouth they have opened wide [As] for the latter rain.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />I laugh unto them--they give no credence, And the light of my face cause not to fall.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />I choose their way, and sit head, And I dwell as a king in a troop, When mourners he doth comfort.</para>
	<chapter number="30" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And now, laughed at me, Have the younger in days than I, Whose fathers I have loathed to set With the dogs of my flock.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Also--the power of their hands, why [is it] to me? On them hath old age perished.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />With want and with famine gloomy, Those fleeing to a dry place, Formerly a desolation and waste,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Those cropping mallows near a shrub, And broom-roots [is] their food.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />From the midst they are cast out, (They shout against them as a thief),</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />In a frightful place of valleys to dwell, Holes of earth and clefts.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Among shrubs they do groan, Under nettles they are gathered together.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Sons of folly--even sons without name, They have been smitten from the land.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />And now, their song I have been, And I am to them for a byword.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />They have abominated me, They have kept far from me, And from before me have not spared to spit.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Because His cord He loosed and afflicteth me, And the bridle from before me, They have cast away.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />On the right hand doth a brood arise, My feet they have cast away, And they raise up against me, Their paths of calamity.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />They have broken down my path, By my calamity they profit, `He hath no helper.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />As a wide breach they come, Under the desolation have rolled themselves.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />He hath turned against me terrors, It pursueth as the wind mine abundance, And as a thick cloud, Hath my safety passed away.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />And now, in me my soul poureth itself out, Seize me do days of affliction.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />At night my bone hath been pierced in me, And mine eyelids do not lie down.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />By the abundance of power, Is my clothing changed, As the mouth of my coat it doth gird me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Casting me into mire, And I am become like dust and ashes.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />I cry unto Thee, And Thou dost not answer me, I have stood, and Thou dost consider me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Thou art turned to be fierce to me, With the strength of Thy hand, Thou oppressest me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Thou dost lift me up, On the wind Thou dost cause me to ride, And Thou meltest--Thou levellest me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />For I have known To death Thou dost bring me back, And [to] the house appointed for all living.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Surely not against the heap Doth He send forth the hand, Though in its ruin they have safety.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />Did not I weep for him whose day is hard? Grieved hath my soul for the needy.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />When good I expected, then cometh evil, And I wait for light, and darkness cometh.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />My bowels have boiled, and have not ceased, Gone before me have days of affliction.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />Mourning I have gone without the sun, I have risen, in an assembly I cry.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />A brother I have been to dragons, And a companion to daughters of the ostrich.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />My skin hath been black upon me, And my bone hath burned from heat,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />And my harp doth become mourning, And my organ the sound of weeping.</para>
	<chapter number="31" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />A covenant I made for mine eyes, And what--do I attend to a virgin?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />And what [is] the portion of God from above? And the inheritance of the Mighty from the heights?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Is not calamity to the perverse? And strangeness to workers of iniquity?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Doth not He see my ways, And all my steps number?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />If I have walked with vanity, And my foot doth hasten to deceit,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />He doth weigh me in righteous balances, And God doth know my integrity.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />If my step doth turn aside from the way, And after mine eyes hath my heart gone, And to my hands cleaved hath blemish,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Let me sow--and another eat, And my products let be rooted out.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />If my heart hath been enticed by woman, And by the opening of my neighbour I laid wait,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Grind to another let my wife, And over her let others bend.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />For it [is] a wicked thing, and a judicial iniquity;</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />For a fire it [is], to destruction it consumeth, And among all mine increase doth take root,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />If I despise the cause of my man-servant, And of my handmaid, In their contending with me,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Then what do I do when God ariseth? And when He doth inspect, What do I answer Him?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Did not He that made me in the womb make him? Yea, prepare us in the womb doth One.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />If I withhold from pleasure the poor, And the eyes of the widow do consume,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />And I do eat my morsel by myself, And the orphan hath not eat of it,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />(But from my youth He grew up with me as [with] a father, And from the belly of my mother I am led.)</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />If I see [any] perishing without clothing, And there is no covering to the needy,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />If his loins have not blessed me, And from the fleece of my sheep He doth not warm himself,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />If I have waved at the fatherless my hand, When I see in [him] the gate of my court,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />My shoulder from its blade let fall, And mine arm from the bone be broken.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />For a dread unto me [is] calamity [from] God, And because of His excellency I am not able.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />If I have made gold my confidence, And to the pure gold have said, `My trust,'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />If I rejoice because great [is] my wealth, And because abundance hath my hand found,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />If I see the light when it shineth, And the precious moon walking,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />And my heart is enticed in secret, And my hand doth kiss my mouth,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />It also [is] a judicial iniquity, For I had lied to God above.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />If I rejoice at the ruin of my hater, And stirred up myself when evil found him,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />Yea, I have not suffered my mouth to sin, To ask with an oath his life.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />If not--say ye, O men of my tent, `O that we had of his flesh, we are not satisfied.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />In the street doth not lodge a stranger, My doors to the traveller I open.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />If I have covered as Adam my transgressions, To hide in my bosom mine iniquity,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />Because I fear a great multitude, And the contempt of families doth affright me, Then I am silent, I go not out of the opening.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" />Who giveth to me a hearing? lo, my mark. The Mighty One doth answer me, And a bill hath mine adversary written.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />If not--on my shoulder I take it up, I bind it a crown on myself.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" />The number of my steps I tell Him, As a leader I approach Him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" />If against me my land doth cry out, And together its furrows weep,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" />If its strength I consumed without money, And the life of its possessors, I have caused to breathe out,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" />Instead of wheat let a thorn go forth, And instead of barley a useless weed! The words of</para>
	<chapter number="32" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And these three men cease from answering Job, for he [is] righteous in his own eyes,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />and burn doth the anger of Elihu son of Barachel the Buzite, of the family of Ram; against</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />and against his three friends hath his anger burned, because that they have not found an answer, and condemn Job.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />And Elihu hath waited earnestly beside Job with words, for they are older than he in days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />And Elihu seeth that there is no answer in the mouth of the three men, and his anger burneth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />And Elihu son of Barachel the Buzite answereth and saith: --Young I [am] in days, and ye [are] age Therefore I have feared, And am afraid of shewing you my opinion.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />I said: Days do speak, And multitude of years teach wisdom.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Surely a spirit is in man, And the breath of the Mighty One Doth cause them to understand.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />The multitude are not wise, Nor do the aged understand judgment.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Therefore I have said: Hearken to me, I do shew my opinion--even I.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Lo, I have waited for your words, I give ear unto your reasons, Till ye search out sayings.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And unto you I attend, And lo, there is no reasoner for Job, [Or] answerer of his sayings among you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Lest ye say, We have found wisdom, God doth thrust him away, not man.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />And he hath not set in array words for me, And with your sayings I do not answer him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />(They have broken down, They have not answered again, They removed from themselves words.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />And I have waited, but they do not speak, For they have stood still, They have not answered any more.)</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />I answer, even I--my share, I shew my opinion--even I.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />For I have been full of words, Distressed me hath the spirit of my breast,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Lo, my breast [is] as wine not opened, Like new bottles it is broken up.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />I speak, and there is refreshment to me, I open my lips and answer.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Let me not, I pray you, accept the face of any, Nor unto man give flattering titles,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />For I have not known to give flattering titles, In a little doth my Maker take me away.</para>
	<chapter number="33" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And yet, I pray thee, O Job, Hear my speech and [to] all my words give ear.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Lo, I pray thee, I have opened my mouth, My tongue hath spoken in the palate.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Of the uprightness of my heart [are] my sayings, And knowledge have my lips clearly spoken.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />The Spirit of God hath made me, And the breath of the Mighty doth quicken me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />If thou art able--answer me, Set in array before me--station thyself.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Lo, I [am], according to thy word, for God, From the clay I--I also, have been formed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Lo, my terror doth not frighten thee, And my burden on thee is not heavy.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Surely--thou hast said in mine ears, And the sounds of words I hear:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />`Pure [am] I, without transgression, Innocent [am] I, and I have no iniquity.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Lo, occasions against me He doth find, He doth reckon me for an enemy to Him,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />He doth put in the stocks my feet, He doth watch all my paths.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Lo, [in] this thou hast not been righteous, I answer thee, that greater is God than man.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Wherefore against Him hast thou striven, When [for] all His matters He answereth not?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />For once doth God speak, and twice, (He doth not behold it.)</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />In a dream--a vision of night, In the falling of deep sleep on men, In slumberings on a bed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Then He uncovereth the ear of men, And for their instruction sealeth:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />To turn aside man [from] doing, And pride from man He concealeth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />He keepeth back his soul from corruption, And his life from passing away by a dart.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />And he hath been reproved With pain on his bed, And the strife of his bones [is] enduring.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />And his life hath nauseated bread, And his soul desirable food.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />His flesh is consumed from being seen, And high are his bones, they were not seen!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />And draw near to the pit doth his soul, And his life to those causing death.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />If there is by him a messenger, An interpreter--one of a thousand, To declare for man his uprightness:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Then He doth favour him and saith, `Ransom him from going down to the pit, I have found an atonement.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />Fresher [is] his flesh than a child's, He returneth to the days of his youth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />He maketh supplication unto God, And He accepteth him. And he seeth His face with shouting, And He returneth to man His righteousness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />He looketh on men, and saith, `I sinned, And uprightness I have perverted, And it hath not been profitable to me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />He hath ransomed my soul From going over into the pit, And my life on the light looketh.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />Lo, all these doth God work, Twice--thrice with man,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />To bring back his soul from the pit, To be enlightened with the light of the living.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />Attend, O Job, hearken to me, Keep silent, and I--I do speak.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />If there are words--answer me, Speak, for I have a desire to justify thee.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />If there are not--hearken thou to me, Keep silent, and I teach thee wisdom.</para>
	<chapter number="34" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Elihu answereth and saith:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Hear, O wise men, my words, And, O knowing ones, give ear to me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />For the ear doth try words, And the palate tasteth to eat.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Judgment let us choose for ourselves, Let us know among ourselves what [is] good.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />For Job hath said, `I have been righteous, And God hath turned aside my right,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Against my right do I lie? Mortal [is] mine arrow--without transgression.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Who [is] a man like Job? He drinketh scoffing like water,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And he hath travelled for company With workers of iniquity, So as to go with men of wickedness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />For he hath said, `It doth not profit a man, When he delighteth himself with God.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Therefore, O men of heart, hearken to me; Far be it from God to do wickedness, And [from] the Mighty to do perverseness:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />For the work of man he repayeth to him, And according to the path of each He doth cause him to find.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Yea, truly, God doth not do wickedly, And the Mighty doth not pervert judgment.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Who hath inspected for Himself the earth? And who hath placed all the habitable world?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />If He doth set on him His heart, His spirit and his breath unto Him He gathereth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Expire doth all flesh together, And man to dust returneth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />And if [there is] understanding, hear this, Give ear to the voice of my words.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Yea, doth one hating justice govern? Or the Most Just dost thou condemn?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Who hath said to a king--`Worthless,' Unto princes--`Wicked?'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />That hath not accepted the person of princes, Nor hath known the rich before the poor, For a work of His hands [are] all of them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />[In] a moment they die, and at midnight Shake do people, and they pass away, And they remove the mighty without hand.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />For His eyes [are] on the ways of each, And all his steps He doth see.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />There is no darkness nor death-shade, For workers of iniquity to be hidden there;</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />For He doth not suffer man any more, To go unto God in judgment,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />He breaketh the mighty--no searching! And He appointeth others in their stead.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />Therefore He knoweth their works, And He hath overturned by night, And they are bruised.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />As wicked He hath stricken them, In the place of beholders.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />Because that against right They have turned aside from after Him, And none of His ways have considered wisely,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />To cause to come in unto Him The cry of the poor, And the cry of the afflicted He heareth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />And He giveth rest, and who maketh wrong? And hideth the face, and who beholdeth it? And in reference to a nation and to a man, [It is] the same.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />From the reigning of a profane man, From the snares of a people;</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />For unto God hath any said: `I have taken away, I do not corruptly,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />Besides [that which] I see, shew Thou me, If iniquity I have done--I do not add?'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />By thee doth He recompense, That thou hast refused--That thou dost choose, and not I? And what thou hast known, speak.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />Let men of heart say to me, And a wise man is hearkening to me.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" />Job--not with knowledge doth he speak, And his words [are] not with wisdom.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />My Father! let Job be tried--unto victory, Because of answers for men of iniquity,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" />For he doth add to his sin, Transgression among us he vomiteth, And multiplieth his sayings to God.</para>
	<chapter number="35" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Elihu answereth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />This hast thou reckoned for judgment: Thou hast said--`My righteousness [is] more than God's?'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />For thou sayest, `What doth it profit Thee! What do I profit from my sin?'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />I return thee words, and thy friends with thee,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Behold attentively the heavens--and see, And behold the clouds, They have been higher than thou.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />If thou hast sinned, what dost thou against Him? And thy transgressions have been multiplied, What dost thou to Him?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />If thou hast been righteous, What dost thou give to Him? Or what from thy hand doth He receive?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />For a man like thyself [is] thy wickedness, And for a son of man thy righteousness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Because of the multitude of oppressions They cause to cry out, They cry because of the arm of the mighty.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />And none said, `Where [is] God my maker? Giving songs in the night,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Teaching us more than the beasts of the earth, Yea, than the fowl of the heavens He maketh us wiser.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />There they cry, and He doth not answer, Because of the pride of evil doers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Surely vanity God doth not hear, And the Mighty doth not behold it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Yea, though thou sayest thou dost not behold Him, Judgment [is] before Him, and stay for Him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And, now, because there is not, He hath appointed His anger, And He hath not known in great extremity.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />And Job [with] vanity doth open his mouth, Without knowledge words he multiplieth.</para>
	<chapter number="36" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Elihu addeth and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Honour me a little, and I shew thee, That yet for God [are] words.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />I lift up my knowledge from afar, And to my Maker I ascribe righteousness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />For, truly, my words [are] not false, The perfect in knowledge [is] with thee.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Lo, God [is] mighty, and despiseth not, Mighty [in] power [and] heart.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />He reviveth not the wicked, And the judgment of the poor appointeth;</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />He withdraweth not from the righteous His eyes, And [from] kings on the throne, And causeth them to sit for ever, and they are high,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And if prisoners in fetters They are captured with cords of affliction,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Then He declareth to them their work, And their transgressions, Because they have become mighty,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />And He uncovereth their ear for instruction, And saith that they turn back from iniquity.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />If they do hear and serve, They complete their days in good, And their years in pleasantness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And if they do not hearken, By the dart they pass away, And expire without knowledge.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And the profane in heart set the face, They cry not when He hath bound them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Their soul dieth in youth, And their life among the defiled.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />He draweth out the afflicted in his affliction, And uncovereth in oppression their ear.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />And also He moved thee from a strait place, [To] a broad place--no straitness under it, And the sitting beyond of thy table Hath been full of fatness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />And the judgment of the wicked thou hast fulfilled, Judgment and justice are upheld-- because of fury,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Lest He move thee with a stroke, And the abundance of an atonement turn thee not aside.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Doth He value thy riches? He hath gold, and all the forces of power.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Desire not the night, For the going up of peoples in their stead.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Take heed--do not turn unto iniquity, For on this thou hast fixed Rather than [on] affliction.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Lo, God doth sit on high by His power, Who [is] like Him--a teacher?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Who hath appointed unto Him his way? And who said, `Thou hast done iniquity?'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Remember that thou magnify His work That men have beheld.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />All men have looked on it, Man looketh attentively from afar.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Lo, God [is] high, And we know not the number of His years, Yea, there [is] no searching.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />When He doth diminish droppings of the waters, They refine rain according to its vapour,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />Which clouds do drop, They distil on man abundantly.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />Yea, doth [any] understand The spreadings out of a cloud? The noises of His tabernacle?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />Lo, He hath spread over it His light, And the roots of the sea He hath covered,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />For by them He doth judge peoples, He giveth food in abundance.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />By two palms He hath covered the light, And layeth a charge over it in meeting,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />He sheweth by it [to] his friend substance, Anger against perversity.</para>
	<chapter number="37" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Also, at this my heart trembleth, And it moveth from its place.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Hearken diligently to the trembling of His voice, Yea, the sound from His mouth goeth forth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Under the whole heavens He directeth it, And its light [is] over the skirts of the earth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />After it roar doth a voice--He thundereth with the voice of His excellency, And He doth not hold them back, When His voice is heard.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />God thundereth with His voice wonderfully, Doing great things and we know not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />For to snow He saith, `Be [on] the earth.' And the small rain and great rain of His power.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Into the hand of every man he sealeth, For the knowledge by all men of His work.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And enter doth the beast into covert, And in its habitations it doth continue.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />From the inner chamber cometh a hurricane, And from scatterings winds--cold,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />From the breath of God is frost given, And the breadth of waters is straitened,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Yea, by filling He doth press out a cloud, Scatter a cloud doth His light.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And it is turning itself round by His counsels, For their doing all He commandeth them, On the face of the habitable earth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Whether for a rod, or for His land, Or for kindness--He doth cause it to come.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Hear this, O Job, Stand and consider the wonders of God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Dost thou know when God doth place them, And caused to shine the light of His cloud?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Dost thou know the balancings of a cloud? The wonders of the Perfect in knowledge?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />How thy garments [are] warm, In the quieting of the earth from the south?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Thou hast made an expanse with Him For the clouds--strong as a hard mirror!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Let us know what we say to Him, We set not in array because of darkness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Is it declared to Him that I speak? If a man hath spoken, surely he is swallowed up.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />And now, they have not seen the light, Bright it [is] in the clouds, And the wind hath passed by and cleanseth them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />From the golden north it cometh, Beside God [is] fearful honour.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />The Mighty! we have not found Him out, High in power and judgment, He doth not answer! And abundant in righteousness,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Therefore do men fear Him, He seeth not any of the wise of heart.</para>
	<chapter number="38" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Jehovah answereth Job out of the whirlwind, and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Who [is] this--darkening counsel, By words without knowledge?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Gird, I pray thee, as a man, thy loins, And I ask thee, and cause thou Me to know.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Where wast thou when I founded earth? Declare, if thou hast known understanding.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Who placed its measures--if thou knowest? Or who hath stretched out upon it a line?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />On what have its sockets been sunk? Or who hath cast its corner-stone?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />In the singing together of stars of morning, And all sons of God shout for joy,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And He shutteth up with doors the sea, In its coming forth, from the womb it goeth out.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />In My making a cloud its clothing, And thick darkness its swaddling band,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />And I measure over it My statute, And place bar and doors,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />And say, `Hitherto come thou, and add not, And a command is placed On the pride of thy billows.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Hast thou commanded morning since thy days? Causest thou the dawn to know its place?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />To take hold on the skirts of the earth, And the wicked are shaken out of it,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />It turneth itself as clay of a seal And they station themselves as clothed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And withheld from the wicked is their light, And the arm lifted up is broken.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Hast thou come in to springs of the sea? And in searching the deep Hast thou walked up and down?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Revealed to thee were the gates of death? And the gates of death-shade dost thou see?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Thou hast understanding, Even unto the broad places of earth! Declare--if thou hast known it all.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Where [is] this--the way light dwelleth? And darkness, where [is] this--its place?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />That thou dost take it unto its boundary, And that thou dost understand The paths of its house.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Thou hast known--for then thou art born And the number of thy days [are] many!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Hast thou come in unto the treasure of snow? Yea, the treasures of hail dost thou see?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />That I have kept back for a time of distress, For a day of conflict and battle.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Where [is] this, the way light is apportioned? It scattereth an east wind over the earth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />Who hath divided for the flood a conduit? And a way for the lightning of the voices?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />To cause [it] to rain on a land--no man, A wilderness--no man in it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />To satisfy a desolate and waste place, And to cause to shoot up The produce of the tender grass?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />Hath the rain a father? Or who hath begotten the drops of dew?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />From whose belly came forth the ice? And the hoar-frost of the heavens, Who hath begotten it?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />As a stone waters are hidden, And the face of the deep is captured.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />Dost thou bind sweet influences of Kimah? Or the attractions of Kesil dost thou open?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />Dost thou bring out Mazzaroth in its season? And Aysh for her sons dost thou comfort?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />Hast thou known the statutes of heaven? Or dost thou appoint Its dominion in the earth?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />Dost thou lift up to the cloud thy voice, And abundance of water doth cover thee?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" />Dost thou send out lightnings, and they go And say unto thee, `Behold us?'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />Who hath put in the inward parts wisdom? Or who hath given To the covered part understanding?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" />Who doth number the clouds by wisdom? And the bottles of the heavens, Who doth cause to lie down,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" />In the hardening of dust into hardness, And clods cleave together?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" />Dost thou hunt for a lion prey? And the desire of young lions fulfil?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" />When they bow down in dens--Abide in a thicket for a covert?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" />Who doth prepare for a raven his provision, When his young ones cry unto God? They wander without food.</para>
	<chapter number="39" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Hast thou known the time of The bearing of the wild goats of the rock? The bringing forth of hinds thou dost mark!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Thou dost number the months they fulfil? And thou hast known the time of their bringing forth!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />They bow down, Their young ones they bring forth safely, Their pangs they cast forth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Safe are their young ones, They grow up in the field, they have gone out, And have not returned to them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Who hath sent forth the wild ass free? Yea, the bands of the wild ass who opened?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Whose house I have made the wilderness, And his dwellings the barren land,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />He doth laugh at the multitude of a city, The cries of an exactor he heareth not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />The range of mountains [is] his pasture, And after every green thing he seeketh.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Is a Reem willing to serve thee? Doth he lodge by thy crib?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Dost thou bind a Reem in a furrow [with] his thick band? Doth he harrow valleys after thee?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Dost thou trust in him because great [is] his power? And dost thou leave unto him thy labour?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Dost thou trust in him That he doth bring back thy seed? And [to] thy threshing-floor doth gather [it]?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />The wing of the rattling ones exulteth, Whether the pinion of the ostrich or hawk.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />For she leaveth on the earth her eggs, And on the dust she doth warm them,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And she forgetteth that a foot may press it, And a beast of the field tread it down.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Her young ones it hath hardened without her, In vain [is] her labour without fear.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />For God hath caused her to forget wisdom, And He hath not given a portion To her in understanding:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />At the time on high she lifteth herself up, She laugheth at the horse and at his rider.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Dost thou give to the horse might? Dost thou clothe his neck [with] a mane?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Dost thou cause him to rush as a locust? The majesty of his snorting [is] terrible.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />They dig in a valley, and he rejoiceth in power, He goeth forth to meet the armour.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />He laugheth at fear, and is not affrighted, And he turneth not back from the face of the sword.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Against him rattle doth quiver, The flame of a spear, and a halbert.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />With trembling and rage he swalloweth the ground, And remaineth not stedfast Because of the sound of a trumpet.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />Among the trumpets he saith, Aha, And from afar he doth smell battle, Roaring of princes and shouting.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />By thine understanding flieth a hawk? Spreadeth he his wings to the south?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />At thy command goeth an eagle up high? Or lifteth he up his nest?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />A rock he doth inhabit, Yea, he lodgeth on the tooth of a rock, and fortress.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />From thence he hath sought food, To a far off place his eyes look attentively,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />And his brood gulp up blood, And where the pierced [are] --there [is] he!</para>
	<chapter number="40" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Jehovah doth answer Job, and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Is the striver with the Mighty instructed? The reprover of God, let him answer it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />And Job answereth Jehovah, and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Lo, I have been vile, What do I return to Thee? My hand I have placed on my mouth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Once I have spoken, and I answer not, And twice, and I add not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />And Jehovah answereth Job out of the whirlwind, and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Gird, I pray thee, as a man, thy loins, I ask thee, and cause thou Me to know.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Dost thou also make void My judgment? Dost thou condemn Me, That thou mayest be righteous?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />And an arm like God hast thou? And with a voice like Him dost thou thunder?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Put on, I pray thee, excellency and loftiness, Yea, honour and beauty put on.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Scatter abroad the wrath of thine anger, And see every proud one, and make him low.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />See every proud one--humble him, And tread down the wicked in their place.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Hide them in the dust together, Their faces bind in secret.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />And even I--I do praise thee, For thy right hand giveth salvation to thee.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Lo, I pray thee, Behemoth, that I made with thee: Grass as an ox he eateth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Lo, I pray thee, his power [is] in his loins, And his strength in the muscles of his belly.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />He doth bend his tail as a cedar, The sinews of his thighs are wrapped together,</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />His bones [are] tubes of brass, His bones [are] as a bar of iron.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />He [is] a beginning of the ways of God, His Maker bringeth nigh his sword;</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />For food do mountains bear for him, And all the beasts of the field play there.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Under shades he lieth down, In a secret place of reed and mire.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Cover him do shades, [with] their shadow, Cover him do willows of the brook.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Lo, a flood oppresseth--he doth not haste, He is confident though Jordan Doth come forth unto his mouth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Before his eyes doth [one] take him, With snares doth [one] pierce the nose?</para>
	<chapter number="41" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Dost thou draw leviathan with an angle? And with a rope thou lettest down--his tongue?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Dost thou put a reed in his nose? And with a thorn pierce his jaw?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Doth he multiply unto thee supplications? Doth he speak unto thee tender things?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Doth he make a covenant with thee? Dost thou take him for a servant age-during?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Dost thou play with him as a bird? And dost thou bind him for thy damsels?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />(Feast upon him do companions, They divide him among the merchants!)</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Dost thou fill with barbed irons his skin? And with fish-spears his head?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Place on him thy hand, Remember the battle--do not add!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Lo, the hope of him is found a liar, Also at his appearance is not one cast down?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />None so fierce that he doth awake him, And who [is] he before Me stationeth himself?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Who hath brought before Me and I repay? Under the whole heavens it [is] mine.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />I do not keep silent concerning his parts, And the matter of might, And the grace of his arrangement.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Who hath uncovered the face of his clothing? Within his double bridle who doth enter?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />The doors of his face who hath opened? Round about his teeth [are] terrible.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />A pride--strong ones of shields, Shut up--a close seal.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />One unto another they draw nigh, And air doth not enter between them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />One unto another they adhere, They stick together and are not separated.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />His sneezings cause light to shine, And his eyes [are] as the eyelids of the dawn.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Out of his mouth do flames go, sparks of fire escape.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Out of his nostrils goeth forth smoke, As a blown pot and reeds.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />His breath setteth coals on fire, And a flame from his mouth goeth forth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />In his neck lodge doth strength, And before him doth grief exult.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />The flakes of his flesh have adhered--Firm upon him--it is not moved.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />His heart [is] firm as a stone, Yea, firm as the lower piece.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />From his rising are the mighty afraid, From breakings they keep themselves free.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />The sword of his overtaker standeth not, Spear--dart--and lance.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />He reckoneth iron as straw, brass as rotten wood.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />The son of the bow doth not cause him to flee, Turned by him into stubble are stones of the sling.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />As stubble have darts been reckoned, And he laugheth at the shaking of a javelin.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />Under him [are] sharp points of clay, He spreadeth gold on the mire.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />He causeth to boil as a pot the deep, The sea he maketh as a pot of ointment.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />After him he causeth a path to shine, One thinketh the deep to be hoary.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />There is not on the earth his like, That is made without terror.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />Every high thing he doth see, He [is] king over all sons of pride.</para>
	<chapter number="42" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Job answereth Jehovah and saith: --</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Thou hast known that [for] all things Thou art able, And not withheld from Thee is [any] device:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />`Who [is] this, hiding counsel without knowledge?' Therefore, I have declared, and understand not, Too wonderful for me, and I know not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />`Hear, I pray thee, and I--I do speak, I ask thee, and cause thou me to know.'</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />By the hearing of the ear I heard Thee, And now mine eye hath seen Thee.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Therefore do I loathe [it], And I have repented on dust and ashes.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And it cometh to pass after Jehovah's speaking these words unto Job, that Jehovah saith unto Eliphaz the Temanite, `Burned hath Mine anger against thee, and against thy two friends, because ye have not spoken concerning Me rightly, like My servant Job.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And now, take to you seven bullocks and seven rams, and go ye unto My servant Job, and ye have caused a burnt-offering to ascend for you; and Job My servant doth pray for you, for surely his face I accept, so as not to do with you folly, becauseye have not spoken concerning Me rightly, like My servant Job.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />And they go--Eliphaz the Temanite, and Bildad the Shuhite, Zophar the Naamathite--and do as Jehovah hath spoken unto them; and Jehovah doth accept the face of Job.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />And Jehovah hath turned [to] the captivity of Job in his praying for his friends, and Jehovah doth add [to] all that Job hath--to double.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />And come unto him do all his brethren, and all his sisters, and all his former acquaintances, and they eat bread with him in his house, and bemoan him, and comfort him concerning all the evil that Jehovah had brought upon him, and they gave to him each one kesitah, and each one ring of gold.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And Jehovah hath blessed the latter end of Job more than his beginning, and he hath fourteen thousand of a flock, and six thousand camels, and a thousand pairs of oxen, and a thousand she-asses.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And he hath seven sons and three daughters;</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />and he calleth the name of the one Jemima, and the name of the second Kezia, and the name of the third Keren-Happuch.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And there have not been found women fair as the daughters of Job in all the land, and their father doth give to them an inheritance in the midst of their brethren.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />And Job liveth after this a hundred and forty years, and seeth his sons, and his sons' sons, four generations;</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />and Job dieth, aged and satisfied [with] days.</para>
	
</usx>