<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="2.0">
  <book code="PRO" style="id">Proverbs</book>
  <para style="mt">Proverbs</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The proverbs of Solomon the son of David, king of Israel;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />To know wisdom and instruction; to perceive the words of understanding;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />To receive the instruction of wisdom, justice, and judgment, and equity;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">equity: Heb. equities</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />To give subtilty to the simple, to the young man knowledge and discretion.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">discretion: or, advisement</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />A wise man will hear, and will increase learning; and a man of understanding shall attain unto wise counsels:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />To understand a proverb, and the interpretation; the words of the wise, and their dark sayings.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the interpretation: or, an eloquent speech</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />The fear of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is the beginning of knowledge: but fools despise wisdom and instruction.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the beginning: or, the principal part</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />My son, hear the instruction of thy father, and forsake not the law of thy mother:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />For they shall be an ornament of grace unto thy head, and chains about thy neck.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">an…: Heb. an adding</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />My son, if sinners entice thee, consent thou not.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />If they say, Come with us, let us lay wait for blood, let us lurk privily for the innocent without cause:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Let us swallow them up alive as the grave; and whole, as those that go down into the pit:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />We shall find all precious substance, we shall fill our houses with spoil:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Cast in thy lot among us; let us all have one purse:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />My son, walk not thou in the way with them; refrain thy foot from their path:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />For their feet run to evil, and make haste to shed blood.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Surely in vain the net is spread in the sight of any bird.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">in the…: Heb. in the eyes of every thing that hath a wing</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />And they lay wait for their own blood; they lurk privily for their own lives.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />So are the ways of every one that is greedy of gain; which taketh away the life of the owners thereof.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />Wisdom crieth without; she uttereth her voice in the streets:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Wisdom: Heb. Wisdoms, that is, Excellent wisdom</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />She crieth in the chief place of concourse, in the openings of the gates: in the city she uttereth her words, saying,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />How long, ye simple ones, will ye love simplicity? and the scorners delight in their scorning, and fools hate knowledge?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Turn you at my reproof: behold, I will pour out my spirit unto you, I will make known my words unto you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Because I have called, and ye refused; I have stretched out my hand, and no man regarded;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />But ye have set at nought all my counsel, and would none of my reproof:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />I also will laugh at your calamity; I will mock when your fear cometh;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />When your fear cometh as desolation, and your destruction cometh as a whirlwind; when distress and anguish cometh upon you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Then shall they call upon me, but I will not answer; they shall seek me early, but they shall not find me:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />For that they hated knowledge, and did not choose the fear of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />They would none of my counsel: they despised all my reproof.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />Therefore shall they eat of the fruit of their own way, and be filled with their own devices.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />For the turning away of the simple shall slay them, and the prosperity of fools shall destroy them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">turning…: or, ease of the simple</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />But whoso hearkeneth unto me shall dwell safely, and shall be quiet from fear of evil.</para>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />My son, if thou wilt receive my words, and hide my commandments with thee;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />So that thou incline thine ear unto wisdom, and apply thine heart to understanding;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Yea, if thou criest after knowledge, and liftest up thy voice for understanding;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">liftest…: Heb. givest thy voice</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />If thou seekest her as silver, and searchest for her as for hid treasures;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Then shalt thou understand the fear of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and find the knowledge of God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />For the <char style="nd">Lord</char> giveth wisdom: out of his mouth cometh knowledge and understanding.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />He layeth up sound wisdom for the righteous: he is a buckler to them that walk uprightly.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />He keepeth the paths of judgment, and preserveth the way of his saints.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Then shalt thou understand righteousness, and judgment, and equity; yea, every good path.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />When wisdom entereth into thine heart, and knowledge is pleasant unto thy soul;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Discretion shall preserve thee, understanding shall keep thee:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />To deliver thee from the way of the evil man, from the man that speaketh froward things;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Who leave the paths of uprightness, to walk in the ways of darkness;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Who rejoice to do evil, and delight in the frowardness of the wicked;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Whose ways are crooked, and they froward in their paths:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />To deliver thee from the strange woman, even from the stranger which flattereth with her words;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Which forsaketh the guide of her youth, and forgetteth the covenant of her God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />For her house inclineth unto death, and her paths unto the dead.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />None that go unto her return again, neither take they hold of the paths of life.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />That thou mayest walk in the way of good men, and keep the paths of the righteous.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />For the upright shall dwell in the land, and the perfect shall remain in it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />But the wicked shall be cut off from the earth, and the transgressors shall be rooted out of it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">rooted: or, plucked up</char></note></para>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />My son, forget not my law; but let thine heart keep my commandments:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />For length of days, and long life, and peace, shall they add to thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">long…: Heb. years of life</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Let not mercy and truth forsake thee: bind them about thy neck; write them upon the table of thine heart:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />So shalt thou find favour and good understanding in the sight of God and man.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">good…: or, good success</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Trust in the <char style="nd">Lord</char> with all thine heart; and lean not unto thine own understanding.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />In all thy ways acknowledge him, and he shall direct thy paths.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Be not wise in thine own eyes: fear the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and depart from evil.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />It shall be health to thy navel, and marrow to thy bones.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">health: Heb. medicine</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">marrow: Heb. watering, or, moistening</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Honour the <char style="nd">Lord</char> with thy substance, and with the firstfruits of all thine increase:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />So shall thy barns be filled with plenty, and thy presses shall burst out with new wine.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />My son, despise not the chastening of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>; neither be weary of his correction:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />For whom the <char style="nd">Lord</char> loveth he correcteth; even as a father the son in whom he delighteth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Happy is the man that findeth wisdom, and the man that getteth understanding.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">that getteth…: Heb. that draweth out understanding</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />For the merchandise of it is better than the merchandise of silver, and the gain thereof than fine gold.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />She is more precious than rubies: and all the things thou canst desire are not to be compared unto her.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Length of days is in her right hand; and in her left hand riches and honour.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Her ways are ways of pleasantness, and all her paths are peace.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />She is a tree of life to them that lay hold upon her: and happy is every one that retaineth her.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> by wisdom hath founded the earth; by understanding hath he established the heavens.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">established: or, prepared</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />By his knowledge the depths are broken up, and the clouds drop down the dew.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />My son, let not them depart from thine eyes: keep sound wisdom and discretion:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />So shall they be life unto thy soul, and grace to thy neck.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Then shalt thou walk in thy way safely, and thy foot shall not stumble.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />When thou liest down, thou shalt not be afraid: yea, thou shalt lie down, and thy sleep shall be sweet.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Be not afraid of sudden fear, neither of the desolation of the wicked, when it cometh.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />For the <char style="nd">Lord</char> shall be thy confidence, and shall keep thy foot from being taken.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Withhold not good from them to whom it is due, when it is in the power of thine hand to do it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">them…: Heb. the owners thereof</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Say not unto thy neighbour, Go, and come again, and to morrow I will give; when thou hast it by thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Devise not evil against thy neighbour, seeing he dwelleth securely by thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Devise…: or, Practise no evil</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />Strive not with a man without cause, if he have done thee no harm.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />Envy thou not the oppressor, and choose none of his ways.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the oppressor: Heb. a man of violence</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />For the froward is abomination to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>: but his secret is with the righteous.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />The curse of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is in the house of the wicked: but he blesseth the habitation of the just.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />Surely he scorneth the scorners: but he giveth grace unto the lowly.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />The wise shall inherit glory: but shame shall be the promotion of fools.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">shall be…: Heb. exalteth the fools</char></note></para>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Hear, ye children, the instruction of a father, and attend to know understanding.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />For I give you good doctrine, forsake ye not my law.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />For I was my father's son, tender and only beloved in the sight of my mother.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />He taught me also, and said unto me, Let thine heart retain my words: keep my commandments, and live.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Get wisdom, get understanding: forget it not; neither decline from the words of my mouth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Forsake her not, and she shall preserve thee: love her, and she shall keep thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Wisdom is the principal thing; therefore get wisdom: and with all thy getting get understanding.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Exalt her, and she shall promote thee: she shall bring thee to honour, when thou dost embrace her.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />She shall give to thine head an ornament of grace: a crown of glory shall she deliver to thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">a crown…: or, she shall compass thee with a crown of glory</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Hear, O my son, and receive my sayings; and the years of thy life shall be many.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />I have taught thee in the way of wisdom; I have led thee in right paths.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />When thou goest, thy steps shall not be straitened; and when thou runnest, thou shalt not stumble.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Take fast hold of instruction; let her not go: keep her; for she is thy life.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Enter not into the path of the wicked, and go not in the way of evil men.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Avoid it, pass not by it, turn from it, and pass away.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />For they sleep not, except they have done mischief; and their sleep is taken away, unless they cause some to fall.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />For they eat the bread of wickedness, and drink the wine of violence.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />But the path of the just is as the shining light, that shineth more and more unto the perfect day.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />The way of the wicked is as darkness: they know not at what they stumble.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />My son, attend to my words; incline thine ear unto my sayings.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />Let them not depart from thine eyes; keep them in the midst of thine heart.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />For they are life unto those that find them, and health to all their flesh.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">health: Heb. medicine</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Keep thy heart with all diligence; for out of it are the issues of life.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">with…: Heb. above all keeping</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Put away from thee a froward mouth, and perverse lips put far from thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">a froward…: Heb. frowardness of mouth and perverseness of lips</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Let thine eyes look right on, and let thine eyelids look straight before thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />Ponder the path of thy feet, and let all thy ways be established.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">let…: or, all thy ways shall be ordered aright</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Turn not to the right hand nor to the left: remove thy foot from evil.</para>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />My son, attend unto my wisdom, and bow thine ear to my understanding:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />That thou mayest regard discretion, and that thy lips may keep knowledge.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />For the lips of a strange woman drop as an honeycomb, and her mouth is smoother than oil:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">mouth: Heb. palate</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />But her end is bitter as wormwood, sharp as a twoedged sword.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Her feet go down to death; her steps take hold on hell.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Lest thou shouldest ponder the path of life, her ways are moveable, that thou canst not know them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Hear me now therefore, O ye children, and depart not from the words of my mouth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Remove thy way far from her, and come not nigh the door of her house:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Lest thou give thine honour unto others, and thy years unto the cruel:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Lest strangers be filled with thy wealth; and thy labours be in the house of a stranger;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">thy wealth: Heb. thy strength</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />And thou mourn at the last, when thy flesh and thy body are consumed,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />And say, How have I hated instruction, and my heart despised reproof;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />And have not obeyed the voice of my teachers, nor inclined mine ear to them that instructed me!</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />I was almost in all evil in the midst of the congregation and assembly.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Drink waters out of thine own cistern, and running waters out of thine own well.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Let thy fountains be dispersed abroad, and rivers of waters in the streets.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Let them be only thine own, and not strangers' with thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Let thy fountain be blessed: and rejoice with the wife of thy youth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />Let her be as the loving hind and pleasant roe; let her breasts satisfy thee at all times; and be thou ravished always with her love.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">satisfy…: Heb. water thee</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">be thou…: Heb. err thou always in her love</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And why wilt thou, my son, be ravished with a strange woman, and embrace the bosom of a stranger?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />For the ways of man are before the eyes of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and he pondereth all his goings.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />His own iniquities shall take the wicked himself, and he shall be holden with the cords of his sins.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">sins: Heb. sin</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />He shall die without instruction; and in the greatness of his folly he shall go astray.</para>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />My son, if thou be surety for thy friend, if thou hast stricken thy hand with a stranger,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Thou art snared with the words of thy mouth, thou art taken with the words of thy mouth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Do this now, my son, and deliver thyself, when thou art come into the hand of thy friend; go, humble thyself, and make sure thy friend.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">and make…: or, so shalt thou prevail with thy friend</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Give not sleep to thine eyes, nor slumber to thine eyelids.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Deliver thyself as a roe from the hand of the hunter, and as a bird from the hand of the fowler.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Go to the ant, thou sluggard; consider her ways, and be wise:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Which having no guide, overseer, or ruler,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Provideth her meat in the summer, and gathereth her food in the harvest.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />How long wilt thou sleep, O sluggard? when wilt thou arise out of thy sleep?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Yet a little sleep, a little slumber, a little folding of the hands to sleep:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />So shall thy poverty come as one that travelleth, and thy want as an armed man.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />A naughty person, a wicked man, walketh with a froward mouth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />He winketh with his eyes, he speaketh with his feet, he teacheth with his fingers;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Frowardness is in his heart, he deviseth mischief continually; he soweth discord.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">soweth: Heb. casteth forth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Therefore shall his calamity come suddenly; suddenly shall he be broken without remedy.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />These six things doth the <char style="nd">Lord</char> hate: yea, seven are an abomination unto him:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">unto…: Heb. of his soul</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />A proud look, a lying tongue, and hands that shed innocent blood,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">A proud…: Heb. Haughty eyes</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />An heart that deviseth wicked imaginations, feet that be swift in running to mischief,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />A false witness that speaketh lies, and he that soweth discord among brethren.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />My son, keep thy father's commandment, and forsake not the law of thy mother:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />Bind them continually upon thine heart, and tie them about thy neck.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />When thou goest, it shall lead thee; when thou sleepest, it shall keep thee; and when thou awakest, it shall talk with thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />For the commandment is a lamp; and the law is light; and reproofs of instruction are the way of life:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">lamp: or, candle</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />To keep thee from the evil woman, from the flattery of the tongue of a strange woman.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">of the…: or, of the strange tongue</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Lust not after her beauty in thine heart; neither let her take thee with her eyelids.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />For by means of a whorish woman a man is brought to a piece of bread: and the adulteress will hunt for the precious life.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the adulteress: Heb. the woman of a man, or, a man's wife</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Can a man take fire in his bosom, and his clothes not be burned?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Can one go upon hot coals, and his feet not be burned?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />So he that goeth in to his neighbour's wife; whosoever toucheth her shall not be innocent.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />Men do not despise a thief, if he steal to satisfy his soul when he is hungry;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />But if he be found, he shall restore sevenfold; he shall give all the substance of his house.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />But whoso committeth adultery with a woman lacketh understanding: he that doeth it destroyeth his own soul.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">understanding: Heb. heart</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />A wound and dishonour shall he get; and his reproach shall not be wiped away.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />For jealousy is the rage of a man: therefore he will not spare in the day of vengeance.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />He will not regard any ransom; neither will he rest content, though thou givest many gifts.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">He will…: Heb. He will not accept the face of any ransom</char></note></para>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />My son, keep my words, and lay up my commandments with thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Keep my commandments, and live; and my law as the apple of thine eye.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Bind them upon thy fingers, write them upon the table of thine heart.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Say unto wisdom, Thou art my sister; and call understanding thy kinswoman:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />That they may keep thee from the strange woman, from the stranger which flattereth with her words.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />For at the window of my house I looked through my casement,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And beheld among the simple ones, I discerned among the youths, a young man void of understanding,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the youths: Heb. the sons</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Passing through the street near her corner; and he went the way to her house,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />In the twilight, in the evening, in the black and dark night:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">in the evening: Heb. in the evening of days</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />And, behold, there met him a woman with the attire of an harlot, and subtil of heart.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />(She is loud and stubborn; her feet abide not in her house:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Now is she without, now in the streets, and lieth in wait at every corner.)</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />So she caught him, and kissed him, and with an impudent face said unto him,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">with…: Heb. she strengthened her face and said</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />I have peace offerings with me; this day have I payed my vows.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">I have…: Heb. Peace offerings are upon me</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Therefore came I forth to meet thee, diligently to seek thy face, and I have found thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />I have decked my bed with coverings of tapestry, with carved works, with fine linen of Egypt.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />I have perfumed my bed with myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Come, let us take our fill of love until the morning: let us solace ourselves with loves.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />For the goodman is not at home, he is gone a long journey:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />He hath taken a bag of money with him, and will come home at the day appointed.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">with…: Heb. in his hand</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the day…: or, the new moon</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />With her much fair speech she caused him to yield, with the flattering of her lips she forced him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />He goeth after her straightway, as an ox goeth to the slaughter, or as a fool to the correction of the stocks;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">straightway: Heb. suddenly</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Till a dart strike through his liver; as a bird hasteth to the snare, and knoweth not that it is for his life.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Hearken unto me now therefore, O ye children, and attend to the words of my mouth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Let not thine heart decline to her ways, go not astray in her paths.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />For she hath cast down many wounded: yea, many strong men have been slain by her.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Her house is the way to hell, going down to the chambers of death.</para>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Doth not wisdom cry? and understanding put forth her voice?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />She standeth in the top of high places, by the way in the places of the paths.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />She crieth at the gates, at the entry of the city, at the coming in at the doors.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Unto you, O men, I call; and my voice is to the sons of man.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />O ye simple, understand wisdom: and, ye fools, be ye of an understanding heart.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Hear; for I will speak of excellent things; and the opening of my lips shall be right things.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />For my mouth shall speak truth; and wickedness is an abomination to my lips.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">an…: Heb. the abomination of my lips</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />All the words of my mouth are in righteousness; there is nothing froward or perverse in them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">froward: Heb. wreathed</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />They are all plain to him that understandeth, and right to them that find knowledge.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Receive my instruction, and not silver; and knowledge rather than choice gold.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />For wisdom is better than rubies; and all the things that may be desired are not to be compared to it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />I wisdom dwell with prudence, and find out knowledge of witty inventions.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">prudence: or, subtilty</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />The fear of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is to hate evil: pride, and arrogancy, and the evil way, and the froward mouth, do I hate.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Counsel is mine, and sound wisdom: I am understanding; I have strength.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />By me kings reign, and princes decree justice.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />By me princes rule, and nobles, even all the judges of the earth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />I love them that love me; and those that seek me early shall find me.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Riches and honour are with me; yea, durable riches and righteousness.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />My fruit is better than gold, yea, than fine gold; and my revenue than choice silver.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />I lead in the way of righteousness, in the midst of the paths of judgment:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">lead: or, walk</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />That I may cause those that love me to inherit substance; and I will fill their treasures.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> possessed me in the beginning of his way, before his works of old.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />I was set up from everlasting, from the beginning, or ever the earth was.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />When there were no depths, I was brought forth; when there were no fountains abounding with water.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Before the mountains were settled, before the hills was I brought forth:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />While as yet he had not made the earth, nor the fields, nor the highest part of the dust of the world.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">fields: or, open places</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the highest…: or, the chief part</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />When he prepared the heavens, I was there: when he set a compass upon the face of the depth:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">a compass: or, a circle</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />When he established the clouds above: when he strengthened the fountains of the deep:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />When he gave to the sea his decree, that the waters should not pass his commandment: when he appointed the foundations of the earth:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />Then I was by him, as one brought up with him: and I was daily his delight, rejoicing always before him;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />Rejoicing in the habitable part of his earth; and my delights were with the sons of men.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />Now therefore hearken unto me, O ye children: for blessed are they that keep my ways.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />Hear instruction, and be wise, and refuse it not.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />Blessed is the man that heareth me, watching daily at my gates, waiting at the posts of my doors.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />For whoso findeth me findeth life, and shall obtain favour of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">obtain: Heb. bring forth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" />But he that sinneth against me wrongeth his own soul: all they that hate me love death.</para>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Wisdom hath builded her house, she hath hewn out her seven pillars:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />She hath killed her beasts; she hath mingled her wine; she hath also furnished her table.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">her beasts: Heb. her killing</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />She hath sent forth her maidens: she crieth upon the highest places of the city,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Whoso is simple, let him turn in hither: as for him that wanteth understanding, she saith to him,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Come, eat of my bread, and drink of the wine which I have mingled.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Forsake the foolish, and live; and go in the way of understanding.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />He that reproveth a scorner getteth to himself shame: and he that rebuketh a wicked man getteth himself a blot.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Reprove not a scorner, lest he hate thee: rebuke a wise man, and he will love thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Give instruction to a wise man, and he will be yet wiser: teach a just man, and he will increase in learning.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />The fear of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is the beginning of wisdom: and the knowledge of the holy is understanding.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />For by me thy days shall be multiplied, and the years of thy life shall be increased.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />If thou be wise, thou shalt be wise for thyself: but if thou scornest, thou alone shalt bear it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />A foolish woman is clamorous: she is simple, and knoweth nothing.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />For she sitteth at the door of her house, on a seat in the high places of the city,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />To call passengers who go right on their ways:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Whoso is simple, let him turn in hither: and as for him that wanteth understanding, she saith to him,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Stolen waters are sweet, and bread eaten in secret is pleasant.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">eaten…: Heb. of secrecies</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />But he knoweth not that the dead are there; and that her guests are in the depths of hell.</para>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The proverbs of Solomon. A wise son maketh a glad father: but a foolish son is the heaviness of his mother.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Treasures of wickedness profit nothing: but righteousness delivereth from death.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will not suffer the soul of the righteous to famish: but he casteth away the substance of the wicked.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the substance…: or, the wicked for their wickedness</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />He becometh poor that dealeth with a slack hand: but the hand of the diligent maketh rich.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />He that gathereth in summer is a wise son: but he that sleepeth in harvest is a son that causeth shame.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Blessings are upon the head of the just: but violence covereth the mouth of the wicked.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />The memory of the just is blessed: but the name of the wicked shall rot.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />The wise in heart will receive commandments: but a prating fool shall fall.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">a prating…: Heb. a fool of lips</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">fall: Heb. be beaten</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />He that walketh uprightly walketh surely: but he that perverteth his ways shall be known.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />He that winketh with the eye causeth sorrow: but a prating fool shall fall.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">fall: Heb. be beaten</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />The mouth of a righteous man is a well of life: but violence covereth the mouth of the wicked.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Hatred stirreth up strifes: but love covereth all sins.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />In the lips of him that hath understanding wisdom is found: but a rod is for the back of him that is void of understanding.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">of understanding: Heb. of heart</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Wise men lay up knowledge: but the mouth of the foolish is near destruction.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />The rich man's wealth is his strong city: the destruction of the poor is their poverty.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />The labour of the righteous tendeth to life: the fruit of the wicked to sin.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />He is in the way of life that keepeth instruction: but he that refuseth reproof erreth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">erreth: or, causeth to err</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />He that hideth hatred with lying lips, and he that uttereth a slander, is a fool.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />In the multitude of words there wanteth not sin: but he that refraineth his lips is wise.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />The tongue of the just is as choice silver: the heart of the wicked is little worth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />The lips of the righteous feed many: but fools die for want of wisdom.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">of wisdom: Heb. of heart</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />The blessing of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, it maketh rich, and he addeth no sorrow with it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />It is as sport to a fool to do mischief: but a man of understanding hath wisdom.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />The fear of the wicked, it shall come upon him: but the desire of the righteous shall be granted.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />As the whirlwind passeth, so is the wicked no more: but the righteous is an everlasting foundation.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />As vinegar to the teeth, and as smoke to the eyes, so is the sluggard to them that send him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />The fear of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> prolongeth days: but the years of the wicked shall be shortened.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">prolongeth: Heb. addeth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />The hope of the righteous shall be gladness: but the expectation of the wicked shall perish.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />The way of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is strength to the upright: but destruction shall be to the workers of iniquity.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />The righteous shall never be removed: but the wicked shall not inhabit the earth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />The mouth of the just bringeth forth wisdom: but the froward tongue shall be cut out.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />The lips of the righteous know what is acceptable: but the mouth of the wicked speaketh frowardness.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">frowardness: Heb. frowardnesses</char></note></para>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />A false balance is abomination to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>: but a just weight is his delight.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">A false…: Heb. Balances of deceit</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">just…: Heb. perfect stone</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />When pride cometh, then cometh shame: but with the lowly is wisdom.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />The integrity of the upright shall guide them: but the perverseness of transgressors shall destroy them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Riches profit not in the day of wrath: but righteousness delivereth from death.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />The righteousness of the perfect shall direct his way: but the wicked shall fall by his own wickedness.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">direct: Heb. rectify</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />The righteousness of the upright shall deliver them: but transgressors shall be taken in their own naughtiness.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />When a wicked man dieth, his expectation shall perish: and the hope of unjust men perisheth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />The righteous is delivered out of trouble, and the wicked cometh in his stead.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />An hypocrite with his mouth destroyeth his neighbour: but through knowledge shall the just be delivered.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />When it goeth well with the righteous, the city rejoiceth: and when the wicked perish, there is shouting.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />By the blessing of the upright the city is exalted: but it is overthrown by the mouth of the wicked.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />He that is void of wisdom despiseth his neighbour: but a man of understanding holdeth his peace.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">void…: Heb. destitute of heart</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />A talebearer revealeth secrets: but he that is of a faithful spirit concealeth the matter.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">A talebearer: Heb. He that walketh, being a talebearer</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Where no counsel is, the people fall: but in the multitude of counsellors there is safety.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />He that is surety for a stranger shall smart for it: and he that hateth suretiship is sure.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">smart: Heb. be sore broken</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">suretiship: Heb. those that strike hands</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />A gracious woman retaineth honour: and strong men retain riches.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />The merciful man doeth good to his own soul: but he that is cruel troubleth his own flesh.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />The wicked worketh a deceitful work: but to him that soweth righteousness shall be a sure reward.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />As righteousness tendeth to life: so he that pursueth evil pursueth it to his own death.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />They that are of a froward heart are abomination to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>: but such as are upright in their way are his delight.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />Though hand join in hand, the wicked shall not be unpunished: but the seed of the righteous shall be delivered.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />As a jewel of gold in a swine's snout, so is a fair woman which is without discretion.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">is without: Heb. departeth from</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />The desire of the righteous is only good: but the expectation of the wicked is wrath.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />There is that scattereth, and yet increaseth; and there is that withholdeth more than is meet, but it tendeth to poverty.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />The liberal soul shall be made fat: and he that watereth shall be watered also himself.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">liberal…: Heb. soul of blessing</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />He that withholdeth corn, the people shall curse him: but blessing shall be upon the head of him that selleth it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />He that diligently seeketh good procureth favour: but he that seeketh mischief, it shall come unto him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />He that trusteth in his riches shall fall: but the righteous shall flourish as a branch.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />He that troubleth his own house shall inherit the wind: and the fool shall be servant to the wise of heart.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />The fruit of the righteous is a tree of life; and he that winneth souls is wise.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">winneth: Heb. taketh</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />Behold, the righteous shall be recompensed in the earth: much more the wicked and the sinner.</para>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Whoso loveth instruction loveth knowledge: but he that hateth reproof is brutish.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />A good man obtaineth favour of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>: but a man of wicked devices will he condemn.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />A man shall not be established by wickedness: but the root of the righteous shall not be moved.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />A virtuous woman is a crown to her husband: but she that maketh ashamed is as rottenness in his bones.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />The thoughts of the righteous are right: but the counsels of the wicked are deceit.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />The words of the wicked are to lie in wait for blood: but the mouth of the upright shall deliver them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />The wicked are overthrown, and are not: but the house of the righteous shall stand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />A man shall be commended according to his wisdom: but he that is of a perverse heart shall be despised.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">of a…: Heb. perverse of heart</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />He that is despised, and hath a servant, is better than he that honoureth himself, and lacketh bread.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />A righteous man regardeth the life of his beast: but the tender mercies of the wicked are cruel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">tender…: or, bowels</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />He that tilleth his land shall be satisfied with bread: but he that followeth vain persons is void of understanding.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />The wicked desireth the net of evil men: but the root of the righteous yieldeth fruit.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the net: or, the fortress</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />The wicked is snared by the transgression of his lips: but the just shall come out of trouble.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">The wicked…: Heb. The snare of the wicked is in the transgression of lips</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />A man shall be satisfied with good by the fruit of his mouth: and the recompence of a man's hands shall be rendered unto him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />The way of a fool is right in his own eyes: but he that hearkeneth unto counsel is wise.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />A fool's wrath is presently known: but a prudent man covereth shame.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">presently: Heb. in that day</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />He that speaketh truth sheweth forth righteousness: but a false witness deceit.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />There is that speaketh like the piercings of a sword: but the tongue of the wise is health.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />The lip of truth shall be established for ever: but a lying tongue is but for a moment.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />Deceit is in the heart of them that imagine evil: but to the counsellors of peace is joy.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />There shall no evil happen to the just: but the wicked shall be filled with mischief.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Lying lips are abomination to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>: but they that deal truly are his delight.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />A prudent man concealeth knowledge: but the heart of fools proclaimeth foolishness.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />The hand of the diligent shall bear rule: but the slothful shall be under tribute.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">slothful: or, deceitful</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Heaviness in the heart of man maketh it stoop: but a good word maketh it glad.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />The righteous is more excellent than his neighbour: but the way of the wicked seduceth them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">excellent: or, abundant</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />The slothful man roasteth not that which he took in hunting: but the substance of a diligent man is precious.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />In the way of righteousness is life; and in the pathway thereof there is no death.</para>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />A wise son heareth his father's instruction: but a scorner heareth not rebuke.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />A man shall eat good by the fruit of his mouth: but the soul of the transgressors shall eat violence.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />He that keepeth his mouth keepeth his life: but he that openeth wide his lips shall have destruction.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />The soul of the sluggard desireth, and hath nothing: but the soul of the diligent shall be made fat.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />A righteous man hateth lying: but a wicked man is loathsome, and cometh to shame.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Righteousness keepeth him that is upright in the way: but wickedness overthroweth the sinner.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the sinner: Heb. sin</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />There is that maketh himself rich, yet hath nothing: there is that maketh himself poor, yet hath great riches.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />The ransom of a man's life are his riches: but the poor heareth not rebuke.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />The light of the righteous rejoiceth: but the lamp of the wicked shall be put out.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">lamp: or, candle</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Only by pride cometh contention: but with the well advised is wisdom.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Wealth gotten by vanity shall be diminished: but he that gathereth by labour shall increase.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">by labour: Heb. with the hand</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Hope deferred maketh the heart sick: but when the desire cometh, it is a tree of life.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Whoso despiseth the word shall be destroyed: but he that feareth the commandment shall be rewarded.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">shall be rewarded: or, shall be in peace</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The law of the wise is a fountain of life, to depart from the snares of death.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Good understanding giveth favour: but the way of transgressors is hard.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Every prudent man dealeth with knowledge: but a fool layeth open his folly.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">layeth…: Heb. spreadeth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />A wicked messenger falleth into mischief: but a faithful ambassador is health.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">a faithful…: Heb. an ambassador of faithfulness</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Poverty and shame shall be to him that refuseth instruction: but he that regardeth reproof shall be honoured.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />The desire accomplished is sweet to the soul: but it is abomination to fools to depart from evil.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />He that walketh with wise men shall be wise: but a companion of fools shall be destroyed.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">destroyed: Heb. broken</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />Evil pursueth sinners: but to the righteous good shall be repayed.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />A good man leaveth an inheritance to his children's children: and the wealth of the sinner is laid up for the just.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Much food is in the tillage of the poor: but there is that is destroyed for want of judgment.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />He that spareth his rod hateth his son: but he that loveth him chasteneth him betimes.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />The righteous eateth to the satisfying of his soul: but the belly of the wicked shall want.</para>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Every wise woman buildeth her house: but the foolish plucketh it down with her hands.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />He that walketh in his uprightness feareth the <char style="nd">Lord</char>: but he that is perverse in his ways despiseth him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />In the mouth of the foolish is a rod of pride: but the lips of the wise shall preserve them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Where no oxen are, the crib is clean: but much increase is by the strength of the ox.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />A faithful witness will not lie: but a false witness will utter lies.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />A scorner seeketh wisdom, and findeth it not: but knowledge is easy unto him that understandeth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Go from the presence of a foolish man, when thou perceivest not in him the lips of knowledge.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />The wisdom of the prudent is to understand his way: but the folly of fools is deceit.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Fools make a mock at sin: but among the righteous there is favour.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />The heart knoweth his own bitterness; and a stranger doth not intermeddle with his joy.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">his own…: Heb. the bitterness of his soul</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />The house of the wicked shall be overthrown: but the tabernacle of the upright shall flourish.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />There is a way which seemeth right unto a man, but the end thereof are the ways of death.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Even in laughter the heart is sorrowful; and the end of that mirth is heaviness.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The backslider in heart shall be filled with his own ways: and a good man shall be satisfied from himself.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />The simple believeth every word: but the prudent man looketh well to his going.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />A wise man feareth, and departeth from evil: but the fool rageth, and is confident.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />He that is soon angry dealeth foolishly: and a man of wicked devices is hated.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />The simple inherit folly: but the prudent are crowned with knowledge.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />The evil bow before the good; and the wicked at the gates of the righteous.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />The poor is hated even of his own neighbour: but the rich hath many friends.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the rich…: Heb. many are the lovers of the rich</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />He that despiseth his neighbour sinneth: but he that hath mercy on the poor, happy is he.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Do they not err that devise evil? but mercy and truth shall be to them that devise good.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />In all labour there is profit: but the talk of the lips tendeth only to penury.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />The crown of the wise is their riches: but the foolishness of fools is folly.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />A true witness delivereth souls: but a deceitful witness speaketh lies.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />In the fear of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is strong confidence: and his children shall have a place of refuge.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />The fear of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is a fountain of life, to depart from the snares of death.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />In the multitude of people is the king's honour: but in the want of people is the destruction of the prince.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />He that is slow to wrath is of great understanding: but he that is hasty of spirit exalteth folly.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">hasty…: Heb. short of spirit</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />A sound heart is the life of the flesh: but envy the rottenness of the bones.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />He that oppresseth the poor reproacheth his Maker: but he that honoureth him hath mercy on the poor.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />The wicked is driven away in his wickedness: but the righteous hath hope in his death.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />Wisdom resteth in the heart of him that hath understanding: but that which is in the midst of fools is made known.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />Righteousness exalteth a nation: but sin is a reproach to any people.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">to any…: Heb. to nations</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />The king's favour is toward a wise servant: but his wrath is against him that causeth shame.</para>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />A soft answer turneth away wrath: but grievous words stir up anger.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />The tongue of the wise useth knowledge aright: but the mouth of fools poureth out foolishness.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">poureth: Heb. belcheth, or, bubbleth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />The eyes of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> are in every place, beholding the evil and the good.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />A wholesome tongue is a tree of life: but perverseness therein is a breach in the spirit.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">A wholesome…: Heb. The healing of the tongue</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />A fool despiseth his father's instruction: but he that regardeth reproof is prudent.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />In the house of the righteous is much treasure: but in the revenues of the wicked is trouble.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />The lips of the wise disperse knowledge: but the heart of the foolish doeth not so.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />The sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>: but the prayer of the upright is his delight.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />The way of the wicked is an abomination unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char>: but he loveth him that followeth after righteousness.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Correction is grievous unto him that forsaketh the way: and he that hateth reproof shall die.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Correction: or, Instruction</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Hell and destruction are before the <char style="nd">Lord</char>: how much more then the hearts of the children of men?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />A scorner loveth not one that reproveth him: neither will he go unto the wise.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />A merry heart maketh a cheerful countenance: but by sorrow of the heart the spirit is broken.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The heart of him that hath understanding seeketh knowledge: but the mouth of fools feedeth on foolishness.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />All the days of the afflicted are evil: but he that is of a merry heart hath a continual feast.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Better is little with the fear of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> than great treasure and trouble therewith.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Better is a dinner of herbs where love is, than a stalled ox and hatred therewith.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />A wrathful man stirreth up strife: but he that is slow to anger appeaseth strife.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />The way of the slothful man is as an hedge of thorns: but the way of the righteous is made plain.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">is made…: Heb. is raised up as a causey</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />A wise son maketh a glad father: but a foolish man despiseth his mother.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />Folly is joy to him that is destitute of wisdom: but a man of understanding walketh uprightly.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">destitute…: Heb. void of heart</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Without counsel purposes are disappointed: but in the multitude of counsellors they are established.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />A man hath joy by the answer of his mouth: and a word spoken in due season, how good is it!<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">due…: Heb. his season</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />The way of life is above to the wise, that he may depart from hell beneath.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will destroy the house of the proud: but he will establish the border of the widow.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />The thoughts of the wicked are an abomination to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>: but the words of the pure are pleasant words.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">pleasant…: Heb. words of pleasantness</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />He that is greedy of gain troubleth his own house; but he that hateth gifts shall live.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />The heart of the righteous studieth to answer: but the mouth of the wicked poureth out evil things.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is far from the wicked: but he heareth the prayer of the righteous.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />The light of the eyes rejoiceth the heart: and a good report maketh the bones fat.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />The ear that heareth the reproof of life abideth among the wise.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />He that refuseth instruction despiseth his own soul: but he that heareth reproof getteth understanding.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">instruction: or, correction</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">heareth: or, obeyeth</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">getteth…: Heb. possesseth an heart</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />The fear of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is the instruction of wisdom; and before honour is humility.</para>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The preparations of the heart in man, and the answer of the tongue, is from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">preparations: or, disposings</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />All the ways of a man are clean in his own eyes; but the <char style="nd">Lord</char> weigheth the spirits.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Commit thy works unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and thy thoughts shall be established.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Commit: Heb. Roll</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> hath made all things for himself: yea, even the wicked for the day of evil.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Every one that is proud in heart is an abomination to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>: though hand join in hand, he shall not be unpunished.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">unpunished: Heb. held innocent</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />By mercy and truth iniquity is purged: and by the fear of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> men depart from evil.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />When a man's ways please the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, he maketh even his enemies to be at peace with him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Better is a little with righteousness than great revenues without right.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />A man's heart deviseth his way: but the <char style="nd">Lord</char> directeth his steps.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />A divine sentence is in the lips of the king: his mouth transgresseth not in judgment.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">A divine…: Heb. Divination</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />A just weight and balance are the <char style="nd">Lord's</char>: all the weights of the bag are his work.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the weights: Heb. the stones</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />It is an abomination to kings to commit wickedness: for the throne is established by righteousness.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Righteous lips are the delight of kings; and they love him that speaketh right.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The wrath of a king is as messengers of death: but a wise man will pacify it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />In the light of the king's countenance is life; and his favour is as a cloud of the latter rain.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />How much better is it to get wisdom than gold! and to get understanding rather to be chosen than silver!</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />The highway of the upright is to depart from evil: he that keepeth his way preserveth his soul.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Pride goeth before destruction, and an haughty spirit before a fall.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />Better it is to be of an humble spirit with the lowly, than to divide the spoil with the proud.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />He that handleth a matter wisely shall find good: and whoso trusteth in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, happy is he.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">handleth…: or, understandeth a matter</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />The wise in heart shall be called prudent: and the sweetness of the lips increaseth learning.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Understanding is a wellspring of life unto him that hath it: but the instruction of fools is folly.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />The heart of the wise teacheth his mouth, and addeth learning to his lips.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">teacheth: Heb. maketh wise</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Pleasant words are as an honeycomb, sweet to the soul, and health to the bones.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />There is a way that seemeth right unto a man, but the end thereof are the ways of death.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />He that laboureth laboureth for himself; for his mouth craveth it of him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">He…: Heb. The soul of him that</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">craveth…: Heb. boweth unto him</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />An ungodly man diggeth up evil: and in his lips there is as a burning fire.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">An…: Heb. A man of Belial</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />A froward man soweth strife: and a whisperer separateth chief friends.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">soweth: Heb. sendeth forth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />A violent man enticeth his neighbour, and leadeth him into the way that is not good.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />He shutteth his eyes to devise froward things: moving his lips he bringeth evil to pass.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />The hoary head is a crown of glory, if it be found in the way of righteousness.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />He that is slow to anger is better than the mighty; and he that ruleth his spirit than he that taketh a city.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />The lot is cast into the lap; but the whole disposing thereof is of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Better is a dry morsel, and quietness therewith, than an house full of sacrifices with strife.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">sacrifices: or, good cheer</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />A wise servant shall have rule over a son that causeth shame, and shall have part of the inheritance among the brethren.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />The fining pot is for silver, and the furnace for gold: but the <char style="nd">Lord</char> trieth the hearts.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />A wicked doer giveth heed to false lips; and a liar giveth ear to a naughty tongue.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Whoso mocketh the poor reproacheth his Maker: and he that is glad at calamities shall not be unpunished.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">unpunished: Heb. held innocent</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Children's children are the crown of old men; and the glory of children are their fathers.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Excellent speech becometh not a fool: much less do lying lips a prince.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Excellent…: Heb. A lip of excellency</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">lying…: Heb. a lip of lying</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />A gift is as a precious stone in the eyes of him that hath it: whithersoever it turneth, it prospereth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">a precious…: Heb. a stone of grace</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />He that covereth a transgression seeketh love; but he that repeateth a matter separateth very friends.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">seeketh: or, procureth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />A reproof entereth more into a wise man than an hundred stripes into a fool.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">entereth…: or, aweth more a wise man, than to strike a fool an hundred times</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />An evil man seeketh only rebellion: therefore a cruel messenger shall be sent against him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Let a bear robbed of her whelps meet a man, rather than a fool in his folly.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Whoso rewardeth evil for good, evil shall not depart from his house.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The beginning of strife is as when one letteth out water: therefore leave off contention, before it be meddled with.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />He that justifieth the wicked, and he that condemneth the just, even they both are abomination to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Wherefore is there a price in the hand of a fool to get wisdom, seeing he hath no heart to it?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />A friend loveth at all times, and a brother is born for adversity.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />A man void of understanding striketh hands, and becometh surety in the presence of his friend.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">understanding: Heb. heart</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />He loveth transgression that loveth strife: and he that exalteth his gate seeketh destruction.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />He that hath a froward heart findeth no good: and he that hath a perverse tongue falleth into mischief.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">He that hath a froward…: Heb. The froward of heart</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />He that begetteth a fool doeth it to his sorrow: and the father of a fool hath no joy.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />A merry heart doeth good like a medicine: but a broken spirit drieth the bones.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">like: or, to</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />A wicked man taketh a gift out of the bosom to pervert the ways of judgment.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Wisdom is before him that hath understanding; but the eyes of a fool are in the ends of the earth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />A foolish son is a grief to his father, and bitterness to her that bare him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />Also to punish the just is not good, nor to strike princes for equity.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />He that hath knowledge spareth his words: and a man of understanding is of an excellent spirit.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">an…: or, a cool</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Even a fool, when he holdeth his peace, is counted wise: and he that shutteth his lips is esteemed a man of understanding.</para>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Through desire a man, having separated himself, seeketh and intermeddleth with all wisdom.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Through…: or, He that separateth himself seeketh according to his desire, and intermeddleth in every business</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />A fool hath no delight in understanding, but that his heart may discover itself.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />When the wicked cometh, then cometh also contempt, and with ignominy reproach.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />The words of a man's mouth are as deep waters, and the wellspring of wisdom as a flowing brook.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />It is not good to accept the person of the wicked, to overthrow the righteous in judgment.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />A fool's lips enter into contention, and his mouth calleth for strokes.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />A fool's mouth is his destruction, and his lips are the snare of his soul.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />The words of a talebearer are as wounds, and they go down into the innermost parts of the belly.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">talebearer: or, whisperer</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">as wounds: or, like as when men are wounded</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">innermost…: Heb. chambers</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />He also that is slothful in his work is brother to him that is a great waster.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />The name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is a strong tower: the righteous runneth into it, and is safe.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">safe: Heb. set aloft</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />The rich man's wealth is his strong city, and as an high wall in his own conceit.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Before destruction the heart of man is haughty, and before honour is humility.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />He that answereth a matter before he heareth it, it is folly and shame unto him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">answereth…: Heb. returneth a word</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The spirit of a man will sustain his infirmity; but a wounded spirit who can bear?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />The heart of the prudent getteth knowledge; and the ear of the wise seeketh knowledge.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />A man's gift maketh room for him, and bringeth him before great men.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />He that is first in his own cause seemeth just; but his neighbour cometh and searcheth him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />The lot causeth contentions to cease, and parteth between the mighty.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />A brother offended is harder to be won than a strong city: and their contentions are like the bars of a castle.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />A man's belly shall be satisfied with the fruit of his mouth; and with the increase of his lips shall he be filled.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />Death and life are in the power of the tongue: and they that love it shall eat the fruit thereof.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Whoso findeth a wife findeth a good thing, and obtaineth favour of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />The poor useth entreaties; but the rich answereth roughly.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />A man that hath friends must shew himself friendly: and there is a friend that sticketh closer than a brother.</para>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Better is the poor that walketh in his integrity, than he that is perverse in his lips, and is a fool.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Also, that the soul be without knowledge, it is not good; and he that hasteth with his feet sinneth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />The foolishness of man perverteth his way: and his heart fretteth against the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Wealth maketh many friends; but the poor is separated from his neighbour.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />A false witness shall not be unpunished, and he that speaketh lies shall not escape.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">unpunished: Heb. held innocent</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Many will entreat the favour of the prince: and every man is a friend to him that giveth gifts.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">him…: Heb. a man of gifts</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />All the brethren of the poor do hate him: how much more do his friends go far from him? he pursueth them with words, yet they are wanting to him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />He that getteth wisdom loveth his own soul: he that keepeth understanding shall find good.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">wisdom: Heb. an heart</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />A false witness shall not be unpunished, and he that speaketh lies shall perish.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Delight is not seemly for a fool; much less for a servant to have rule over princes.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />The discretion of a man deferreth his anger; and it is his glory to pass over a transgression.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">discretion: or, prudence</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />The king's wrath is as the roaring of a lion; but his favour is as dew upon the grass.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />A foolish son is the calamity of his father: and the contentions of a wife are a continual dropping.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />House and riches are the inheritance of fathers: and a prudent wife is from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Slothfulness casteth into a deep sleep; and an idle soul shall suffer hunger.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />He that keepeth the commandment keepeth his own soul; but he that despiseth his ways shall die.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />He that hath pity upon the poor lendeth unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char>; and that which he hath given will he pay him again.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">that which…: or, his deed</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Chasten thy son while there is hope, and let not thy soul spare for his crying.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">for…: or, to his destruction: or, to cause him to die</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />A man of great wrath shall suffer punishment: for if thou deliver him, yet thou must do it again.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">do: Heb. add</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />Hear counsel, and receive instruction, that thou mayest be wise in thy latter end.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />There are many devices in a man's heart; nevertheless the counsel of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, that shall stand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />The desire of a man is his kindness: and a poor man is better than a liar.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />The fear of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> tendeth to life: and he that hath it shall abide satisfied; he shall not be visited with evil.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />A slothful man hideth his hand in his bosom, and will not so much as bring it to his mouth again.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Smite a scorner, and the simple will beware: and reprove one that hath understanding, and he will understand knowledge.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">will beware: Heb. will be cunning</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />He that wasteth his father, and chaseth away his mother, is a son that causeth shame, and bringeth reproach.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Cease, my son, to hear the instruction that causeth to err from the words of knowledge.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />An ungodly witness scorneth judgment: and the mouth of the wicked devoureth iniquity.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">An…: Heb. A witness of Belial</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Judgments are prepared for scorners, and stripes for the back of fools.</para>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Wine is a mocker, strong drink is raging: and whosoever is deceived thereby is not wise.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />The fear of a king is as the roaring of a lion: whoso provoketh him to anger sinneth against his own soul.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />It is an honour for a man to cease from strife: but every fool will be meddling.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />The sluggard will not plow by reason of the cold; therefore shall he beg in harvest, and have nothing.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">cold: or, winter</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Counsel in the heart of man is like deep water; but a man of understanding will draw it out.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Most men will proclaim every one his own goodness: but a faithful man who can find?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">goodness: or, bounty</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />The just man walketh in his integrity: his children are blessed after him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />A king that sitteth in the throne of judgment scattereth away all evil with his eyes.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Who can say, I have made my heart clean, I am pure from my sin?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Divers weights, and divers measures, both of them are alike abomination to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Divers weights: Heb. A stone and a stone</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">divers measures: Heb. an ephah and an ephah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Even a child is known by his doings, whether his work be pure, and whether it be right.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />The hearing ear, and the seeing eye, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> hath made even both of them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Love not sleep, lest thou come to poverty; open thine eyes, and thou shalt be satisfied with bread.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />It is naught, it is naught, saith the buyer: but when he is gone his way, then he boasteth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />There is gold, and a multitude of rubies: but the lips of knowledge are a precious jewel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Take his garment that is surety for a stranger: and take a pledge of him for a strange woman.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Bread of deceit is sweet to a man; but afterwards his mouth shall be filled with gravel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">deceit: Heb. lying, or, falsehood</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Every purpose is established by counsel: and with good advice make war.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />He that goeth about as a talebearer revealeth secrets: therefore meddle not with him that flattereth with his lips.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">flattereth: or, enticeth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />Whoso curseth his father or his mother, his lamp shall be put out in obscure darkness.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">lamp: or, candle</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />An inheritance may be gotten hastily at the beginning; but the end thereof shall not be blessed.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Say not thou, I will recompense evil; but wait on the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and he shall save thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Divers weights are an abomination unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char>; and a false balance is not good.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">a false…: Heb. balance of deceit</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Man's goings are of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>; how can a man then understand his own way?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />It is a snare to the man who devoureth that which is holy, and after vows to make enquiry.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />A wise king scattereth the wicked, and bringeth the wheel over them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />The spirit of man is the candle of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, searching all the inward parts of the belly.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">candle: or, lamp</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Mercy and truth preserve the king: and his throne is upholden by mercy.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />The glory of young men is their strength: and the beauty of old men is the gray head.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />The blueness of a wound cleanseth away evil: so do stripes the inward parts of the belly.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">cleanseth…: Heb. is a purging medicine against</char></note></para>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The king's heart is in the hand of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, as the rivers of water: he turneth it whithersoever he will.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Every way of a man is right in his own eyes: but the <char style="nd">Lord</char> pondereth the hearts.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />To do justice and judgment is more acceptable to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> than sacrifice.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />An high look, and a proud heart, and the plowing of the wicked, is sin.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">An…: Heb. Haughtiness of eyes</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the plowing: or, the light</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />The thoughts of the diligent tend only to plenteousness; but of every one that is hasty only to want.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />The getting of treasures by a lying tongue is a vanity tossed to and fro of them that seek death.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />The robbery of the wicked shall destroy them; because they refuse to do judgment.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">destroy…: Heb. saw them, or, dwell with them</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />The way of man is froward and strange: but as for the pure, his work is right.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />It is better to dwell in a corner of the housetop, than with a brawling woman in a wide house.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">a brawling…: Heb. a woman of contentions</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">a wide…: Heb. an house of society</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />The soul of the wicked desireth evil: his neighbour findeth no favour in his eyes.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">findeth…: Heb. is not favoured</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />When the scorner is punished, the simple is made wise: and when the wise is instructed, he receiveth knowledge.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />The righteous man wisely considereth the house of the wicked: but God overthroweth the wicked for their wickedness.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Whoso stoppeth his ears at the cry of the poor, he also shall cry himself, but shall not be heard.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />A gift in secret pacifieth anger: and a reward in the bosom strong wrath.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />It is joy to the just to do judgment: but destruction shall be to the workers of iniquity.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />The man that wandereth out of the way of understanding shall remain in the congregation of the dead.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />He that loveth pleasure shall be a poor man: he that loveth wine and oil shall not be rich.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">pleasure: or, sport</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />The wicked shall be a ransom for the righteous, and the transgressor for the upright.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />It is better to dwell in the wilderness, than with a contentious and an angry woman.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">in…: Heb. in the land of the desert</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />There is treasure to be desired and oil in the dwelling of the wise; but a foolish man spendeth it up.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />He that followeth after righteousness and mercy findeth life, righteousness, and honour.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />A wise man scaleth the city of the mighty, and casteth down the strength of the confidence thereof.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Whoso keepeth his mouth and his tongue keepeth his soul from troubles.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Proud and haughty scorner is his name, who dealeth in proud wrath.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">in proud…: Heb. in the wrath of pride</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />The desire of the slothful killeth him; for his hands refuse to labour.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />He coveteth greedily all the day long: but the righteous giveth and spareth not.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />The sacrifice of the wicked is abomination: how much more, when he bringeth it with a wicked mind?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">with…: Heb. in wickedness?</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />A false witness shall perish: but the man that heareth speaketh constantly.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">A…: Heb. A witness of lies</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />A wicked man hardeneth his face: but as for the upright, he directeth his way.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">directeth: or, considereth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />There is no wisdom nor understanding nor counsel against the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />The horse is prepared against the day of battle: but safety is of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">safety: or, victory</char></note></para>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />A good name is rather to be chosen than great riches, and loving favour rather than silver and gold.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">loving…: or, favour is better than, etc.</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />The rich and poor meet together: the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is the maker of them all.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />A prudent man foreseeth the evil, and hideth himself: but the simple pass on, and are punished.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />By humility and the fear of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> are riches, and honour, and life.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">By…: or, The reward of humility, etc.</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Thorns and snares are in the way of the froward: he that doth keep his soul shall be far from them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Train up a child in the way he should go: and when he is old, he will not depart from it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Train…: or, Catechise</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">in…: Heb. in his way</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />The rich ruleth over the poor, and the borrower is servant to the lender.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the lender: Heb. the man that lendeth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />He that soweth iniquity shall reap vanity: and the rod of his anger shall fail.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the rod…: or, with the rod of his anger he shall be consumed</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />He that hath a bountiful eye shall be blessed; for he giveth of his bread to the poor.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">He that…: Heb. Good of eye</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Cast out the scorner, and contention shall go out; yea, strife and reproach shall cease.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />He that loveth pureness of heart, for the grace of his lips the king shall be his friend.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">for…: or, and hath grace in his lips</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />The eyes of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> preserve knowledge, and he overthroweth the words of the transgressor.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the words: or, the matters</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />The slothful man saith, There is a lion without, I shall be slain in the streets.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The mouth of strange women is a deep pit: he that is abhorred of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> shall fall therein.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Foolishness is bound in the heart of a child; but the rod of correction shall drive it far from him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />He that oppresseth the poor to increase his riches, and he that giveth to the rich, shall surely come to want.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Bow down thine ear, and hear the words of the wise, and apply thine heart unto my knowledge.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />For it is a pleasant thing if thou keep them within thee; they shall withal be fitted in thy lips.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">within…: Heb. in thy belly</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />That thy trust may be in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, I have made known to thee this day, even to thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">even…: or, trust thou also</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />Have not I written to thee excellent things in counsels and knowledge,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />That I might make thee know the certainty of the words of truth; that thou mightest answer the words of truth to them that send unto thee?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">to them…: or, to those that send thee?</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Rob not the poor, because he is poor: neither oppress the afflicted in the gate:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />For the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will plead their cause, and spoil the soul of those that spoiled them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Make no friendship with an angry man; and with a furious man thou shalt not go:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Lest thou learn his ways, and get a snare to thy soul.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />Be not thou one of them that strike hands, or of them that are sureties for debts.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />If thou hast nothing to pay, why should he take away thy bed from under thee?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Remove not the ancient landmark, which thy fathers have set.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">landmark: or, bound</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Seest thou a man diligent in his business? he shall stand before kings; he shall not stand before mean men.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">mean…: Heb. obscure men</char></note></para>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />When thou sittest to eat with a ruler, consider diligently what is before thee:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />And put a knife to thy throat, if thou be a man given to appetite.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Be not desirous of his dainties: for they are deceitful meat.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Labour not to be rich: cease from thine own wisdom.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Wilt thou set thine eyes upon that which is not? for riches certainly make themselves wings; they fly away as an eagle toward heaven.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">set…: Heb. cause thine eyes to fly upon</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Eat thou not the bread of him that hath an evil eye, neither desire thou his dainty meats:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />For as he thinketh in his heart, so is he: Eat and drink, saith he to thee; but his heart is not with thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />The morsel which thou hast eaten shalt thou vomit up, and lose thy sweet words.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Speak not in the ears of a fool: for he will despise the wisdom of thy words.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Remove not the old landmark; and enter not into the fields of the fatherless:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">landmark: or, bound</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />For their redeemer is mighty; he shall plead their cause with thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Apply thine heart unto instruction, and thine ears to the words of knowledge.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Withhold not correction from the child: for if thou beatest him with the rod, he shall not die.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Thou shalt beat him with the rod, and shalt deliver his soul from hell.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />My son, if thine heart be wise, my heart shall rejoice, even mine.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">even…: or, even I will rejoice</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Yea, my reins shall rejoice, when thy lips speak right things.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Let not thine heart envy sinners: but be thou in the fear of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> all the day long.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />For surely there is an end; and thine expectation shall not be cut off.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">end: or, reward</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />Hear thou, my son, and be wise, and guide thine heart in the way.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />Be not among winebibbers; among riotous eaters of flesh:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">of flesh: Heb. of their flesh</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />For the drunkard and the glutton shall come to poverty: and drowsiness shall clothe a man with rags.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Hearken unto thy father that begat thee, and despise not thy mother when she is old.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Buy the truth, and sell it not; also wisdom, and instruction, and understanding.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />The father of the righteous shall greatly rejoice: and he that begetteth a wise child shall have joy of him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Thy father and thy mother shall be glad, and she that bare thee shall rejoice.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />My son, give me thine heart, and let thine eyes observe my ways.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />For a whore is a deep ditch; and a strange woman is a narrow pit.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />She also lieth in wait as for a prey, and increaseth the transgressors among men.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">as for…: or, as a robber</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Who hath woe? who hath sorrow? who hath contentions? who hath babbling? who hath wounds without cause? who hath redness of eyes?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />They that tarry long at the wine; they that go to seek mixed wine.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />Look not thou upon the wine when it is red, when it giveth his colour in the cup, when it moveth itself aright.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />At the last it biteth like a serpent, and stingeth like an adder.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">an…: or, a cockatrice</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />Thine eyes shall behold strange women, and thine heart shall utter perverse things.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />Yea, thou shalt be as he that lieth down in the midst of the sea, or as he that lieth upon the top of a mast.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the midst…: Heb. the heart of the sea</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />They have stricken me, shalt thou say, and I was not sick; they have beaten me, and I felt it not: when shall I awake? I will seek it yet again.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">I felt…: Heb. I knew it not</char></note></para>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Be not thou envious against evil men, neither desire to be with them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />For their heart studieth destruction, and their lips talk of mischief.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Through wisdom is an house builded; and by understanding it is established:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />And by knowledge shall the chambers be filled with all precious and pleasant riches.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />A wise man is strong; yea, a man of knowledge increaseth strength.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">is strong: Heb. is in strength</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">increaseth…: Heb. strengtheneth might</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />For by wise counsel thou shalt make thy war: and in multitude of counsellors there is safety.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Wisdom is too high for a fool: he openeth not his mouth in the gate.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />He that deviseth to do evil shall be called a mischievous person.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />The thought of foolishness is sin: and the scorner is an abomination to men.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />If thou faint in the day of adversity, thy strength is small.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">small: Heb. narrow</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />If thou forbear to deliver them that are drawn unto death, and those that are ready to be slain;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />If thou sayest, Behold, we knew it not; doth not he that pondereth the heart consider it? and he that keepeth thy soul, doth not he know it? and shall not he render to every man according to his works?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />My son, eat thou honey, because it is good; and the honeycomb, which is sweet to thy taste:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">to…: Heb. upon thy palate</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />So shall the knowledge of wisdom be unto thy soul: when thou hast found it, then there shall be a reward, and thy expectation shall not be cut off.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Lay not wait, O wicked man, against the dwelling of the righteous; spoil not his resting place:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />For a just man falleth seven times, and riseth up again: but the wicked shall fall into mischief.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Rejoice not when thine enemy falleth, and let not thine heart be glad when he stumbleth:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Lest the <char style="nd">Lord</char> see it, and it displease him, and he turn away his wrath from him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">it displease…: Heb. it be evil in his eyes</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />Fret not thyself because of evil men, neither be thou envious at the wicked;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Fret…: or, Keep not company with the wicked</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />For there shall be no reward to the evil man; the candle of the wicked shall be put out.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">candle: or, lamp</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />My son, fear thou the <char style="nd">Lord</char> and the king: and meddle not with them that are given to change:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">them…: Heb. changers</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />For their calamity shall rise suddenly; and who knoweth the ruin of them both?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />These things also belong to the wise. It is not good to have respect of persons in judgment.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />He that saith unto the wicked, Thou art righteous; him shall the people curse, nations shall abhor him:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />But to them that rebuke him shall be delight, and a good blessing shall come upon them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">a good…: Heb. a blessing of good</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />Every man shall kiss his lips that giveth a right answer.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">that…: Heb. that answereth right words</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Prepare thy work without, and make it fit for thyself in the field; and afterwards build thine house.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Be not a witness against thy neighbour without cause; and deceive not with thy lips.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Say not, I will do so to him as he hath done to me: I will render to the man according to his work.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />I went by the field of the slothful, and by the vineyard of the man void of understanding;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />And, lo, it was all grown over with thorns, and nettles had covered the face thereof, and the stone wall thereof was broken down.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />Then I saw, and considered it well: I looked upon it, and received instruction.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">considered…: Heb. set my heart</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />Yet a little sleep, a little slumber, a little folding of the hands to sleep:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />So shall thy poverty come as one that travelleth; and thy want as an armed man.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">an…: Heb. a man of shield</char></note></para>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />These are also proverbs of Solomon, which the men of Hezekiah king of Judah copied out.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />It is the glory of God to conceal a thing: but the honour of kings is to search out a matter.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />The heaven for height, and the earth for depth, and the heart of kings is unsearchable.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">is…: Heb. there is no searching</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Take away the dross from the silver, and there shall come forth a vessel for the finer.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Take away the wicked from before the king, and his throne shall be established in righteousness.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Put not forth thyself in the presence of the king, and stand not in the place of great men:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Put…: Heb. Set not out thy glory</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />For better it is that it be said unto thee, Come up hither; than that thou shouldest be put lower in the presence of the prince whom thine eyes have seen.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Go not forth hastily to strive, lest thou know not what to do in the end thereof, when thy neighbour hath put thee to shame.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Debate thy cause with thy neighbour himself; and discover not a secret to another:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">a secret…: or, the secret of</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Lest he that heareth it put thee to shame, and thine infamy turn not away.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />A word fitly spoken is like apples of gold in pictures of silver.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">fitly…: Heb. spoken upon his wheels</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />As an earring of gold, and an ornament of fine gold, so is a wise reprover upon an obedient ear.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />As the cold of snow in the time of harvest, so is a faithful messenger to them that send him: for he refresheth the soul of his masters.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Whoso boasteth himself of a false gift is like clouds and wind without rain.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">of a…: Heb. in a gift of falsehood</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />By long forbearing is a prince persuaded, and a soft tongue breaketh the bone.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Hast thou found honey? eat so much as is sufficient for thee, lest thou be filled therewith, and vomit it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Withdraw thy foot from thy neighbour's house; lest he be weary of thee, and so hate thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Withdraw…: or, Let thy foot be seldom in</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">weary…: Heb. full of thee</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />A man that beareth false witness against his neighbour is a maul, and a sword, and a sharp arrow.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />Confidence in an unfaithful man in time of trouble is like a broken tooth, and a foot out of joint.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />As he that taketh away a garment in cold weather, and as vinegar upon nitre, so is he that singeth songs to an heavy heart.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />If thine enemy be hungry, give him bread to eat; and if he be thirsty, give him water to drink:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />For thou shalt heap coals of fire upon his head, and the <char style="nd">Lord</char> shall reward thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />The north wind driveth away rain: so doth an angry countenance a backbiting tongue.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">driveth…: or, bringeth forth rain: so doth a backbiting tongue an angry countenance</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />It is better to dwell in the corner of the housetop, than with a brawling woman and in a wide house.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />As cold waters to a thirsty soul, so is good news from a far country.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />A righteous man falling down before the wicked is as a troubled fountain, and a corrupt spring.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />It is not good to eat much honey: so for men to search their own glory is not glory.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />He that hath no rule over his own spirit is like a city that is broken down, and without walls.</para>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />As snow in summer, and as rain in harvest, so honour is not seemly for a fool.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />As the bird by wandering, as the swallow by flying, so the curse causeless shall not come.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />A whip for the horse, a bridle for the ass, and a rod for the fool's back.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Answer not a fool according to his folly, lest thou also be like unto him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Answer a fool according to his folly, lest he be wise in his own conceit.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">conceit: Heb. eyes</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />He that sendeth a message by the hand of a fool cutteth off the feet, and drinketh damage.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">damage: or, violence</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />The legs of the lame are not equal: so is a parable in the mouth of fools.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">are…: Heb. are lifted up</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />As he that bindeth a stone in a sling, so is he that giveth honour to a fool.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">bindeth…: or, putteth a precious stone in an heap of stones</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />As a thorn goeth up into the hand of a drunkard, so is a parable in the mouth of fools.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />The great God that formed all things both rewardeth the fool, and rewardeth transgressors.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">The great…: or, A great man grieveth all, and he hireth the fool, he hireth also transgressors</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />As a dog returneth to his vomit, so a fool returneth to his folly.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">returneth to his folly: Heb. iterateth his folly</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Seest thou a man wise in his own conceit? there is more hope of a fool than of him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />The slothful man saith, There is a lion in the way; a lion is in the streets.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />As the door turneth upon his hinges, so doth the slothful upon his bed.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />The slothful hideth his hand in his bosom; it grieveth him to bring it again to his mouth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">it grieveth…: or, he is weary</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />The sluggard is wiser in his own conceit than seven men that can render a reason.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />He that passeth by, and meddleth with strife belonging not to him, is like one that taketh a dog by the ears.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">meddleth: or, is enraged</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />As a mad man who casteth firebrands, arrows, and death,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">firebrands: Heb. flames, or, sparks</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />So is the man that deceiveth his neighbour, and saith, Am not I in sport?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />Where no wood is, there the fire goeth out: so where there is no talebearer, the strife ceaseth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Where no…: Heb. Without wood</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">talebearer: or, whisperer</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">ceaseth: Heb. is silent</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />As coals are to burning coals, and wood to fire; so is a contentious man to kindle strife.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />The words of a talebearer are as wounds, and they go down into the innermost parts of the belly.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">innermost…: Heb. chambers</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Burning lips and a wicked heart are like a potsherd covered with silver dross.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />He that hateth dissembleth with his lips, and layeth up deceit within him;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">dissembleth: or, is known</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />When he speaketh fair, believe him not: for there are seven abominations in his heart.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">speaketh…: Heb. maketh his voice gracious</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />Whose hatred is covered by deceit, his wickedness shall be shewed before the whole congregation.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">by…: or, in secret</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Whoso diggeth a pit shall fall therein: and he that rolleth a stone, it will return upon him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />A lying tongue hateth those that are afflicted by it; and a flattering mouth worketh ruin.</para>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Boast not thyself of to morrow; for thou knowest not what a day may bring forth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">to…: Heb. to morrow day</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Let another man praise thee, and not thine own mouth; a stranger, and not thine own lips.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />A stone is heavy, and the sand weighty; but a fool's wrath is heavier than them both.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">heavy: Heb. heaviness</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Wrath is cruel, and anger is outrageous; but who is able to stand before envy?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Wrath…: Heb. Wrath is cruelty, and anger an overflowing</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">envy: or, jealousy?</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Open rebuke is better than secret love.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Faithful are the wounds of a friend; but the kisses of an enemy are deceitful.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">deceitful: or, earnest, or, frequent</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />The full soul loatheth an honeycomb; but to the hungry soul every bitter thing is sweet.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">loatheth: Heb. treadeth under foot</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />As a bird that wandereth from her nest, so is a man that wandereth from his place.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Ointment and perfume rejoice the heart: so doth the sweetness of a man's friend by hearty counsel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">by…: Heb. from the counsel of the soul</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Thine own friend, and thy father's friend, forsake not; neither go into thy brother's house in the day of thy calamity: for better is a neighbour that is near than a brother far off.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />My son, be wise, and make my heart glad, that I may answer him that reproacheth me.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />A prudent man foreseeth the evil, and hideth himself; but the simple pass on, and are punished.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Take his garment that is surety for a stranger, and take a pledge of him for a strange woman.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />He that blesseth his friend with a loud voice, rising early in the morning, it shall be counted a curse to him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />A continual dropping in a very rainy day and a contentious woman are alike.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Whosoever hideth her hideth the wind, and the ointment of his right hand, which bewrayeth itself.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Iron sharpeneth iron; so a man sharpeneth the countenance of his friend.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Whoso keepeth the fig tree shall eat the fruit thereof: so he that waiteth on his master shall be honoured.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />As in water face answereth to face, so the heart of man to man.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />Hell and destruction are never full; so the eyes of man are never satisfied.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">never: Heb. not</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />As the fining pot for silver, and the furnace for gold; so is a man to his praise.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Though thou shouldest bray a fool in a mortar among wheat with a pestle, yet will not his foolishness depart from him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Be thou diligent to know the state of thy flocks, and look well to thy herds.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">look…: Heb. set thy heart</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />For riches are not for ever: and doth the crown endure to every generation?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">riches: Heb. strength</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">to…: Heb. to generation and generation?</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />The hay appeareth, and the tender grass sheweth itself, and herbs of the mountains are gathered.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />The lambs are for thy clothing, and the goats are the price of the field.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />And thou shalt have goats' milk enough for thy food, for the food of thy household, and for the maintenance for thy maidens.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">maintenance: Heb. life</char></note></para>
  <chapter number="28" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The wicked flee when no man pursueth: but the righteous are bold as a lion.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />For the transgression of a land many are the princes thereof: but by a man of understanding and knowledge the state thereof shall be prolonged.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">by…: or, by men of understanding and wisdom shall they likewise be prolonged</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />A poor man that oppresseth the poor is like a sweeping rain which leaveth no food.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">which…: Heb. without food</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />They that forsake the law praise the wicked: but such as keep the law contend with them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Evil men understand not judgment: but they that seek the <char style="nd">Lord</char> understand all things.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Better is the poor that walketh in his uprightness, than he that is perverse in his ways, though he be rich.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Whoso keepeth the law is a wise son: but he that is a companion of riotous men shameth his father.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">is a companion…: or, feedeth gluttons</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />He that by usury and unjust gain increaseth his substance, he shall gather it for him that will pity the poor.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">unjust…: Heb. by increase</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />He that turneth away his ear from hearing the law, even his prayer shall be abomination.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Whoso causeth the righteous to go astray in an evil way, he shall fall himself into his own pit: but the upright shall have good things in possession.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />The rich man is wise in his own conceit; but the poor that hath understanding searcheth him out.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">own…: Heb. eyes</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />When righteous men do rejoice, there is great glory: but when the wicked rise, a man is hidden.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">hidden: or, sought for</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />He that covereth his sins shall not prosper: but whoso confesseth and forsaketh them shall have mercy.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Happy is the man that feareth alway: but he that hardeneth his heart shall fall into mischief.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />As a roaring lion, and a ranging bear; so is a wicked ruler over the poor people.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />The prince that wanteth understanding is also a great oppressor: but he that hateth covetousness shall prolong his days.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />A man that doeth violence to the blood of any person shall flee to the pit; let no man stay him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Whoso walketh uprightly shall be saved: but he that is perverse in his ways shall fall at once.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />He that tilleth his land shall have plenty of bread: but he that followeth after vain persons shall have poverty enough.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />A faithful man shall abound with blessings: but he that maketh haste to be rich shall not be innocent.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">innocent: or, unpunished</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />To have respect of persons is not good: for for a piece of bread that man will transgress.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />He that hasteth to be rich hath an evil eye, and considereth not that poverty shall come upon him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">hasteth…: or, hath and evil eye hasteth to be rich</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />He that rebuketh a man afterwards shall find more favour than he that flattereth with the tongue.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Whoso robbeth his father or his mother, and saith, It is no transgression; the same is the companion of a destroyer.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">a destroyer: Heb. a man destroying</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />He that is of a proud heart stirreth up strife: but he that putteth his trust in the <char style="nd">Lord</char> shall be made fat.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />He that trusteth in his own heart is a fool: but whoso walketh wisely, he shall be delivered.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />He that giveth unto the poor shall not lack: but he that hideth his eyes shall have many a curse.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />When the wicked rise, men hide themselves: but when they perish, the righteous increase.</para>
  <chapter number="29" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />He, that being often reproved hardeneth his neck, shall suddenly be destroyed, and that without remedy.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">He…: Heb. A man of reproofs</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />When the righteous are in authority, the people rejoice: but when the wicked beareth rule, the people mourn.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">in…: or, increased</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Whoso loveth wisdom rejoiceth his father: but he that keepeth company with harlots spendeth his substance.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />The king by judgment establisheth the land: but he that receiveth gifts overthroweth it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">he…: Heb. a man of oblations</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />A man that flattereth his neighbour spreadeth a net for his feet.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />In the transgression of an evil man there is a snare: but the righteous doth sing and rejoice.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />The righteous considereth the cause of the poor: but the wicked regardeth not to know it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Scornful men bring a city into a snare: but wise men turn away wrath.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">bring…: or, set a city on fire</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />If a wise man contendeth with a foolish man, whether he rage or laugh, there is no rest.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />The bloodthirsty hate the upright: but the just seek his soul.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">The bloodthirsty: Heb. Men of blood</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />A fool uttereth all his mind: but a wise man keepeth it in till afterwards.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />If a ruler hearken to lies, all his servants are wicked.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />The poor and the deceitful man meet together: the <char style="nd">Lord</char> lighteneth both their eyes.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the deceitful…: or, the usurer</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The king that faithfully judgeth the poor, his throne shall be established for ever.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />The rod and reproof give wisdom: but a child left to himself bringeth his mother to shame.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />When the wicked are multiplied, transgression increaseth: but the righteous shall see their fall.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Correct thy son, and he shall give thee rest; yea, he shall give delight unto thy soul.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Where there is no vision, the people perish: but he that keepeth the law, happy is he.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">perish: or, is made naked</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />A servant will not be corrected by words: for though he understand he will not answer.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />Seest thou a man that is hasty in his words? there is more hope of a fool than of him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">words: or, matters?</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />He that delicately bringeth up his servant from a child shall have him become his son at the length.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />An angry man stirreth up strife, and a furious man aboundeth in transgression.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />A man's pride shall bring him low: but honour shall uphold the humble in spirit.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Whoso is partner with a thief hateth his own soul: he heareth cursing, and bewrayeth it not.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />The fear of man bringeth a snare: but whoso putteth his trust in the <char style="nd">Lord</char> shall be safe.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">safe: Heb. set on high</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />Many seek the ruler's favour; but every man's judgment cometh from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the ruler's…: Heb. the face of a ruler</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />An unjust man is an abomination to the just: and he that is upright in the way is abomination to the wicked.</para>
  <chapter number="30" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The words of Agur the son of Jakeh, even the prophecy: the man spake unto Ithiel, even unto Ithiel and Ucal,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Surely I am more brutish than any man, and have not the understanding of a man.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />I neither learned wisdom, nor have the knowledge of the holy.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">have: Heb. know</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Who hath ascended up into heaven, or descended? who hath gathered the wind in his fists? who hath bound the waters in a garment? who hath established all the ends of the earth? what is his name, and what is his son's name, if thou canst tell?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Every word of God is pure: he is a shield unto them that put their trust in him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">pure: Heb. purified</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Add thou not unto his words, lest he reprove thee, and thou be found a liar.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Two things have I required of thee; deny me them not before I die:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">deny…: Heb. withhold not from me</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Remove far from me vanity and lies: give me neither poverty nor riches; feed me with food convenient for me:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">convenient…: Heb. of my allowance</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Lest I be full, and deny thee, and say, Who is the <char style="nd">Lord</char>? or lest I be poor, and steal, and take the name of my God in vain.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">deny…: Heb. belie thee</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Accuse not a servant unto his master, lest he curse thee, and thou be found guilty.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Accuse…: Heb. Hurt not with thy tongue</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />There is a generation that curseth their father, and doth not bless their mother.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />There is a generation that are pure in their own eyes, and yet is not washed from their filthiness.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />There is a generation, O how lofty are their eyes! and their eyelids are lifted up.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />There is a generation, whose teeth are as swords, and their jaw teeth as knives, to devour the poor from off the earth, and the needy from among men.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />The horseleach hath two daughters, crying, Give, give. There are three things that are never satisfied, yea, four things say not, It is enough:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">It is…: Heb. Wealth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />The grave; and the barren womb; the earth that is not filled with water; and the fire that saith not, It is enough.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />The eye that mocketh at his father, and despiseth to obey his mother, the ravens of the valley shall pick it out, and the young eagles shall eat it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the valley: or, the brook</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />There be three things which are too wonderful for me, yea, four which I know not:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />The way of an eagle in the air; the way of a serpent upon a rock; the way of a ship in the midst of the sea; and the way of a man with a maid.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">midst: Heb. heart</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />Such is the way of an adulterous woman; she eateth, and wipeth her mouth, and saith, I have done no wickedness.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />For three things the earth is disquieted, and for four which it cannot bear:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />For a servant when he reigneth; and a fool when he is filled with meat;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />For an odious woman when she is married; and an handmaid that is heir to her mistress.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />There be four things which are little upon the earth, but they are exceeding wise:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">exceeding…: Heb. wise, made wise</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />The ants are a people not strong, yet they prepare their meat in the summer;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />The conies are but a feeble folk, yet make they their houses in the rocks;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />The locusts have no king, yet go they forth all of them by bands;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">by…: Heb. gathered together</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />The spider taketh hold with her hands, and is in kings' palaces.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />There be three things which go well, yea, four are comely in going:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />A lion which is strongest among beasts, and turneth not away for any;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />A greyhound; an he goat also; and a king, against whom there is no rising up.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">greyhound: or, horse: Heb. girt in the loins</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />If thou hast done foolishly in lifting up thyself, or if thou hast thought evil, lay thine hand upon thy mouth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />Surely the churning of milk bringeth forth butter, and the wringing of the nose bringeth forth blood: so the forcing of wrath bringeth forth strife.</para>
  <chapter number="31" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The words of king Lemuel, the prophecy that his mother taught him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />What, my son? and what, the son of my womb? and what, the son of my vows?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Give not thy strength unto women, nor thy ways to that which destroyeth kings.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />It is not for kings, O Lemuel, it is not for kings to drink wine; nor for princes strong drink:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Lest they drink, and forget the law, and pervert the judgment of any of the afflicted.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">pervert: Heb. alter</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">of any…: Heb. of all the sons of affliction</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Give strong drink unto him that is ready to perish, and wine unto those that be of heavy hearts.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">of…: Heb. bitter of soul</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Let him drink, and forget his poverty, and remember his misery no more.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Open thy mouth for the dumb in the cause of all such as are appointed to destruction.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">such…: Heb. the sons of destruction</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Open thy mouth, judge righteously, and plead the cause of the poor and needy.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Who can find a virtuous woman? for her price is far above rubies.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />The heart of her husband doth safely trust in her, so that he shall have no need of spoil.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />She will do him good and not evil all the days of her life.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />She seeketh wool, and flax, and worketh willingly with her hands.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />She is like the merchants' ships; she bringeth her food from afar.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />She riseth also while it is yet night, and giveth meat to her household, and a portion to her maidens.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />She considereth a field, and buyeth it: with the fruit of her hands she planteth a vineyard.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">buyeth: Heb. taketh</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />She girdeth her loins with strength, and strengtheneth her arms.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />She perceiveth that her merchandise is good: her candle goeth not out by night.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">She…: Heb. She tasteth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />She layeth her hands to the spindle, and her hands hold the distaff.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />She stretcheth out her hand to the poor; yea, she reacheth forth her hands to the needy.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">She…: Heb. She spreadeth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />She is not afraid of the snow for her household: for all her household are clothed with scarlet.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">scarlet: or, double garments</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />She maketh herself coverings of tapestry; her clothing is silk and purple.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Her husband is known in the gates, when he sitteth among the elders of the land.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />She maketh fine linen, and selleth it; and delivereth girdles unto the merchant.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Strength and honour are her clothing; and she shall rejoice in time to come.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />She openeth her mouth with wisdom; and in her tongue is the law of kindness.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />She looketh well to the ways of her household, and eateth not the bread of idleness.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Her children arise up, and call her blessed; her husband also, and he praiseth her.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Many daughters have done virtuously, but thou excellest them all.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">have…: or, have gotten riches</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />Favour is deceitful, and beauty is vain: but a woman that feareth the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, she shall be praised.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />Give her of the fruit of her hands; and let her own works praise her in the gates.</para>
</usx>