<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="2.0">
  <book code="1CH" style="id">1 Chronicles</book>
  <para style="mt">1 Chronicles</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Adam, Seth, Enosh,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Kenan, Mahalaleel, Jared,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Enoch, Methuselah, Lamech,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Noah, Shem, Ham, and Japheth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />The sons of Japheth; Gomer, and Magog, and Madai, and Javan, and Tubal, and Meshech, and Tiras.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />And the sons of Gomer; Ashkenaz, and Riphath, and Togarmah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Riphath: or, Diphath as it is in some copies</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And the sons of Javan; Elishah, and Tarshish, Kittim, and Dodanim.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Dodanim: or, Rodanim, according to some copies</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />The sons of Ham; Cush, and Mizraim, Put, and Canaan.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />And the sons of Cush; Seba, and Havilah, and Sabtah, and Raamah, and Sabtecha. And the sons of Raamah; Sheba, and Dedan.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />And Cush begat Nimrod: he began to be mighty upon the earth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />And Mizraim begat Ludim, and Anamim, and Lehabim, and Naphtuhim,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />And Pathrusim, and Casluhim, (of whom came the Philistines,) and Caphtorim.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />And Canaan begat Zidon his firstborn, and Heth,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The Jebusite also, and the Amorite, and the Girgashite,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />And the Hivite, and the Arkite, and the Sinite,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />And the Arvadite, and the Zemarite, and the Hamathite.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />The sons of Shem; Elam, and Asshur, and Arphaxad, and Lud, and Aram, and Uz, and Hul, and Gether, and Meshech.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Meshech: or, Mash</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />And Arphaxad begat Shelah, and Shelah begat Eber.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />And unto Eber were born two sons: the name of the one was Peleg; because in his days the earth was divided: and his brother's name was Joktan.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Peleg: that is, division</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And Joktan begat Almodad, and Sheleph, and Hazarmaveth, and Jerah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />Hadoram also, and Uzal, and Diklah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />And Ebal, and Abimael, and Sheba,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />And Ophir, and Havilah, and Jobab. All these were the sons of Joktan.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Shem, Arphaxad, Shelah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Eber, Peleg, Reu,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />Serug, Nahor, Terah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Abram; the same is Abraham.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />The sons of Abraham; Isaac, and Ishmael.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />These are their generations: The firstborn of Ishmael, Nebaioth; then Kedar, and Adbeel, and Mibsam,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />Mishma, and Dumah, Massa, Hadad, and Tema,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Hadad: also called, Hadar</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />Jetur, Naphish, and Kedemah. These are the sons of Ishmael.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />Now the sons of Keturah, Abraham's concubine: she bare Zimran, and Jokshan, and Medan, and Midian, and Ishbak, and Shuah. And the sons of Jokshan; Sheba, and Dedan.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />And the sons of Midian; Ephah, and Epher, and Hanoch, and Abida, and Eldaah. All these are the sons of Keturah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />And Abraham begat Isaac. The sons of Isaac; Esau and Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />The sons of Esau; Eliphaz, Reuel, and Jeush, and Jaalam, and Korah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" />The sons of Eliphaz; Teman, and Omar, Zephi, and Gatam, Kenaz, and Timna, and Amalek.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Zephi: or, Zepho</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" />The sons of Reuel; Nahath, Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />And the sons of Seir; Lotan, and Shobal, and Zibeon, and Anah, and Dishon, and Ezer, and Dishan.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" />And the sons of Lotan; Hori, and Homam: and Timna was Lotan's sister.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Homam: or, Hemam</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" />The sons of Shobal; Alian, and Manahath, and Ebal, Shephi, and Onam. And the sons of Zibeon; Aiah, and Anah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Alian: also called, Alvan</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shephi: also called, Shepho</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" />The sons of Anah; Dishon. And the sons of Dishon; Amram, and Eshban, and Ithran, and Cheran.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Amram: or, Hemdan</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" />The sons of Ezer; Bilhan, and Zaavan, and Jakan. The sons of Dishan; Uz, and Aran.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Jakan: or, Akan</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" />Now these are the kings that reigned in the land of Edom before any king reigned over the children of Israel; Bela the son of Beor: and the name of his city was Dinhabah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" />And when Bela was dead, Jobab the son of Zerah of Bozrah reigned in his stead.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" />And when Jobab was dead, Husham of the land of the Temanites reigned in his stead.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" />And when Husham was dead, Hadad the son of Bedad, which smote Midian in the field of Moab, reigned in his stead: and the name of his city was Avith.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" />And when Hadad was dead, Samlah of Masrekah reigned in his stead.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" />And when Samlah was dead, Shaul of Rehoboth by the river reigned in his stead.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" />And when Shaul was dead, Baal–hanan the son of Achbor reigned in his stead.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" />And when Baal–hanan was dead, Hadad reigned in his stead: and the name of his city was Pau; and his wife's name was Mehetabel, the daughter of Matred, the daughter of Mezahab.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Hadad: or, Hadar</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Pai: or, Pau</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="51" style="v" />Hadad died also. And the dukes of Edom were; duke Timnah, duke Alvah, duke Jetheth,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="52" style="v" />Duke Aholibamah, duke Elah, duke Pinon,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="53" style="v" />Duke Kenaz, duke Teman, duke Mibzar,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" />Duke Magdiel, duke Iram. These are the dukes of Edom.</para>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />These are the sons of Israel; Reuben, Simeon, Levi, and Judah, Issachar, and Zebulun,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Israel: or, Jacob</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Dan, Joseph, and Benjamin, Naphtali, Gad, and Asher.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />The sons of Judah; Er, and Onan, and Shelah: which three were born unto him of the daughter of Shua the Canaanitess. And Er, the firstborn of Judah, was evil in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>; and he slew him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />And Tamar his daughter in law bare him Pharez and Zerah. All the sons of Judah were five.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />The sons of Pharez; Hezron, and Hamul.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />And the sons of Zerah; Zimri, and Ethan, and Heman, and Calcol, and Dara: five of them in all.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Zimri: or, Zabdi</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Dara: or, Darda</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And the sons of Carmi; Achar, the troubler of Israel, who transgressed in the thing accursed.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Achar: or, Achan</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And the sons of Ethan; Azariah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />The sons also of Hezron, that were born unto him; Jerahmeel, and Ram, and Chelubai.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Ram: Gr. Aram</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Chelubai: or, Caleb</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />And Ram begat Amminadab; and Amminadab begat Nahshon, prince of the children of Judah;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />And Nahshon begat Salma, and Salma begat Boaz,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Salma: also called, Salmon</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />And Boaz begat Obed, and Obed begat Jesse,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />And Jesse begat his firstborn Eliab, and Abinadab the second, and Shimma the third,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shimma: or, Shammah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Nethaneel the fourth, Raddai the fifth,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Ozem the sixth, David the seventh:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Whose sisters were Zeruiah, and Abigail. And the sons of Zeruiah; Abishai, and Joab, and Asahel, three.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />And Abigail bare Amasa: and the father of Amasa was Jether the Ishmaelite.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Jether…: also called, Ithra an Israelite</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />And Caleb the son of Hezron begat children of Azubah his wife, and of Jerioth: her sons are these; Jesher, and Shobab, and Ardon.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />And when Azubah was dead, Caleb took unto him Ephrath, which bare him Hur.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And Hur begat Uri, and Uri begat Bezaleel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />And afterward Hezron went in to the daughter of Machir the father of Gilead, whom he married when he was threescore years old; and she bare him Segub.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">married: Heb. took</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />And Segub begat Jair, who had three and twenty cities in the land of Gilead.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />And he took Geshur, and Aram, with the towns of Jair, from them, with Kenath, and the towns thereof, even threescore cities. All these belonged to the sons of Machir the father of Gilead.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />And after that Hezron was dead in Caleb–ephratah, then Abiah Hezron's wife bare him Ashur the father of Tekoa.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />And the sons of Jerahmeel the firstborn of Hezron were, Ram the firstborn, and Bunah, and Oren, and Ozem, and Ahijah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />Jerahmeel had also another wife, whose name was Atarah; she was the mother of Onam.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />And the sons of Ram the firstborn of Jerahmeel were, Maaz, and Jamin, and Eker.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />And the sons of Onam were, Shammai, and Jada. And the sons of Shammai; Nadab, and Abishur.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />And the name of the wife of Abishur was Abihail, and she bare him Ahban, and Molid.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />And the sons of Nadab; Seled, and Appaim: but Seled died without children.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />And the sons of Appaim; Ishi. And the sons of Ishi; Sheshan. And the children of Sheshan; Ahlai.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />And the sons of Jada the brother of Shammai; Jether, and Jonathan: and Jether died without children.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />And the sons of Jonathan; Peleth, and Zaza. These were the sons of Jerahmeel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />Now Sheshan had no sons, but daughters. And Sheshan had a servant, an Egyptian, whose name was Jarha.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />And Sheshan gave his daughter to Jarha his servant to wife; and she bare him Attai.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" />And Attai begat Nathan, and Nathan begat Zabad,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" />And Zabad begat Ephlal, and Ephlal begat Obed,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />And Obed begat Jehu, and Jehu begat Azariah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" />And Azariah begat Helez, and Helez begat Eleasah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" />And Eleasah begat Sisamai, and Sisamai begat Shallum,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" />And Shallum begat Jekamiah, and Jekamiah begat Elishama.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" />Now the sons of Caleb the brother of Jerahmeel were, Mesha his firstborn, which was the father of Ziph; and the sons of Mareshah the father of Hebron.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" />And the sons of Hebron; Korah, and Tappuah, and Rekem, and Shema.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" />And Shema begat Raham, the father of Jorkoam: and Rekem begat Shammai.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" />And the son of Shammai was Maon: and Maon was the father of Beth–zur.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" />And Ephah, Caleb's concubine, bare Haran, and Moza, and Gazez: and Haran begat Gazez.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" />And the sons of Jahdai; Regem, and Jotham, and Geshan, and Pelet, and Ephah, and Shaaph.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" />Maachah, Caleb's concubine, bare Sheber, and Tirhanah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" />She bare also Shaaph the father of Madmannah, Sheva the father of Machbenah, and the father of Gibea: and the daughter of Caleb was Achsah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" />These were the sons of Caleb the son of Hur, the firstborn of Ephratah; Shobal the father of Kirjath–jearim,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Ephratah: also called, Ephreth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="51" style="v" />Salma the father of Beth–lehem, Hareph the father of Beth–gader.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="52" style="v" />And Shobal the father of Kirjath–jearim had sons; Haroeh, and half of the Manahethites.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Haroeh: or, Reaiah</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">half…: or, half of the Menuchites, or, Hatsi–ham–menuchoth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="53" style="v" />And the families of Kirjath–jearim; the Ithrites, and the Puhites, and the Shumathites, and the Mishraites; of them came the Zorathites, and the Eshtaulites.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" />The sons of Salma; Beth–lehem, and the Netophathites, Ataroth, the house of Joab, and half of the Manahethites, the Zorites.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Ataroth…: or, Atarites, or, crowns of the house of Joab</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="55" style="v" />And the families of the scribes which dwelt at Jabez; the Tirathites, the Shimeathites, and Suchathites. These are the Kenites that came of Hemath, the father of the house of Rechab.</para>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now these were the sons of David, which were born unto him in Hebron; the firstborn Amnon, of Ahinoam the Jezreelitess; the second Daniel, of Abigail the Carmelitess:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Daniel: or, Chileab</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />The third, Absalom the son of Maacah the daughter of Talmai king of Geshur: the fourth, Adonijah the son of Haggith:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />The fifth, Shephatiah of Abital: the sixth, Ithream by Eglah his wife.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />These six were born unto him in Hebron; and there he reigned seven years and six months: and in Jerusalem he reigned thirty and three years.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />And these were born unto him in Jerusalem; Shimea, and Shobab, and Nathan, and Solomon, four, of Bath–shua the daughter of Ammiel:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shimea: or, Shammua</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Bath–shua: or, Bath–sheba</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Ammiel: or, Eliam</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Ibhar also, and Elishama, and Eliphelet,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Elishama: also called, Elishua</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And Nogah, and Nepheg, and Japhia,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And Elishama, and Eliada, and Eliphelet, nine.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Eliada: or, Beeliada</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />These were all the sons of David, beside the sons of the concubines, and Tamar their sister.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />And Solomon's son was Rehoboam, Abia his son, Asa his son, Jehoshaphat his son,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Abia: or, Abijam</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Joram his son, Ahaziah his son, Joash his son,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Ahaziah: or, Azariah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Amaziah his son, Azariah his son, Jotham his son,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Azariah: or, Uzziah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Ahaz his son, Hezekiah his son, Manasseh his son,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Amon his son, Josiah his son.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />And the sons of Josiah were, the firstborn Johanan, the second Jehoiakim, the third Zedekiah, the fourth Shallum.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Johanan: or, Jehoahaz</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Jehoiakim: or, Eliakim</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Zedekiah: or, Mattaniah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />And the sons of Jehoiakim: Jeconiah his son, Zedekiah his son.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Jeconiah: also called, Jehoiachin or Coniah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />And the sons of Jeconiah; Assir, Salathiel his son,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Salathiel: Heb. Shealtiel</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Malchiram also, and Pedaiah, and Shenazar, Jecamiah, Hoshama, and Nedabiah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />And the sons of Pedaiah were, Zerubbabel, and Shimei: and the sons of Zerubbabel; Meshullam, and Hananiah, and Shelomith their sister:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And Hashubah, and Ohel, and Berechiah, and Hasadiah, Jushab–hesed, five.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />And the sons of Hananiah; Pelatiah, and Jesaiah: the sons of Rephaiah, the sons of Arnan, the sons of Obadiah, the sons of Shechaniah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />And the sons of Shechaniah; Shemaiah: and the sons of Shemaiah; Hattush, and Igeal, and Bariah, and Neariah, and Shaphat, six.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />And the sons of Neariah; Elioenai, and Hezekiah, and Azrikam, three.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Hezekiah: Heb. Hiskijah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />And the sons of Elioenai were, Hodaiah, and Eliashib, and Pelaiah, and Akkub, and Johanan, and Dalaiah, and Anani, seven.</para>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The sons of Judah; Pharez, Hezron, and Carmi, and Hur, and Shobal.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Carmi: also called, Chelubai or Caleb</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />And Reaiah the son of Shobal begat Jahath; and Jahath begat Ahumai, and Lahad. These are the families of the Zorathites.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Reaiah: or, Haroeh</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />And these were of the father of Etam; Jezreel, and Ishma, and Idbash: and the name of their sister was Hazelelponi:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />And Penuel the father of Gedor, and Ezer the father of Hushah. These are the sons of Hur, the firstborn of Ephratah, the father of Beth–lehem.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />And Ashur the father of Tekoa had two wives, Helah and Naarah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />And Naarah bare him Ahuzam, and Hepher, and Temeni, and Haahashtari. These were the sons of Naarah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And the sons of Helah were, Zereth, and Jezoar, and Ethnan.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And Coz begat Anub, and Zobebah, and the families of Aharhel the son of Harum.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />And Jabez was more honourable than his brethren: and his mother called his name Jabez, saying, Because I bare him with sorrow.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Jabez: that is, Sorrowful</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />And Jabez called on the God of Israel, saying, Oh that thou wouldest bless me indeed, and enlarge my coast, and that thine hand might be with me, and that thou wouldest keep me from evil, that it may not grieve me! And God granted him that which he requested.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Oh…: Heb. If thou wilt, etc.</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">keep…: Heb. do me</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />And Chelub the brother of Shuah begat Mehir, which was the father of Eshton.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />And Eshton begat Beth–rapha, and Paseah, and Tehinnah the father of Ir–nahash. These are the men of Rechah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Ir–nahash: or, the city of Nahash</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />And the sons of Kenaz; Othniel, and Seraiah: and the sons of Othniel; Hathath.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Hathath…: or, Hathath, and Meonothai, who begat, etc.</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />And Meonothai begat Ophrah: and Seraiah begat Joab, the father of the valley of Charashim; for they were craftsmen.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">valley: or, inhabitants of the valley</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Charashim: that is, craftsmen</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Hathath…: or, Hathath, and Meonothai, who begat, etc.</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />And the sons of Caleb the son of Jephunneh; Iru, Elah, and Naam: and the sons of Elah, even Kenaz.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">even Kenaz: or, Uknaz</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />And the sons of Jehaleleel; Ziph, and Ziphah, Tiria, and Asareel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />And the sons of Ezra were, Jether, and Mered, and Epher, and Jalon: and she bare Miriam, and Shammai, and Ishbah the father of Eshtemoa.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />And his wife Jehudijah bare Jered the father of Gedor, and Heber the father of Soco, and Jekuthiel the father of Zanoah. And these are the sons of Bithiah the daughter of Pharaoh, which Mered took.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Jehudijah: or, the Jewess</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />And the sons of his wife Hodiah the sister of Naham, the father of Keilah the Garmite, and Eshtemoa the Maachathite.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Hodiah: or, Jehudijah, mentioned before</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And the sons of Shimon were, Amnon, and Rinnah, Ben–hanan, and Tilon. And the sons of Ishi were, Zoheth, and Ben–zoheth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />The sons of Shelah the son of Judah were, Er the father of Lecah, and Laadah the father of Mareshah, and the families of the house of them that wrought fine linen, of the house of Ashbea,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />And Jokim, and the men of Chozeba, and Joash, and Saraph, who had the dominion in Moab, and Jashubi–lehem. And these are ancient things.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />These were the potters, and those that dwelt among plants and hedges: there they dwelt with the king for his work.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />The sons of Simeon were, Nemuel, and Jamin, Jarib, Zerah, and Shaul:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Nemuel: or, Jemuel</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Jarib, Zerah: or, Jachin Zohar</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Shallum his son, Mibsam his son, Mishma his son.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />And the sons of Mishma; Hamuel his son, Zacchur his son, Shimei his son.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />And Shimei had sixteen sons and six daughters; but his brethren had not many children, neither did all their family multiply, like to the children of Judah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">like…: Heb. unto</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />And they dwelt at Beer–sheba, and Moladah, and Hazar–shual,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />And at Bilhah, and at Ezem, and at Tolad,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Bilhah: or, Balah</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Tolad: or, Eltolad</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />And at Bethuel, and at Hormah, and at Ziklag,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />And at Beth–marcaboth, and Hazar–susim, and at Beth–biri, and at Shaaraim. These were their cities unto the reign of David.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Hazar–susim: or, Hazar–susah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />And their villages were, Etam, and Ain, Rimmon, and Tochen, and Ashan, five cities:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Etam: or, Ether</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />And all their villages that were round about the same cities, unto Baal. These were their habitations, and their genealogy.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Baal: or, Baalath–beer</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">their genealogy: or, as they divided themselves by nations among them</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />And Meshobab, and Jamlech, and Joshah the son of Amaziah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />And Joel, and Jehu the son of Josibiah, the son of Seraiah, the son of Asiel,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" />And Elioenai, and Jaakobah, and Jeshohaiah, and Asaiah, and Adiel, and Jesimiel, and Benaiah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" />And Ziza the son of Shiphi, the son of Allon, the son of Jedaiah, the son of Shimri, the son of Shemaiah;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />These mentioned by their names were princes in their families: and the house of their fathers increased greatly.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">mentioned: Heb. coming</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" />And they went to the entrance of Gedor, even unto the east side of the valley, to seek pasture for their flocks.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" />And they found fat pasture and good, and the land was wide, and quiet, and peaceable; for they of Ham had dwelt there of old.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" />And these written by name came in the days of Hezekiah king of Judah, and smote their tents, and the habitations that were found there, and destroyed them utterly unto this day, and dwelt in their rooms: because there was pasture there for their flocks.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" />And some of them, even of the sons of Simeon, five hundred men, went to mount Seir, having for their captains Pelatiah, and Neariah, and Rephaiah, and Uzziel, the sons of Ishi.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" />And they smote the rest of the Amalekites that were escaped, and dwelt there unto this day.</para>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now the sons of Reuben the firstborn of Israel, (for he was the firstborn; but, forasmuch as he defiled his father's bed, his birthright was given unto the sons of Joseph the son of Israel: and the genealogy is not to be reckoned after the birthright.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />For Judah prevailed above his brethren, and of him came the chief ruler; but the birthright was Joseph's:)<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">chief…: or, prince</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />The sons, I say, of Reuben the firstborn of Israel were, Hanoch, and Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />The sons of Joel; Shemaiah his son, Gog his son, Shimei his son,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Micah his son, Reaia his son, Baal his son,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Beerah his son, whom Tilgath–pilneser king of Assyria carried away captive: he was prince of the Reubenites.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Tilgath–pilneser: also called, Tiglath–pileser</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And his brethren by their families, when the genealogy of their generations was reckoned, were the chief, Jeiel, and Zechariah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And Bela the son of Azaz, the son of Shema, the son of Joel, who dwelt in Aroer, even unto Nebo and Baal–meon:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shema: or, Shemaiah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />And eastward he inhabited unto the entering in of the wilderness from the river Euphrates: because their cattle were multiplied in the land of Gilead.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />And in the days of Saul they made war with the Hagarites, who fell by their hand: and they dwelt in their tents throughout all the east land of Gilead.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">throughout…: Heb. upon all the face of the east</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />And the children of Gad dwelt over against them, in the land of Bashan unto Salecah:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Joel the chief, and Shapham the next, and Jaanai, and Shaphat in Bashan.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />And their brethren of the house of their fathers were, Michael, and Meshullam, and Sheba, and Jorai, and Jachan, and Zia, and Heber, seven.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />These are the children of Abihail the son of Huri, the son of Jaroah, the son of Gilead, the son of Michael, the son of Jeshishai, the son of Jahdo, the son of Buz;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Ahi the son of Abdiel, the son of Guni, chief of the house of their fathers.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />And they dwelt in Gilead in Bashan, and in her towns, and in all the suburbs of Sharon, upon their borders.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">their…: Heb. their goings forth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />All these were reckoned by genealogies in the days of Jotham king of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam king of Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />The sons of Reuben, and the Gadites, and half the tribe of Manasseh, of valiant men, men able to bear buckler and sword, and to shoot with bow, and skilful in war, were four and forty thousand seven hundred and threescore, that went out to the war.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">valiant…: Heb. sons of valour</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />And they made war with the Hagarites, with Jetur, and Naphish, and Nodab.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And they were helped against them, and the Hagarites were delivered into their hand, and all that were with them: for they cried to God in the battle, and he was entreated of them; because they put their trust in him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />And they took away their cattle; of their camels fifty thousand, and of sheep two hundred and fifty thousand, and of asses two thousand, and of men an hundred thousand.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">took…: Heb. led captive</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">men: Heb. souls of men</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />For there fell down many slain, because the war was of God. And they dwelt in their steads until the captivity.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />And the children of the half tribe of Manasseh dwelt in the land: they increased from Bashan unto Baal–hermon and Senir, and unto mount Hermon.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />And these were the heads of the house of their fathers, even Epher, and Ishi, and Eliel, and Azriel, and Jeremiah, and Hodaviah, and Jahdiel, mighty men of valour, famous men, and heads of the house of their fathers.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">famous…: Heb. men of names</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />And they transgressed against the God of their fathers, and went a whoring after the gods of the people of the land, whom God destroyed before them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />And the God of Israel stirred up the spirit of Pul king of Assyria, and the spirit of Tilgath–pilneser king of Assyria, and he carried them away, even the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half tribe of Manasseh, and brought them unto Halah, and Habor, and Hara, and to the river Gozan, unto this day.</para>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The sons of Levi; Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Gershon: or, Gershom</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />And the sons of Kohath; Amram, Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />And the children of Amram; Aaron, and Moses, and Miriam. The sons also of Aaron; Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Eleazar begat Phinehas, Phinehas begat Abishua,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />And Abishua begat Bukki, and Bukki begat Uzzi,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />And Uzzi begat Zerahiah, and Zerahiah begat Meraioth,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Meraioth begat Amariah, and Amariah begat Ahitub,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And Ahitub begat Zadok, and Zadok begat Ahimaaz,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />And Ahimaaz begat Azariah, and Azariah begat Johanan,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />And Johanan begat Azariah, (he it is that executed the priest's office in the temple that Solomon built in Jerusalem:)<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">in the temple: Heb. in the house</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />And Azariah begat Amariah, and Amariah begat Ahitub,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />And Ahitub begat Zadok, and Zadok begat Shallum,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shallum: or, Meshullam</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />And Shallum begat Hilkiah, and Hilkiah begat Azariah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />And Azariah begat Seraiah, and Seraiah begat Jehozadak,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />And Jehozadak went into captivity, when the <char style="nd">Lord</char> carried away Judah and Jerusalem by the hand of Nebuchadnezzar.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />The sons of Levi; Gershom, Kohath, and Merari.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Gershom: or, Gershon</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />And these be the names of the sons of Gershom; Libni, and Shimei.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />And the sons of Kohath were, Amram, and Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />The sons of Merari; Mahli, and Mushi. And these are the families of the Levites according to their fathers.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />Of Gershom; Libni his son, Jahath his son, Zimmah his son,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />Joah his son, Iddo his son, Zerah his son, Jeaterai his son.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Joah: or, Ethan</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Iddo: or, Adaiah</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Jeaterai: also called, Ethni</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />The sons of Kohath; Amminadab his son, Korah his son, Assir his son,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Amminadab: or, Izhar</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Elkanah his son, and Ebiasaph his son, and Assir his son,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Tahath his son, Uriel his son, Uzziah his son, and Shaul his son.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />And the sons of Elkanah; Amasai, and Ahimoth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />As for Elkanah: the sons of Elkanah; Zophai his son, and Nahath his son,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Zophai: or, Zuph</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Eliab his son, Jeroham his son, Elkanah his son.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />And the sons of Samuel; the firstborn Vashni, and Abiah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Vashni: called also Joel</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />The sons of Merari; Mahli, Libni his son, Shimei his son, Uzza his son,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />Shimea his son, Haggiah his son, Asaiah his son.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />And these are they whom David set over the service of song in the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, after that the ark had rest.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />And they ministered before the dwelling place of the tabernacle of the congregation with singing, until Solomon had built the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> in Jerusalem: and then they waited on their office according to their order.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />And these are they that waited with their children. Of the sons of the Kohathites: Heman a singer, the son of Joel, the son of Shemuel,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">waited: Heb. stood</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />The son of Elkanah, the son of Jeroham, the son of Eliel, the son of Toah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />The son of Zuph, the son of Elkanah, the son of Mahath, the son of Amasai,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" />The son of Elkanah, the son of Joel, the son of Azariah, the son of Zephaniah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" />The son of Tahath, the son of Assir, the son of Ebiasaph, the son of Korah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />The son of Izhar, the son of Kohath, the son of Levi, the son of Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" />And his brother Asaph, who stood on his right hand, even Asaph the son of Berechiah, the son of Shimea,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" />The son of Michael, the son of Baaseiah, the son of Malchiah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" />The son of Ethni, the son of Zerah, the son of Adaiah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" />The son of Ethan, the son of Zimmah, the son of Shimei,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" />The son of Jahath, the son of Gershom, the son of Levi.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" />And their brethren the sons of Merari stood on the left hand: Ethan the son of Kishi, the son of Abdi, the son of Malluch,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Kishi: or, Kushaiah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" />The son of Hashabiah, the son of Amaziah, the son of Hilkiah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" />The son of Amzi, the son of Bani, the son of Shamer,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" />The son of Mahli, the son of Mushi, the son of Merari, the son of Levi.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" />Their brethren also the Levites were appointed unto all manner of service of the tabernacle of the house of God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" />But Aaron and his sons offered upon the altar of the burnt offering, and on the altar of incense, and were appointed for all the work of the place most holy, and to make an atonement for Israel, according to all that Moses the servant of God had commanded.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" />And these are the sons of Aaron; Eleazar his son, Phinehas his son, Abishua his son,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="51" style="v" />Bukki his son, Uzzi his son, Zerahiah his son,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="52" style="v" />Meraioth his son, Amariah his son, Ahitub his son,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="53" style="v" />Zadok his son, Ahimaaz his son.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" />Now these are their dwelling places throughout their castles in their coasts, of the sons of Aaron, of the families of the Kohathites: for theirs was the lot.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="55" style="v" />And they gave them Hebron in the land of Judah, and the suburbs thereof round about it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="56" style="v" />But the fields of the city, and the villages thereof, they gave to Caleb the son of Jephunneh.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="57" style="v" />And to the sons of Aaron they gave the cities of Judah, namely, Hebron, the city of refuge, and Libnah with her suburbs, and Jattir, and Eshtemoa, with their suburbs,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="58" style="v" />And Hilen with her suburbs, Debir with her suburbs,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Hilen: or, Holon</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="59" style="v" />And Ashan with her suburbs, and Beth–shemesh with her suburbs:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Ashan: or, Ain</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="60" style="v" />And out of the tribe of Benjamin; Geba with her suburbs, and Alemeth with her suburbs, and Anathoth with her suburbs. All their cities throughout their families were thirteen cities.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Alemeth: or, Almon</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="61" style="v" />And unto the sons of Kohath, which were left of the family of that tribe, were cities given out of the half tribe, namely, out of the half tribe of Manasseh, by lot, ten cities.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="62" style="v" />And to the sons of Gershom throughout their families out of the tribe of Issachar, and out of the tribe of Asher, and out of the tribe of Naphtali, and out of the tribe of Manasseh in Bashan, thirteen cities.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="63" style="v" />Unto the sons of Merari were given by lot, throughout their families, out of the tribe of Reuben, and out of the tribe of Gad, and out of the tribe of Zebulun, twelve cities.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="64" style="v" />And the children of Israel gave to the Levites these cities with their suburbs.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="65" style="v" />And they gave by lot out of the tribe of the children of Judah, and out of the tribe of the children of Simeon, and out of the tribe of the children of Benjamin, these cities, which are called by their names.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="66" style="v" />And the residue of the families of the sons of Kohath had cities of their coasts out of the tribe of Ephraim.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="67" style="v" />And they gave unto them, of the cities of refuge, Shechem in mount Ephraim with her suburbs; they gave also Gezer with her suburbs,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="68" style="v" />And Jokmeam with her suburbs, and Beth–horon with her suburbs,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="69" style="v" />And Aijalon with her suburbs, and Gath–rimmon with her suburbs:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="70" style="v" />And out of the half tribe of Manasseh; Aner with her suburbs, and Bileam with her suburbs, for the family of the remnant of the sons of Kohath.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="71" style="v" />Unto the sons of Gershom were given out of the family of the half tribe of Manasseh, Golan in Bashan with her suburbs, and Ashtaroth with her suburbs:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="72" style="v" />And out of the tribe of Issachar; Kedesh with her suburbs, Daberath with her suburbs,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="73" style="v" />And Ramoth with her suburbs, and Anem with her suburbs:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="74" style="v" />And out of the tribe of Asher; Mashal with her suburbs, and Abdon with her suburbs,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="75" style="v" />And Hukok with her suburbs, and Rehob with her suburbs:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="76" style="v" />And out of the tribe of Naphtali; Kedesh in Galilee with her suburbs, and Hammon with her suburbs, and Kirjathaim with her suburbs.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="77" style="v" />Unto the rest of the children of Merari were given out of the tribe of Zebulun, Rimmon with her suburbs, Tabor with her suburbs:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="78" style="v" />And on the other side Jordan by Jericho, on the east side of Jordan, were given them out of the tribe of Reuben, Bezer in the wilderness with her suburbs, and Jahzah with her suburbs,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="79" style="v" />Kedemoth also with her suburbs, and Mephaath with her suburbs:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="80" style="v" />And out of the tribe of Gad; Ramoth in Gilead with her suburbs, and Mahanaim with her suburbs,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="81" style="v" />And Heshbon with her suburbs, and Jazer with her suburbs.</para>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now the sons of Issachar were, Tola, and Puah, Jashub, and Shimron, four.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />And the sons of Tola; Uzzi, and Rephaiah, and Jeriel, and Jahmai, and Jibsam, and Shemuel, heads of their father's house, to wit, of Tola: they were valiant men of might in their generations; whose number was in the days of David two and twenty thousand and six hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />And the sons of Uzzi; Izrahiah: and the sons of Izrahiah; Michael, and Obadiah, and Joel, Ishiah, five: all of them chief men.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />And with them, by their generations, after the house of their fathers, were bands of soldiers for war, six and thirty thousand men: for they had many wives and sons.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />And their brethren among all the families of Issachar were valiant men of might, reckoned in all by their genealogies fourscore and seven thousand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />The sons of Benjamin; Bela, and Becher, and Jediael, three.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And the sons of Bela; Ezbon, and Uzzi, and Uzziel, and Jerimoth, and Iri, five; heads of the house of their fathers, mighty men of valour; and were reckoned by their genealogies twenty and two thousand and thirty and four.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And the sons of Becher; Zemira, and Joash, and Eliezer, and Elioenai, and Omri, and Jerimoth, and Abiah, and Anathoth, and Alameth. All these are the sons of Becher.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />And the number of them, after their genealogy by their generations, heads of the house of their fathers, mighty men of valour, was twenty thousand and two hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />The sons also of Jediael; Bilhan: and the sons of Bilhan; Jeush, and Benjamin, and Ehud, and Chenaanah, and Zethan, and Tharshish, and Ahishahar.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />All these the sons of Jediael, by the heads of their fathers, mighty men of valour, were seventeen thousand and two hundred soldiers, fit to go out for war and battle.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Shuppim also, and Huppim, the children of Ir, and Hushim, the sons of Aher.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Ir: or, Iri</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Aher: or, Ahiram</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />The sons of Naphtali; Jahziel, and Guni, and Jezer, and Shallum, the sons of Bilhah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The sons of Manasseh; Asriel, whom she bare: (but his concubine the Aramitess bare Machir the father of Gilead:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />And Machir took to wife the sister of Huppim and Shuppim, whose sister's name was Maachah;) and the name of the second was Zelophehad: and Zelophehad had daughters.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />And Maachah the wife of Machir bare a son, and she called his name Peresh; and the name of his brother was Sheresh; and his sons were Ulam and Rakem.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />And the sons of Ulam; Bedan. These were the sons of Gilead, the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />And his sister Hammoleketh bare Ishod, and Abiezer, and Mahalah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />And the sons of Shemida were, Ahian, and Shechem, and Likhi, and Aniam.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And the sons of Ephraim; Shuthelah, and Bered his son, and Tahath his son, and Eladah his son, and Tahath his son,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />And Zabad his son, and Shuthelah his son, and Ezer, and Elead, whom the men of Gath that were born in that land slew, because they came down to take away their cattle.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />And Ephraim their father mourned many days, and his brethren came to comfort him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />And when he went in to his wife, she conceived, and bare a son, and he called his name Beriah, because it went evil with his house.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />(And his daughter was Sherah, who built Beth–horon the nether, and the upper, and Uzzen–sheerah.)</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />And Rephah was his son, also Resheph, and Telah his son, and Tahan his son,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />Laadan his son, Ammihud his son, Elishama his son,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Non his son, Jehoshua his son.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Non: or, Nun</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Jehoshua: or, Joshua</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />And their possessions and habitations were, Beth–el and the towns thereof, and eastward Naaran, and westward Gezer, with the towns thereof; Shechem also and the towns thereof, unto Gaza and the towns thereof:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">towns: Heb. daughters</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">unto Gaza: or, Adassa</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />And by the borders of the children of Manasseh, Beth–shean and her towns, Taanach and her towns, Megiddo and her towns, Dor and her towns. In these dwelt the children of Joseph the son of Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">towns: Heb. daughters</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />The sons of Asher; Imnah, and Ishuah, and Ishvi, and Beriah, and Serah their sister.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />And the sons of Beriah; Heber, and Malchiel, who is the father of Birzavith.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />And Heber begat Japhlet, and Shomer, and Hotham, and Shua their sister.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />And the sons of Japhlet; Pasach, and Bimhal, and Ashvath. These are the children of Japhlet.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />And the sons of Shamer; Ahi, and Rohgah, Jehubbah, and Aram.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />And the sons of his brother Helem; Zophah, and Imna, and Shelesh, and Amal.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" />The sons of Zophah; Suah, and Harnepher, and Shual, and Beri, and Imrah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" />Bezer, and Hod, and Shamma, and Shilshah, and Ithran, and Beera.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />And the sons of Jether; Jephunneh, and Pispah, and Ara.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" />And the sons of Ulla; Arah, and Haniel, and Rezia.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" />All these were the children of Asher, heads of their father's house, choice and mighty men of valour, chief of the princes. And the number throughout the genealogy of them that were apt to the war and to battle was twenty and six thousand men.</para>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now Benjamin begat Bela his firstborn, Ashbel the second, and Aharah the third,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Nohah the fourth, and Rapha the fifth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />And the sons of Bela were, Addar, and Gera, and Abihud,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Addar: or, Ard</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />And Abishua, and Naaman, and Ahoah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />And Gera, and Shephuphan, and Huram.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shephuphan: or, Shupham</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />And these are the sons of Ehud: these are the heads of the fathers of the inhabitants of Geba, and they removed them to Manahath:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And Naaman, and Ahiah, and Gera, he removed them, and begat Uzza, and Ahihud.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And Shaharaim begat children in the country of Moab, after he had sent them away; Hushim and Baara were his wives.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />And he begat of Hodesh his wife, Jobab, and Zibia, and Mesha, and Malcham,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />And Jeuz, and Shachia, and Mirma. These were his sons, heads of the fathers.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />And of Hushim he begat Abitub, and Elpaal.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />The sons of Elpaal; Eber, and Misham, and Shamed, who built Ono, and Lod, with the towns thereof:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Beriah also, and Shema, who were heads of the fathers of the inhabitants of Aijalon, who drove away the inhabitants of Gath:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />And Ahio, Shashak, and Jeremoth,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />And Zebadiah, and Arad, and Ader,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />And Michael, and Ispah, and Joha, the sons of Beriah;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />And Zebadiah, and Meshullam, and Hezeki, and Heber,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Ishmerai also, and Jezliah, and Jobab, the sons of Elpaal;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />And Jakim, and Zichri, and Zabdi,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And Elienai, and Zilthai, and Eliel,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />And Adaiah, and Beraiah, and Shimrath, the sons of Shimhi;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shimhi: or, Shema</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />And Ishpan, and Heber, and Eliel,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />And Abdon, and Zichri, and Hanan,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />And Hananiah, and Elam, and Antothijah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />And Iphedeiah, and Penuel, the sons of Shashak;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />And Shamsherai, and Shehariah, and Athaliah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />And Jaresiah, and Eliah, and Zichri, the sons of Jeroham.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />These were heads of the fathers, by their generations, chief men. These dwelt in Jerusalem.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />And at Gibeon dwelt the father of Gibeon; whose wife's name was Maachah:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">father…: also called Jehiel</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />And his firstborn son Abdon, and Zur, and Kish, and Baal, and Nadab,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />And Gedor, and Ahio, and Zacher.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Zacher: or, Zechariah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />And Mikloth begat Shimeah. And these also dwelt with their brethren in Jerusalem, over against them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shimeah: or, Shimeam</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />And Ner begat Kish, and Kish begat Saul, and Saul begat Jonathan, and Malchi–shua, and Abinadab, and Esh–baal.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Abinadab: also called, Ishui</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Esh–baal: or, Ish–bosheth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />And the son of Jonathan was Merib–baal; and Merib–baal begat Micah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Merib–baal: or, Mephibosheth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />And the sons of Micah were, Pithon, and Melech, and Tarea, and Ahaz.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Tarea: or, Tahrea</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" />And Ahaz begat Jehoadah; and Jehoadah begat Alemeth, and Azmaveth, and Zimri; and Zimri begat Moza,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Jehoadah: also called, Jarah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" />And Moza begat Binea: Rapha was his son, Eleasah his son, Azel his son:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Rapha: also called, Rephaiah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />And Azel had six sons, whose names are these, Azrikam, Bocheru, and Ishmael, and Sheariah, and Obadiah, and Hanan. All these were the sons of Azel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" />And the sons of Eshek his brother were, Ulam his firstborn, Jehush the second, and Eliphelet the third.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" />And the sons of Ulam were mighty men of valour, archers, and had many sons, and sons' sons, an hundred and fifty. All these are of the sons of Benjamin.</para>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />So all Israel were reckoned by genealogies; and, behold, they were written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah, who were carried away to Babylon for their transgression.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Now the first inhabitants that dwelt in their possessions in their cities were, the Israelites, the priests, Levites, and the Nethinims.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />And in Jerusalem dwelt of the children of Judah, and of the children of Benjamin, and of the children of Ephraim, and Manasseh;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Uthai the son of Ammihud, the son of Omri, the son of Imri, the son of Bani, of the children of Pharez the son of Judah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />And of the Shilonites; Asaiah the firstborn, and his sons.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />And of the sons of Zerah; Jeuel, and their brethren, six hundred and ninety.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And of the sons of Benjamin; Sallu the son of Meshullam, the son of Hodaviah, the son of Hasenuah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And Ibneiah the son of Jeroham, and Elah the son of Uzzi, the son of Michri, and Meshullam the son of Shephathiah, the son of Reuel, the son of Ibnijah;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />And their brethren, according to their generations, nine hundred and fifty and six. All these men were chief of the fathers in the house of their fathers.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />And of the priests; Jedaiah, and Jehoiarib, and Jachin,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />And Azariah the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, the ruler of the house of God;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Azariah: also called, Seraiah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />And Adaiah the son of Jeroham, the son of Pashur, the son of Malchijah, and Maasiai the son of Adiel, the son of Jahzerah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Meshillemith, the son of Immer;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />And their brethren, heads of the house of their fathers, a thousand and seven hundred and threescore; very able men for the work of the service of the house of God.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">very…: Heb. mighty men of valour</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />And of the Levites; Shemaiah the son of Hasshub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, of the sons of Merari;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />And Bakbakkar, Heresh, and Galal, and Mattaniah the son of Mica, the son of Zichri, the son of Asaph;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />And Obadiah the son of Shemaiah, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun, and Berechiah the son of Asa, the son of Elkanah, that dwelt in the villages of the Netophathites.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />And the porters were, Shallum, and Akkub, and Talmon, and Ahiman, and their brethren: Shallum was the chief;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Who hitherto waited in the king's gate eastward: they were porters in the companies of the children of Levi.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />And Shallum the son of Kore, the son of Ebiasaph, the son of Korah, and his brethren, of the house of his father, the Korahites, were over the work of the service, keepers of the gates of the tabernacle: and their fathers, being over the host of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, were keepers of the entry.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">gates: Heb. thresholds</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And Phinehas the son of Eleazar was the ruler over them in time past, and the <char style="nd">Lord</char> was with him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />And Zechariah the son of Meshelemiah was porter of the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />All these which were chosen to be porters in the gates were two hundred and twelve. These were reckoned by their genealogy in their villages, whom David and Samuel the seer did ordain in their set office.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">did…: Heb. founded</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">set…: or, trust</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />So they and their children had the oversight of the gates of the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, namely, the house of the tabernacle, by wards.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />In four quarters were the porters, toward the east, west, north, and south.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />And their brethren, which were in their villages, were to come after seven days from time to time with them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />For these Levites, the four chief porters, were in their set office, and were over the chambers and treasuries of the house of God.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">set…: or, trust</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">chambers: or, storehouses</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />And they lodged round about the house of God, because the charge was upon them, and the opening thereof every morning pertained to them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />And certain of them had the charge of the ministering vessels, that they should bring them in and out by tale.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">bring…: Heb. bring them in by tale, and carry them out by tale</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Some of them also were appointed to oversee the vessels, and all the instruments of the sanctuary, and the fine flour, and the wine, and the oil, and the frankincense, and the spices.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">instruments: or, vessels</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />And some of the sons of the priests made the ointment of the spices.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />And Mattithiah, one of the Levites, who was the firstborn of Shallum the Korahite, had the set office over the things that were made in the pans.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">set…: or, trust</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">in…: or, on flat plates, or, slices</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />And other of their brethren, of the sons of the Kohathites, were over the shewbread, to prepare it every sabbath.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">shewbread: Heb. bread of ordering</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />And these are the singers, chief of the fathers of the Levites, who remaining in the chambers were free: for they were employed in that work day and night.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">they…: Heb. upon them</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />These chief fathers of the Levites were chief throughout their generations; these dwelt at Jerusalem.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />And in Gibeon dwelt the father of Gibeon, Jehiel, whose wife's name was Maachah:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" />And his firstborn son Abdon, then Zur, and Kish, and Baal, and Ner, and Nadab,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" />And Gedor, and Ahio, and Zechariah, and Mikloth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />And Mikloth begat Shimeam. And they also dwelt with their brethren at Jerusalem, over against their brethren.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" />And Ner begat Kish; and Kish begat Saul; and Saul begat Jonathan, and Malchi–shua, and Abinadab, and Esh–baal.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" />And the son of Jonathan was Merib–baal: and Merib–baal begat Micah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" />And the sons of Micah were, Pithon, and Melech, and Tahrea, and Ahaz.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" />And Ahaz begat Jarah; and Jarah begat Alemeth, and Azmaveth, and Zimri; and Zimri begat Moza;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" />And Moza begat Binea; and Rephaiah his son, Eleasah his son, Azel his son.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" />And Azel had six sons, whose names are these, Azrikam, Bocheru, and Ishmael, and Sheariah, and Obadiah, and Hanan: these were the sons of Azel.</para>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now the Philistines fought against Israel; and the men of Israel fled from before the Philistines, and fell down slain in mount Gilboa.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">slain: or, wounded</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />And the Philistines followed hard after Saul, and after his sons; and the Philistines slew Jonathan, and Abinadab, and Malchi–shua, the sons of Saul.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Abinadab: also called, Ishui</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />And the battle went sore against Saul, and the archers hit him, and he was wounded of the archers.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">and the archers: Heb. and the shooters with bows</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">hit: Heb. found</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Then said Saul to his armourbearer, Draw thy sword, and thrust me through therewith; lest these uncircumcised come and abuse me. But his armourbearer would not; for he was sore afraid. So Saul took a sword, and fell upon it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">abuse me: or, mock me</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />And when his armourbearer saw that Saul was dead, he fell likewise on the sword, and died.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />So Saul died, and his three sons, and all his house died together.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And when all the men of Israel that were in the valley saw that they fled, and that Saul and his sons were dead, then they forsook their cities, and fled: and the Philistines came and dwelt in them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And it came to pass on the morrow, when the Philistines came to strip the slain, that they found Saul and his sons fallen in mount Gilboa.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />And when they had stripped him, they took his head, and his armour, and sent into the land of the Philistines round about, to carry tidings unto their idols, and to the people.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />And they put his armour in the house of their gods, and fastened his head in the temple of Dagon.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />And when all Jabesh–gilead heard all that the Philistines had done to Saul,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />They arose, all the valiant men, and took away the body of Saul, and the bodies of his sons, and brought them to Jabesh, and buried their bones under the oak in Jabesh, and fasted seven days.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />So Saul died for his transgression which he committed against the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, even against the word of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, which he kept not, and also for asking counsel of one that had a familiar spirit, to enquire of it;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">committed: Heb. transgressed</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />And enquired not of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>: therefore he slew him, and turned the kingdom unto David the son of Jesse.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Jesse: Heb. Isai</char></note></para>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Then all Israel gathered themselves to David unto Hebron, saying, Behold, we are thy bone and thy flesh.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />And moreover in time past, even when Saul was king, thou wast he that leddest out and broughtest in Israel: and the <char style="nd">Lord</char> thy God said unto thee, Thou shalt feed my people Israel, and thou shalt be ruler over my people Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">in time…: Heb. both yesterday and the third day</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">feed: or, rule</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Therefore came all the elders of Israel to the king to Hebron; and David made a covenant with them in Hebron before the <char style="nd">Lord</char>; and they anointed David king over Israel, according to the word of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> by Samuel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">by: Heb. by the hand of</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />And David and all Israel went to Jerusalem, which is Jebus; where the Jebusites were, the inhabitants of the land.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />And the inhabitants of Jebus said to David, Thou shalt not come hither. Nevertheless David took the castle of Zion, which is the city of David.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />And David said, Whosoever smiteth the Jebusites first shall be chief and captain. So Joab the son of Zeruiah went first up, and was chief.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">chief: Heb. head</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And David dwelt in the castle; therefore they called it the city of David.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">it: that is, Zion</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And he built the city round about, even from Millo round about: and Joab repaired the rest of the city.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">repaired: Heb. revived</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />So David waxed greater and greater: for the <char style="nd">Lord</char> of hosts was with him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">waxed…: Heb. went in going and increasing</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />These also are the chief of the mighty men whom David had, who strengthened themselves with him in his kingdom, and with all Israel, to make him king, according to the word of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> concerning Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">strengthened…: or, held strongly with him</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />And this is the number of the mighty men whom David had; Jashobeam, an Hachmonite, the chief of the captains: he lifted up his spear against three hundred slain by him at one time.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">an Hachmonite: or, son of Hachmoni</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />And after him was Eleazar the son of Dodo, the Ahohite, who was one of the three mighties.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />He was with David at Pas–dammim, and there the Philistines were gathered together to battle, where was a parcel of ground full of barley; and the people fled from before the Philistines.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Pas–dammim: also called, Ephes–dammim</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />And they set themselves in the midst of that parcel, and delivered it, and slew the Philistines; and the <char style="nd">Lord</char> saved them by a great deliverance.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">set…: or, stood</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">deliverance: or, salvation</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Now three of the thirty captains went down to the rock to David, into the cave of Adullam; and the host of the Philistines encamped in the valley of Rephaim.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">three…: or, three captains over the thirty</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />And David was then in the hold, and the Philistines' garrison was then at Beth–lehem.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />And David longed, and said, Oh that one would give me drink of the water of the well of Beth–lehem, that is at the gate!</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />And the three brake through the host of the Philistines, and drew water out of the well of Beth–lehem, that was by the gate, and took it, and brought it to David: but David would not drink of it, but poured it out to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />And said, My God forbid it me, that I should do this thing: shall I drink the blood of these men that have put their lives in jeopardy? for with the jeopardy of their lives they brought it. Therefore he would not drink it. These things did these three mightiest.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">that have…: Heb. with their lives?</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And Abishai the brother of Joab, he was chief of the three: for lifting up his spear against three hundred, he slew them, and had a name among the three.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />Of the three, he was more honourable than the two; for he was their captain: howbeit he attained not to the first three.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, the son of a valiant man of Kabzeel, who had done many acts; he slew two lionlike men of Moab: also he went down and slew a lion in a pit in a snowy day.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">who had…: Heb. great of deeds</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />And he slew an Egyptian, a man of great stature, five cubits high; and in the Egyptian's hand was a spear like a weaver's beam; and he went down to him with a staff, and plucked the spear out of the Egyptian's hand, and slew him with his own spear.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">great…: Heb. measure</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />These things did Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and had the name among the three mighties.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Behold, he was honourable among the thirty, but attained not to the first three: and David set him over his guard.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />Also the valiant men of the armies were, Asahel the brother of Joab, Elhanan the son of Dodo of Beth–lehem,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Shammoth the Harorite, Helez the Pelonite,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shammoth: or, Shammah</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Harorite: or, Harodite</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Pelonite: or, Paltite</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite, Abi–ezer the Anathothite,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Sibbecai the Hushathite, Ilai the Ahohite,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Sibbecai: or, Mebunnai</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Ilai: or, Zalmon</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />Maharai the Netophathite, Heled the son of Baanah the Netophathite,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Heled: or, Heleb</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />Ithai the son of Ribai of Gibeah, that pertained to the children of Benjamin, Benaiah the Pirathonite,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />Hurai of the brooks of Gaash, Abiel the Arbathite,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Hurai: or, Hiddai</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Abiel: or, Abi–albon</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />Azmaveth the Baharumite, Eliahba the Shaalbonite,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />The sons of Hashem the Gizonite, Jonathan the son of Shage the Hararite,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Hashem: or, Jashen</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />Ahiam the son of Sacar the Hararite, Eliphal the son of Ur,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Sacar: or, Sharar</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Eliphal: or, Eliphelet</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Ur: or, Ahasbai</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" />Hepher the Mecherathite, Ahijah the Pelonite,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" />Hezro the Carmelite, Naarai the son of Ezbai,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Hezro: or, Hezrai</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Naarai: or, Paarai the Arbite</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />Joel the brother of Nathan, Mibhar the son of Haggeri,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the son…: or, the Haggerite</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" />Zelek the Ammonite, Naharai the Berothite, the armourbearer of Joab the son of Zeruiah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" />Ira the Ithrite, Gareb the Ithrite,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" />Uriah the Hittite, Zabad the son of Ahlai,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" />Adina the son of Shiza the Reubenite, a captain of the Reubenites, and thirty with him,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" />Hanan the son of Maachah, and Joshaphat the Mithnite,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" />Uzzia the Ashterathite, Shama and Jehiel the sons of Hothan the Aroerite,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" />Jediael the son of Shimri, and Joha his brother, the Tizite,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">son…: or, Shimrite</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" />Eliel the Mahavite, and Jeribai, and Joshaviah, the sons of Elnaam, and Ithmah the Moabite,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" />Eliel, and Obed, and Jasiel the Mesobaite.</para>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now these are they that came to David to Ziklag, while he yet kept himself close because of Saul the son of Kish: and they were among the mighty men, helpers of the war.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">while…: Heb. being yet shut up</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />They were armed with bows, and could use both the right hand and the left in hurling stones and shooting arrows out of a bow, even of Saul's brethren of Benjamin.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />The chief was Ahiezer, then Joash, the sons of Shemaah the Gibeathite; and Jeziel, and Pelet, the sons of Azmaveth; and Berachah, and Jehu the Anathothite,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shemaah: or, Hasmaah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />And Ismaiah the Gibeonite, a mighty man among the thirty, and over the thirty; and Jeremiah, and Jahaziel, and Johanan, and Josabad the Gederathite,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Eluzai, and Jerimoth, and Bealiah, and Shemariah, and Shephatiah the Haruphite,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Elkanah, and Jesiah, and Azareel, and Joezer, and Jashobeam, the Korhites,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And Joelah, and Zebadiah, the sons of Jeroham of Gedor.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And of the Gadites there separated themselves unto David into the hold to the wilderness men of might, and men of war fit for the battle, that could handle shield and buckler, whose faces were like the faces of lions, and were as swift as the roes upon the mountains;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">of war: Heb. of the host</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">as swift…: Heb. as the roes upon the mountains to make haste</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Ezer the first, Obadiah the second, Eliab the third,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Mishmannah the fourth, Jeremiah the fifth,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Attai the sixth, Eliel the seventh,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Johanan the eighth, Elzabad the ninth,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Jeremiah the tenth, Machbanai the eleventh.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />These were of the sons of Gad, captains of the host: one of the least was over an hundred, and the greatest over a thousand.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">one…: or, one that was least could resist an hundred, and the greatest a thousand</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />These are they that went over Jordan in the first month, when it had overflown all his banks; and they put to flight all them of the valleys, both toward the east, and toward the west.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">overflown: Heb. filled over</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />And there came of the children of Benjamin and Judah to the hold unto David.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />And David went out to meet them, and answered and said unto them, If ye be come peaceably unto me to help me, mine heart shall be knit unto you: but if ye be come to betray me to mine enemies, seeing there is no wrong in mine hands, the God of our fathers look thereon, and rebuke it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">to meet…: Heb. before them</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">be knit: Heb. be one</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">wrong: or, violence</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Then the spirit came upon Amasai, who was chief of the captains, and he said, Thine are we, David, and on thy side, thou son of Jesse: peace, peace be unto thee, and peace be to thine helpers; for thy God helpeth thee. Then David received them, and made them captains of the band.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">came…: Heb. clothed</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />And there fell some of Manasseh to David, when he came with the Philistines against Saul to battle: but they helped them not: for the lords of the Philistines upon advisement sent him away, saying, He will fall to his master Saul to the jeopardy of our heads.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">to the…: Heb. on our heads</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />As he went to Ziklag, there fell to him of Manasseh, Adnah, and Jozabad, and Jediael, and Michael, and Jozabad, and Elihu, and Zilthai, captains of the thousands that were of Manasseh.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />And they helped David against the band of the rovers: for they were all mighty men of valour, and were captains in the host.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">against…: or, with a band</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />For at that time day by day there came to David to help him, until it was a great host, like the host of God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />And these are the numbers of the bands that were ready armed to the war, and came to David to Hebron, to turn the kingdom of Saul to him, according to the word of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">bands: or, captains, or, men: Heb. heads</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />The children of Judah that bare shield and spear were six thousand and eight hundred, ready armed to the war.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">armed: or, prepared</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Of the children of Simeon, mighty men of valour for the war, seven thousand and one hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />Of the children of Levi four thousand and six hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />And Jehoiada was the leader of the Aaronites, and with him were three thousand and seven hundred;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />And Zadok, a young man mighty of valour, and of his father's house twenty and two captains.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />And of the children of Benjamin, the kindred of Saul, three thousand: for hitherto the greatest part of them had kept the ward of the house of Saul.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">kindred: Heb. brethren</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the greatest…: Heb. a multitude of them</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />And of the children of Ephraim twenty thousand and eight hundred, mighty men of valour, famous throughout the house of their fathers.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">famous: Heb. men of names</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />And of the half tribe of Manasseh eighteen thousand, which were expressed by name, to come and make David king.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />And of the children of Issachar, which were men that had understanding of the times, to know what Israel ought to do; the heads of them were two hundred; and all their brethren were at their commandment.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />Of Zebulun, such as went forth to battle, expert in war, with all instruments of war, fifty thousand, which could keep rank: they were not of double heart.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">expert…: or, rangers of battle, or, ranged in battle</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">keep…: or, set the battle in array</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">not…: Heb. without a heart and a heart</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />And of Naphtali a thousand captains, and with them with shield and spear thirty and seven thousand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />And of the Danites expert in war twenty and eight thousand and six hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" />And of Asher, such as went forth to battle, expert in war, forty thousand.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">expert: or, keeping their rank</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" />And on the other side of Jordan, of the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and of the half tribe of Manasseh, with all manner of instruments of war for the battle, an hundred and twenty thousand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />All these men of war, that could keep rank, came with a perfect heart to Hebron, to make David king over all Israel: and all the rest also of Israel were of one heart to make David king.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" />And there they were with David three days, eating and drinking: for their brethren had prepared for them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" />Moreover they that were nigh them, even unto Issachar and Zebulun and Naphtali, brought bread on asses, and on camels, and on mules, and on oxen, and meat, meal, cakes of figs, and bunches of raisins, and wine, and oil, and oxen, and sheep abundantly: for there was joy in Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">meat…: or, victual of meal</char></note></para>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />And David consulted with the captains of thousands and hundreds, and with every leader.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />And David said unto all the congregation of Israel, If it seem good unto you, and that it be of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God, let us send abroad unto our brethren every where, that are left in all the land of Israel, and with them also to the priests and Levites which are in their cities and suburbs, that they may gather themselves unto us:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">send…: Heb. break forth and send</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">in their…: Heb. in the cities of their suburbs</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />And let us bring again the ark of our God to us: for we enquired not at it in the days of Saul.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">bring…: Heb. bring about</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />And all the congregation said that they would do so: for the thing was right in the eyes of all the people.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />So David gathered all Israel together, from Shihor of Egypt even unto the entering of Hamath, to bring the ark of God from Kirjath–jearim.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />And David went up, and all Israel, to Baalah, that is, to Kirjath–jearim, which belonged to Judah, to bring up thence the ark of God the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, that dwelleth between the cherubims, whose name is called on it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And they carried the ark of God in a new cart out of the house of Abinadab: and Uzza and Ahio drave the cart.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">carried…: Heb. made the ark to ride</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And David and all Israel played before God with all their might, and with singing, and with harps, and with psalteries, and with timbrels, and with cymbals, and with trumpets.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">singing: Heb. songs</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />And when they came unto the threshingfloor of Chidon, Uzza put forth his hand to hold the ark; for the oxen stumbled.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Chidon: also called, Nachon</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">stumbled: or, shook it</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />And the anger of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> was kindled against Uzza, and he smote him, because he put his hand to the ark: and there he died before God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />And David was displeased, because the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had made a breach upon Uzza: wherefore that place is called Perez–uzza to this day.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Perez–uzza: that is, The breach of Uzza</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />And David was afraid of God that day, saying, How shall I bring the ark of God home to me?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />So David brought not the ark home to himself to the city of David, but carried it aside into the house of Obed–edom the Gittite.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">brought: Heb. removed</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />And the ark of God remained with the family of Obed–edom in his house three months. And the <char style="nd">Lord</char> blessed the house of Obed–edom, and all that he had.</para>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now Hiram king of Tyre sent messengers to David, and timber of cedars, with masons and carpenters, to build him an house.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />And David perceived that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had confirmed him king over Israel, for his kingdom was lifted up on high, because of his people Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />And David took more wives at Jerusalem: and David begat more sons and daughters.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">more: Heb. yet</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Now these are the names of his children which he had in Jerusalem; Shammua, and Shobab, Nathan, and Solomon,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />And Ibhar, and Elishua, and Elpalet,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />And Nogah, and Nepheg, and Japhia,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And Elishama, and Beeliada, and Eliphelet.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Beeliada: also called, Eliada</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And when the Philistines heard that David was anointed king over all Israel, all the Philistines went up to seek David. And David heard of it, and went out against them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />And the Philistines came and spread themselves in the valley of Rephaim.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />And David enquired of God, saying, Shall I go up against the Philistines? and wilt thou deliver them into mine hand? And the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said unto him, Go up; for I will deliver them into thine hand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />So they came up to Baal–perazim; and David smote them there. Then David said, God hath broken in upon mine enemies by mine hand like the breaking forth of waters: therefore they called the name of that place Baal–perazim.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Baal–perazim: that is, A place of breaches</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />And when they had left their gods there, David gave a commandment, and they were burned with fire.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />And the Philistines yet again spread themselves abroad in the valley.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Therefore David enquired again of God; and God said unto him, Go not up after them; turn away from them, and come upon them over against the mulberry trees.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />And it shall be, when thou shalt hear a sound of going in the tops of the mulberry trees, that then thou shalt go out to battle: for God is gone forth before thee to smite the host of the Philistines.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />David therefore did as God commanded him: and they smote the host of the Philistines from Gibeon even to Gezer.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Gibeon: also called, Geba</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />And the fame of David went out into all lands; and the <char style="nd">Lord</char> brought the fear of him upon all nations.</para>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />And David made him houses in the city of David, and prepared a place for the ark of God, and pitched for it a tent.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Then David said, None ought to carry the ark of God but the Levites: for them hath the <char style="nd">Lord</char> chosen to carry the ark of God, and to minister unto him for ever.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">None…: Heb. It is not to carry the ark of God, but for the Levites</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />And David gathered all Israel together to Jerusalem, to bring up the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> unto his place, which he had prepared for it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />And David assembled the children of Aaron, and the Levites:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Of the sons of Kohath; Uriel the chief, and his brethren an hundred and twenty:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">brethren: or, kinsmen</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Of the sons of Merari; Asaiah the chief, and his brethren two hundred and twenty:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Of the sons of Gershom; Joel the chief, and his brethren an hundred and thirty:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Of the sons of Elizaphan; Shemaiah the chief, and his brethren two hundred:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Of the sons of Hebron; Eliel the chief, and his brethren fourscore:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Of the sons of Uzziel; Amminadab the chief, and his brethren an hundred and twelve.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />And David called for Zadok and Abiathar the priests, and for the Levites, for Uriel, Asaiah, and Joel, Shemaiah, and Eliel, and Amminadab,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />And said unto them, Ye are the chief of the fathers of the Levites: sanctify yourselves, both ye and your brethren, that ye may bring up the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> God of Israel unto the place that I have prepared for it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />For because ye did it not at the first, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God made a breach upon us, for that we sought him not after the due order.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />So the priests and the Levites sanctified themselves to bring up the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> God of Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />And the children of the Levites bare the ark of God upon their shoulders with the staves thereon, as Moses commanded according to the word of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />And David spake to the chief of the Levites to appoint their brethren to be the singers with instruments of musick, psalteries and harps and cymbals, sounding, by lifting up the voice with joy.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />So the Levites appointed Heman the son of Joel; and of his brethren, Asaph the son of Berechiah; and of the sons of Merari their brethren, Ethan the son of Kushaiah;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />And with them their brethren of the second degree, Zechariah, Ben, and Jaaziel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Unni, Eliab, and Benaiah, and Maaseiah, and Mattithiah, and Elipheleh, and Mikneiah, and Obed–edom, and Jeiel, the porters.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />So the singers, Heman, Asaph, and Ethan, were appointed to sound with cymbals of brass;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And Zechariah, and Aziel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Unni, and Eliab, and Maaseiah, and Benaiah, with psalteries on Alamoth;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />And Mattithiah, and Elipheleh, and Mikneiah, and Obed–edom, and Jeiel, and Azaziah, with harps on the Sheminith to excel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">on the…: or, on the eighth to oversee</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />And Chenaniah, chief of the Levites, was for song: he instructed about the song, because he was skilful.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">was for…: or, was for the carriage: he instructed about the carriage</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">song: Heb. lifting up</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />And Berechiah and Elkanah were doorkeepers for the ark.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />And Shebaniah, and Jehoshaphat, and Nethaneel, and Amasai, and Zechariah, and Benaiah, and Eliezer, the priests, did blow with the trumpets before the ark of God: and Obed–edom and Jehiah were doorkeepers for the ark.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />So David, and the elders of Israel, and the captains over thousands, went to bring up the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> out of the house of Obed–edom with joy.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />And it came to pass, when God helped the Levites that bare the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, that they offered seven bullocks and seven rams.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />And David was clothed with a robe of fine linen, and all the Levites that bare the ark, and the singers, and Chenaniah the master of the song with the singers: David also had upon him an ephod of linen.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">song: or, carriage</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Thus all Israel brought up the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> with shouting, and with sound of the cornet, and with trumpets, and with cymbals, making a noise with psalteries and harps.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />And it came to pass, as the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> came to the city of David, that Michal the daughter of Saul looking out at a window saw king David dancing and playing: and she despised him in her heart.</para>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />So they brought the ark of God, and set it in the midst of the tent that David had pitched for it: and they offered burnt sacrifices and peace offerings before God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />And when David had made an end of offering the burnt offerings and the peace offerings, he blessed the people in the name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />And he dealt to every one of Israel, both man and woman, to every one a loaf of bread, and a good piece of flesh, and a flagon of wine.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />And he appointed certain of the Levites to minister before the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and to record, and to thank and praise the <char style="nd">Lord</char> God of Israel:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Asaph the chief, and next to him Zechariah, Jeiel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Mattithiah, and Eliab, and Benaiah, and Obed–edom: and Jeiel with psalteries and with harps; but Asaph made a sound with cymbals;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">with psalteries…: Heb. with instruments of psalteries and harps</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Benaiah also and Jahaziel the priests with trumpets continually before the ark of the covenant of God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Then on that day David delivered first this psalm to thank the <char style="nd">Lord</char> into the hand of Asaph and his brethren.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Give thanks unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, call upon his name, make known his deeds among the people.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Sing unto him, sing psalms unto him, talk ye of all his wondrous works.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Glory ye in his holy name: let the heart of them rejoice that seek the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Seek the <char style="nd">Lord</char> and his strength, seek his face continually.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Remember his marvellous works that he hath done, his wonders, and the judgments of his mouth;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />O ye seed of Israel his servant, ye children of Jacob, his chosen ones.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />He is the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God; his judgments are in all the earth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Be ye mindful always of his covenant; the word which he commanded to a thousand generations;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Even of the covenant which he made with Abraham, and of his oath unto Isaac;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />And hath confirmed the same to Jacob for a law, and to Israel for an everlasting covenant,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Saying, Unto thee will I give the land of Canaan, the lot of your inheritance;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the lot: Heb. the cord</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />When ye were but few, even a few, and strangers in it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">few, even: Heb. men of number, etc.</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And when they went from nation to nation, and from one kingdom to another people;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />He suffered no man to do them wrong: yea, he reproved kings for their sakes,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Saying, Touch not mine anointed, and do my prophets no harm.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Sing unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, all the earth; shew forth from day to day his salvation.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Declare his glory among the heathen; his marvellous works among all nations.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />For great is the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and greatly to be praised: he also is to be feared above all gods.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />For all the gods of the people are idols: but the <char style="nd">Lord</char> made the heavens.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Glory and honour are in his presence; strength and gladness are in his place.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Give unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, ye kindreds of the people, give unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char> glory and strength.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Give unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char> the glory due unto his name: bring an offering, and come before him: worship the <char style="nd">Lord</char> in the beauty of holiness.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />Fear before him, all the earth: the world also shall be stable, that it be not moved.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />Let the heavens be glad, and let the earth rejoice: and let men say among the nations, The <char style="nd">Lord</char> reigneth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />Let the sea roar, and the fulness thereof: let the fields rejoice, and all that is therein.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />Then shall the trees of the wood sing out at the presence of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, because he cometh to judge the earth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />O give thanks unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char>; for he is good; for his mercy endureth for ever.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />And say ye, Save us, O God of our salvation, and gather us together, and deliver us from the heathen, that we may give thanks to thy holy name, and glory in thy praise.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" />Blessed be the <char style="nd">Lord</char> God of Israel for ever and ever. And all the people said, Amen, and praised the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" />So he left there before the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> Asaph and his brethren, to minister before the ark continually, as every day's work required:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />And Obed–edom with their brethren, threescore and eight; Obed–edom also the son of Jeduthun and Hosah to be porters:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" />And Zadok the priest, and his brethren the priests, before the tabernacle of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> in the high place that was at Gibeon,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" />To offer burnt offerings unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char> upon the altar of the burnt offering continually morning and evening, and to do according to all that is written in the law of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, which he commanded Israel;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">morning…: Heb. in the morning, and in the evening</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" />And with them Heman and Jeduthun, and the rest that were chosen, who were expressed by name, to give thanks to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, because his mercy endureth for ever;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" />And with them Heman and Jeduthun with trumpets and cymbals for those that should make a sound, and with musical instruments of God. And the sons of Jeduthun were porters.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">porters: Heb. for the gate</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" />And all the people departed every man to his house: and David returned to bless his house.</para>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now it came to pass, as David sat in his house, that David said to Nathan the prophet, Lo, I dwell in an house of cedars, but the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> remaineth under curtains.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Then Nathan said unto David, Do all that is in thine heart; for God is with thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />And it came to pass the same night, that the word of God came to Nathan, saying,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Go and tell David my servant, Thus saith the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, Thou shalt not build me an house to dwell in:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />For I have not dwelt in an house since the day that I brought up Israel unto this day; but have gone from tent to tent, and from one tabernacle to another.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">have gone: Heb. have been</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Wheresoever I have walked with all Israel, spake I a word to any of the judges of Israel, whom I commanded to feed my people, saying, Why have ye not built me an house of cedars?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Now therefore thus shalt thou say unto my servant David, Thus saith the <char style="nd">Lord</char> of hosts, I took thee from the sheepcote, even from following the sheep, that thou shouldest be ruler over my people Israel:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">from following: Heb. from after</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And I have been with thee whithersoever thou hast walked, and have cut off all thine enemies from before thee, and have made thee a name like the name of the great men that are in the earth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Also I will ordain a place for my people Israel, and will plant them, and they shall dwell in their place, and shall be moved no more; neither shall the children of wickedness waste them any more, as at the beginning,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />And since the time that I commanded judges to be over my people Israel. Moreover I will subdue all thine enemies. Furthermore I tell thee that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will build thee an house.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />And it shall come to pass, when thy days be expired that thou must go to be with thy fathers, that I will raise up thy seed after thee, which shall be of thy sons; and I will establish his kingdom.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />He shall build me an house, and I will stablish his throne for ever.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />I will be his father, and he shall be my son: and I will not take my mercy away from him, as I took it from him that was before thee:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />But I will settle him in mine house and in my kingdom for ever: and his throne shall be established for evermore.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />According to all these words, and according to all this vision, so did Nathan speak unto David.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />And David the king came and sat before the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and said, Who am I, O <char style="nd">Lord</char> God, and what is mine house, that thou hast brought me hitherto?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />And yet this was a small thing in thine eyes, O God; for thou hast also spoken of thy servant's house for a great while to come, and hast regarded me according to the estate of a man of high degree, O <char style="nd">Lord</char> God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />What can David speak more to thee for the honour of thy servant? for thou knowest thy servant.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />O <char style="nd">Lord</char>, for thy servant's sake, and according to thine own heart, hast thou done all this greatness, in making known all these great things.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">great…: Heb. greatnesses</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />O <char style="nd">Lord</char>, there is none like thee, neither is there any God beside thee, according to all that we have heard with our ears.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />And what one nation in the earth is like thy people Israel, whom God went to redeem to be his own people, to make thee a name of greatness and terribleness, by driving out nations from before thy people, whom thou hast redeemed out of Egypt?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />For thy people Israel didst thou make thine own people for ever; and thou, <char style="nd">Lord</char>, becamest their God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Therefore now, <char style="nd">Lord</char>, let the thing that thou hast spoken concerning thy servant and concerning his house be established for ever, and do as thou hast said.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Let it even be established, that thy name may be magnified for ever, saying, The <char style="nd">Lord</char> of hosts is the God of Israel, even a God to Israel: and let the house of David thy servant be established before thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />For thou, O my God, hast told thy servant that thou wilt build him an house: therefore thy servant hath found in his heart to pray before thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">hast…: Heb. hast revealed the ear of thy servant</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />And now, <char style="nd">Lord</char>, thou art God, and hast promised this goodness unto thy servant:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Now therefore let it please thee to bless the house of thy servant, that it may be before thee for ever: for thou blessest, O <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and it shall be blessed for ever.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">let…: or, it hath pleased thee</char></note></para>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now after this it came to pass, that David smote the Philistines, and subdued them, and took Gath and her towns out of the hand of the Philistines.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />And he smote Moab; and the Moabites became David's servants, and brought gifts.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />And David smote Hadarezer king of Zobah unto Hamath, as he went to stablish his dominion by the river Euphrates.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Hadarezer: or, Hadadezer</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />And David took from him a thousand chariots, and seven thousand horsemen, and twenty thousand footmen: David also houghed all the chariot horses, but reserved of them an hundred chariots.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">seven…: or, seven hundred</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />And when the Syrians of Damascus came to help Hadarezer king of Zobah, David slew of the Syrians two and twenty thousand men.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Damascus: Heb. Darmesek</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Then David put garrisons in Syria–damascus; and the Syrians became David's servants, and brought gifts. Thus the <char style="nd">Lord</char> preserved David whithersoever he went.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And David took the shields of gold that were on the servants of Hadarezer, and brought them to Jerusalem.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Likewise from Tibhath, and from Chun, cities of Hadarezer, brought David very much brass, wherewith Solomon made the brasen sea, and the pillars, and the vessels of brass.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Tibhath…: called in the book of Samuel Betah, and Berothai</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Now when Tou king of Hamath heard how David had smitten all the host of Hadarezer king of Zobah;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Tou: also called, Toi</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />He sent Hadoram his son to king David, to enquire of his welfare, and to congratulate him, because he had fought against Hadarezer, and smitten him; (for Hadarezer had war with Tou;) and with him all manner of vessels of gold and silver and brass.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Hadoram: also called, Joram</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">to enquire…: or, to salute</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">to congratulate: Heb. to bless</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">had war: Heb. was the man of wars</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Them also king David dedicated unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, with the silver and the gold that he brought from all these nations; from Edom, and from Moab, and from the children of Ammon, and from the Philistines, and from Amalek.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Moreover Abishai the son of Zeruiah slew of the Edomites in the valley of salt eighteen thousand.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Abishai: Heb. Abshai</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />And he put garrisons in Edom; and all the Edomites became David's servants. Thus the <char style="nd">Lord</char> preserved David whithersoever he went.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />So David reigned over all Israel, and executed judgment and justice among all his people.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />And Joab the son of Zeruiah was over the host; and Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud, recorder.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">recorder: or, remembrancer</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />And Zadok the son of Ahitub, and Abimelech the son of Abiathar, were the priests; and Shavsha was scribe;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Abimelech: also called, Ahimelech</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shavsha: also called, Seraiah or Shisha</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />And Benaiah the son of Jehoiada was over the Cherethites and the Pelethites; and the sons of David were chief about the king.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">about…: Heb. at the hand of the king</char></note></para>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now it came to pass after this, that Nahash the king of the children of Ammon died, and his son reigned in his stead.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />And David said, I will shew kindness unto Hanun the son of Nahash, because his father shewed kindness to me. And David sent messengers to comfort him concerning his father. So the servants of David came into the land of the children of Ammon to Hanun, to comfort him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />But the princes of the children of Ammon said to Hanun, Thinkest thou that David doth honour thy father, that he hath sent comforters unto thee? are not his servants come unto thee for to search, and to overthrow, and to spy out the land?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Thinkest…: Heb. In thine eyes doth David, etc.</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Wherefore Hanun took David's servants, and shaved them, and cut off their garments in the midst hard by their buttocks, and sent them away.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Then there went certain, and told David how the men were served. And he sent to meet them: for the men were greatly ashamed. And the king said, Tarry at Jericho until your beards be grown, and then return.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />And when the children of Ammon saw that they had made themselves odious to David, Hanun and the children of Ammon sent a thousand talents of silver to hire them chariots and horsemen out of Mesopotamia, and out of Syria–maacah, and out of Zobah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">odious: Heb. to stink</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />So they hired thirty and two thousand chariots, and the king of Maacah and his people; who came and pitched before Medeba. And the children of Ammon gathered themselves together from their cities, and came to battle.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And when David heard of it, he sent Joab, and all the host of the mighty men.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />And the children of Ammon came out, and put the battle in array before the gate of the city: and the kings that were come were by themselves in the field.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Now when Joab saw that the battle was set against him before and behind, he chose out of all the choice of Israel, and put them in array against the Syrians.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the battle…: Heb. the face of the battle was</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">choice: or, young men</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />And the rest of the people he delivered unto the hand of Abishai his brother, and they set themselves in array against the children of Ammon.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Abishai: Heb. Abshai</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />And he said, If the Syrians be too strong for me, then thou shalt help me: but if the children of Ammon be too strong for thee, then I will help thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Be of good courage, and let us behave ourselves valiantly for our people, and for the cities of our God: and let the <char style="nd">Lord</char> do that which is good in his sight.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />So Joab and the people that were with him drew nigh before the Syrians unto the battle; and they fled before him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />And when the children of Ammon saw that the Syrians were fled, they likewise fled before Abishai his brother, and entered into the city. Then Joab came to Jerusalem.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />And when the Syrians saw that they were put to the worse before Israel, they sent messengers, and drew forth the Syrians that were beyond the river: and Shophach the captain of the host of Hadarezer went before them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">river: that is, Euphrates</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shophach: also called, Shobach</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />And it was told David; and he gathered all Israel, and passed over Jordan, and came upon them, and set the battle in array against them. So when David had put the battle in array against the Syrians, they fought with him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />But the Syrians fled before Israel; and David slew of the Syrians seven thousand men which fought in chariots, and forty thousand footmen, and killed Shophach the captain of the host.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />And when the servants of Hadarezer saw that they were put to the worse before Israel, they made peace with David, and became his servants: neither would the Syrians help the children of Ammon any more.</para>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />And it came to pass, that after the year was expired, at the time that kings go out to battle, Joab led forth the power of the army, and wasted the country of the children of Ammon, and came and besieged Rabbah. But David tarried at Jerusalem. And Joab smote Rabbah, and destroyed it.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">after…: Heb. at the return of the year</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />And David took the crown of their king from off his head, and found it to weigh a talent of gold, and there were precious stones in it; and it was set upon David's head: and he brought also exceeding much spoil out of the city.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">to weigh: Heb. the weight of</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />And he brought out the people that were in it, and cut them with saws, and with harrows of iron, and with axes. Even so dealt David with all the cities of the children of Ammon. And David and all the people returned to Jerusalem.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />And it came to pass after this, that there arose war at Gezer with the Philistines; at which time Sibbecai the Hushathite slew Sippai, that was of the children of the giant: and they were subdued.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">arose: or, continued: Heb. stood</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Gezer: also called, Gob</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Sippai: also called, Saph</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the giant: or, Rapha</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />And there was war again with the Philistines; and Elhanan the son of Jair slew Lahmi the brother of Goliath the Gittite, whose spear staff was like a weaver's beam.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Jair: also called, Jaare–oregim</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />And yet again there was war at Gath, where was a man of great stature, whose fingers and toes were four and twenty, six on each hand, and six on each foot: and he also was the son of the giant.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">great…: Heb. measure</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the son…: Heb. born to the giant, or, Rapha</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />But when he defied Israel, Jonathan the son of Shimea David's brother slew him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">defied: or, reproached</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shimea: also called, Shammah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />These were born unto the giant in Gath; and they fell by the hand of David, and by the hand of his servants.</para>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />And Satan stood up against Israel, and provoked David to number Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />And David said to Joab and to the rulers of the people, Go, number Israel from Beer–sheba even to Dan; and bring the number of them to me, that I may know it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />And Joab answered, The <char style="nd">Lord</char> make his people an hundred times so many more as they be: but, my lord the king, are they not all my lord's servants? why then doth my lord require this thing? why will he be a cause of trespass to Israel?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Nevertheless the king's word prevailed against Joab. Wherefore Joab departed, and went throughout all Israel, and came to Jerusalem.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />And Joab gave the sum of the number of the people unto David. And all they of Israel were a thousand thousand and an hundred thousand men that drew sword: and Judah was four hundred threescore and ten thousand men that drew sword.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />But Levi and Benjamin counted he not among them: for the king's word was abominable to Joab.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And God was displeased with this thing; therefore he smote Israel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">And…: Heb. And it was evil in the eyes of the Lord concerning this thing</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And David said unto God, I have sinned greatly, because I have done this thing: but now, I beseech thee, do away the iniquity of thy servant; for I have done very foolishly.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />And the <char style="nd">Lord</char> spake unto Gad, David's seer, saying,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Go and tell David, saying, Thus saith the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, I offer thee three things: choose thee one of them, that I may do it unto thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">offer: Heb. stretch out</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />So Gad came to David, and said unto him, Thus saith the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, Choose thee<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Choose…: Heb. Take to thee</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Either three years' famine; or three months to be destroyed before thy foes, while that the sword of thine enemies overtaketh thee; or else three days the sword of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, even the pestilence, in the land, and the angel of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> destroying throughout all the coasts of Israel. Now therefore advise thyself what word I shall bring again to him that sent me.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />And David said unto Gad, I am in a great strait: let me fall now into the hand of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>; for very great are his mercies: but let me not fall into the hand of man.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">very great: or, very many</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />So the <char style="nd">Lord</char> sent pestilence upon Israel: and there fell of Israel seventy thousand men.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />And God sent an angel unto Jerusalem to destroy it: and as he was destroying, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> beheld, and he repented him of the evil, and said to the angel that destroyed, It is enough, stay now thine hand. And the angel of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> stood by the threshingfloor of Ornan the Jebusite.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Ornan: also called, Araunah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />And David lifted up his eyes, and saw the angel of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> stand between the earth and the heaven, having a drawn sword in his hand stretched out over Jerusalem. Then David and the elders of Israel, who were clothed in sackcloth, fell upon their faces.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />And David said unto God, Is it not I that commanded the people to be numbered? even I it is that have sinned and done evil indeed; but as for these sheep, what have they done? let thine hand, I pray thee, O <char style="nd">Lord</char> my God, be on me, and on my father's house; but not on thy people, that they should be plagued.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Then the angel of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded Gad to say to David, that David should go up, and set up an altar unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char> in the threshingfloor of Ornan the Jebusite.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />And David went up at the saying of Gad, which he spake in the name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And Ornan turned back, and saw the angel; and his four sons with him hid themselves. Now Ornan was threshing wheat.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">And Ornan…: or, When Ornan turned back and saw the angel, then he and his four sons with him hid themselves</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />And as David came to Ornan, Ornan looked and saw David, and went out of the threshingfloor, and bowed himself to David with his face to the ground.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Then David said to Ornan, Grant me the place of this threshingfloor, that I may build an altar therein unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char>: thou shalt grant it me for the full price: that the plague may be stayed from the people.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Grant: Heb. Give</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />And Ornan said unto David, Take it to thee, and let my lord the king do that which is good in his eyes: lo, I give thee the oxen also for burnt offerings, and the threshing instruments for wood, and the wheat for the meat offering; I give it all.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />And king David said to Ornan, Nay; but I will verily buy it for the full price: for I will not take that which is thine for the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, nor offer burnt offerings without cost.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />So David gave to Ornan for the place six hundred shekels of gold by weight.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />And David built there an altar unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and offered burnt offerings and peace offerings, and called upon the <char style="nd">Lord</char>; and he answered him from heaven by fire upon the altar of burnt offering.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />And the <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded the angel; and he put up his sword again into the sheath thereof.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />At that time when David saw that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had answered him in the threshingfloor of Ornan the Jebusite, then he sacrificed there.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />For the tabernacle of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, which Moses made in the wilderness, and the altar of the burnt offering, were at that season in the high place at Gibeon.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />But David could not go before it to enquire of God: for he was afraid because of the sword of the angel of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Then David said, This is the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> God, and this is the altar of the burnt offering for Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />And David commanded to gather together the strangers that were in the land of Israel; and he set masons to hew wrought stones to build the house of God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />And David prepared iron in abundance for the nails for the doors of the gates, and for the joinings; and brass in abundance without weight;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Also cedar trees in abundance: for the Zidonians and they of Tyre brought much cedar wood to David.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />And David said, Solomon my son is young and tender, and the house that is to be builded for the <char style="nd">Lord</char> must be exceeding magnifical, of fame and of glory throughout all countries: I will therefore now make preparation for it. So David prepared abundantly before his death.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Then he called for Solomon his son, and charged him to build an house for the <char style="nd">Lord</char> God of Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And David said to Solomon, My son, as for me, it was in my mind to build an house unto the name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> my God:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />But the word of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> came to me, saying, Thou hast shed blood abundantly, and hast made great wars: thou shalt not build an house unto my name, because thou hast shed much blood upon the earth in my sight.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Behold, a son shall be born to thee, who shall be a man of rest; and I will give him rest from all his enemies round about: for his name shall be Solomon, and I will give peace and quietness unto Israel in his days.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Solomon: that is, Peaceable</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />He shall build an house for my name; and he shall be my son, and I will be his father; and I will establish the throne of his kingdom over Israel for ever.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Now, my son, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> be with thee; and prosper thou, and build the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> thy God, as he hath said of thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Only the <char style="nd">Lord</char> give thee wisdom and understanding, and give thee charge concerning Israel, that thou mayest keep the law of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> thy God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Then shalt thou prosper, if thou takest heed to fulfil the statutes and judgments which the <char style="nd">Lord</char> charged Moses with concerning Israel: be strong, and of good courage; dread not, nor be dismayed.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Now, behold, in my trouble I have prepared for the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> an hundred thousand talents of gold, and a thousand thousand talents of silver; and of brass and iron without weight; for it is in abundance: timber also and stone have I prepared; and thou mayest add thereto.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">trouble: or, poverty</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Moreover there are workmen with thee in abundance, hewers and workers of stone and timber, and all manner of cunning men for every manner of work.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">workers…: that is, masons and carpenters</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Of the gold, the silver, and the brass, and the iron, there is no number. Arise therefore, and be doing, and the <char style="nd">Lord</char> be with thee.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />David also commanded all the princes of Israel to help Solomon his son, saying,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Is not the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God with you? and hath he not given you rest on every side? for he hath given the inhabitants of the land into mine hand; and the land is subdued before the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and before his people.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />Now set your heart and your soul to seek the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God; arise therefore, and build ye the sanctuary of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> God, to bring the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and the holy vessels of God, into the house that is to be built to the name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />So when David was old and full of days, he made Solomon his son king over Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />And he gathered together all the princes of Israel, with the priests and the Levites.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Now the Levites were numbered from the age of thirty years and upward: and their number by their polls, man by man, was thirty and eight thousand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Of which, twenty and four thousand were to set forward the work of the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>; and six thousand were officers and judges:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">set…: or, oversee</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Moreover four thousand were porters; and four thousand praised the <char style="nd">Lord</char> with the instruments which I made, said David, to praise therewith.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />And David divided them into courses among the sons of Levi, namely, Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">courses: Heb. divisions</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Of the Gershonites were, Laadan, and Shimei.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Laadan: or, Libni</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />The sons of Laadan; the chief was Jehiel, and Zetham, and Joel, three.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />The sons of Shimei; Shelomith, and Haziel, and Haran, three. These were the chief of the fathers of Laadan.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />And the sons of Shimei were, Jahath, Zina, and Jeush, and Beriah. These four were the sons of Shimei.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Zina: or, Zizah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />And Jahath was the chief, and Zizah the second: but Jeush and Beriah had not many sons; therefore they were in one reckoning, according to their father's house.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">had…: Heb. did not multiply sons</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />The sons of Kohath; Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel, four.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />The sons of Amram; Aaron and Moses: and Aaron was separated, that he should sanctify the most holy things, he and his sons for ever, to burn incense before the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, to minister unto him, and to bless in his name for ever.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Now concerning Moses the man of God, his sons were named of the tribe of Levi.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />The sons of Moses were, Gershom, and Eliezer.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Of the sons of Gershom, Shebuel was the chief.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shebuel: also called, Shubael</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />And the sons of Eliezer were, Rehabiah the chief. And Eliezer had none other sons; but the sons of Rehabiah were very many.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">the chief: or, the first</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">very many: Heb. highly multiplied</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Of the sons of Izhar; Shelomith the chief.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shelomith: also called, Shelomoth</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />Of the sons of Hebron; Jeriah the first, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, and Jekameam the fourth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />Of the sons of Uzziel; Michah the first, and Isshiah the second.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />The sons of Merari; Mahli, and Mushi. The sons of Mahli; Eleazar, and Kish.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />And Eleazar died, and had no sons, but daughters: and their brethren the sons of Kish took them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">brethren: or, kinsmen</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />The sons of Mushi; Mahli, and Eder, and Jeremoth, three.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />These were the sons of Levi after the house of their fathers; even the chief of the fathers, as they were counted by number of names by their polls, that did the work for the service of the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, from the age of twenty years and upward.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />For David said, The <char style="nd">Lord</char> God of Israel hath given rest unto his people, that they may dwell in Jerusalem for ever:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">that…: or, and he dwelleth in Jerusalem, etc.</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />And also unto the Levites; they shall no more carry the tabernacle, nor any vessels of it for the service thereof.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />For by the last words of David the Levites were numbered from twenty years old and above:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">numbered: Heb. number</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Because their office was to wait on the sons of Aaron for the service of the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, in the courts, and in the chambers, and in the purifying of all holy things, and the work of the service of the house of God;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">their…: Heb. their station was at the hand of the sons of Aaron</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Both for the shewbread, and for the fine flour for meat offering, and for the unleavened cakes, and for that which is baked in the pan, and for that which is fried, and for all manner of measure and size;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">pan: or, flat plate</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />And to stand every morning to thank and praise the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and likewise at even;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />And to offer all burnt sacrifices unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char> in the sabbaths, in the new moons, and on the set feasts, by number, according to the order commanded unto them, continually before the <char style="nd">Lord</char>:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />And that they should keep the charge of the tabernacle of the congregation, and the charge of the holy place, and the charge of the sons of Aaron their brethren, in the service of the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now these are the divisions of the sons of Aaron. The sons of Aaron; Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />But Nadab and Abihu died before their father, and had no children: therefore Eleazar and Ithamar executed the priest's office.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />And David distributed them, both Zadok of the sons of Eleazar, and Ahimelech of the sons of Ithamar, according to their offices in their service.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />And there were more chief men found of the sons of Eleazar than of the sons of Ithamar; and thus were they divided. Among the sons of Eleazar there were sixteen chief men of the house of their fathers, and eight among the sons of Ithamar according to the house of their fathers.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Thus were they divided by lot, one sort with another; for the governors of the sanctuary, and governors of the house of God, were of the sons of Eleazar, and of the sons of Ithamar.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />And Shemaiah the son of Nethaneel the scribe, one of the Levites, wrote them before the king, and the princes, and Zadok the priest, and Ahimelech the son of Abiathar, and before the chief of the fathers of the priests and Levites: one principal household being taken for Eleazar, and one taken for Ithamar.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">principal…: Heb. house of the father</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Now the first lot came forth to Jehoiarib, the second to Jedaiah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />The third to Harim, the fourth to Seorim,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />The fifth to Malchijah, the sixth to Mijamin,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />The seventh to Hakkoz, the eighth to Abijah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />The ninth to Jeshua, the tenth to Shecaniah,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />The eleventh to Eliashib, the twelfth to Jakim,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />The thirteenth to Huppah, the fourteenth to Jeshebeab,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The fifteenth to Bilgah, the sixteenth to Immer,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />The seventeenth to Hezir, the eighteenth to Aphses,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />The nineteenth to Pethahiah, the twentieth to Jehezekel,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />The one and twentieth to Jachin, the two and twentieth to Gamul,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />The three and twentieth to Delaiah, the four and twentieth to Maaziah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />These were the orderings of them in their service to come into the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, according to their manner, under Aaron their father, as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> God of Israel had commanded him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And the rest of the sons of Levi were these: Of the sons of Amram; Shubael: of the sons of Shubael; Jehdeiah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shubael: also called, Shebuel</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />Concerning Rehabiah: of the sons of Rehabiah, the first was Isshiah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Of the Izharites; Shelomoth: of the sons of Shelomoth; Jahath.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shelomoth: also called, Shelomith</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />And the sons of Hebron; Jeriah the first, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, Jekameam the fourth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Of the sons of Uzziel; Michah: of the sons of Michah; Shamir.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />The brother of Michah was Isshiah: of the sons of Isshiah; Zechariah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />The sons of Merari were Mahli and Mushi: the sons of Jaaziah; Beno.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />The sons of Merari by Jaaziah; Beno, and Shoham, and Zaccur, and Ibri.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Of Mahli came Eleazar, who had no sons.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Concerning Kish: the son of Kish was Jerahmeel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />The sons also of Mushi; Mahli, and Eder, and Jerimoth. These were the sons of the Levites after the house of their fathers.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />These likewise cast lots over against their brethren the sons of Aaron in the presence of David the king, and Zadok, and Ahimelech, and the chief of the fathers of the priests and Levites, even the principal fathers over against their younger brethren.</para>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Moreover David and the captains of the host separated to the service of the sons of Asaph, and of Heman, and of Jeduthun, who should prophesy with harps, with psalteries, and with cymbals: and the number of the workmen according to their service was:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Of the sons of Asaph; Zaccur, and Joseph, and Nethaniah, and Asarelah, the sons of Asaph under the hands of Asaph, which prophesied according to the order of the king.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Asarelah: otherwise called Jesharelah</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">according…: Heb. by the hands of the king</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Of Jeduthun: the sons of Jeduthun; Gedaliah, and Zeri, and Jeshaiah, Hashabiah, and Mattithiah, six, under the hands of their father Jeduthun, who prophesied with a harp, to give thanks and to praise the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Zeri: or, Izri</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Of Heman: the sons of Heman; Bukkiah, Mattaniah, Uzziel, Shebuel, and Jerimoth, Hananiah, Hanani, Eliathah, Giddalti, and Romamti–ezer, Joshbekashah, Mallothi, Hothir, and Mahazioth:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Uzziel: also called, Azareel</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shebuel: also called, Shubael</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />All these were the sons of Heman the king's seer in the words of God, to lift up the horn. And God gave to Heman fourteen sons and three daughters.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">words: or, matters</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />All these were under the hands of their father for song in the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, with cymbals, psalteries, and harps, for the service of the house of God, according to the king's order to Asaph, Jeduthun, and Heman.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">according…: Heb. by the hands of the king</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />So the number of them, with their brethren that were instructed in the songs of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, even all that were cunning, was two hundred fourscore and eight.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And they cast lots, ward against ward, as well the small as the great, the teacher as the scholar.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Now the first lot came forth for Asaph to Joseph: the second to Gedaliah, who with his brethren and sons were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />The third to Zaccur, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />The fourth to Izri, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />The fifth to Nethaniah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />The sixth to Bukkiah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The seventh to Jesharelah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />The eighth to Jeshaiah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />The ninth to Mattaniah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />The tenth to Shimei, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />The eleventh to Azareel, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />The twelfth to Hashabiah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />The thirteenth to Shubael, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />The fourteenth to Mattithiah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />The fifteenth to Jeremoth, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />The sixteenth to Hananiah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />The seventeenth to Joshbekashah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />The eighteenth to Hanani, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />The nineteenth to Mallothi, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />The twentieth to Eliathah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />The one and twentieth to Hothir, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />The two and twentieth to Giddalti, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />The three and twentieth to Mahazioth, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />The four and twentieth to Romamti–ezer, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve.</para>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Concerning the divisions of the porters: Of the Korhites was Meshelemiah the son of Kore, of the sons of Asaph.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Meshelemiah: also called, Shelemiah</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Asaph: also called, Ebiasaph</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />And the sons of Meshelemiah were, Zechariah the firstborn, Jediael the second, Zebadiah the third, Jathniel the fourth,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Elam the fifth, Jehohanan the sixth, Elioenai the seventh.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Moreover the sons of Obed–edom were, Shemaiah the firstborn, Jehozabad the second, Joah the third, and Sacar the fourth, and Nethaneel the fifth,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Ammiel the sixth, Issachar the seventh, Peulthai the eighth: for God blessed him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">him: that is, Obed–edom</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Also unto Shemaiah his son were sons born, that ruled throughout the house of their father: for they were mighty men of valour.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />The sons of Shemaiah; Othni, and Rephael, and Obed, Elzabad, whose brethren were strong men, Elihu, and Semachiah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />All these of the sons of Obed–edom: they and their sons and their brethren, able men for strength for the service, were threescore and two of Obed–edom.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />And Meshelemiah had sons and brethren, strong men, eighteen.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Also Hosah, of the children of Merari, had sons; Simri the chief, (for though he was not the firstborn, yet his father made him the chief;)</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Hilkiah the second, Tebaliah the third, Zechariah the fourth: all the sons and brethren of Hosah were thirteen.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Among these were the divisions of the porters, even among the chief men, having wards one against another, to minister in the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />And they cast lots, as well the small as the great, according to the house of their fathers, for every gate.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">as well…: or, as well for the small as for the great</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />And the lot eastward fell to Shelemiah. Then for Zechariah his son, a wise counsellor, they cast lots; and his lot came out northward.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Shelemiah: also called, Meshelemiah</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />To Obed–edom southward; and to his sons the house of Asuppim.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Asuppim: Heb. gatherings</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />To Shuppim and Hosah the lot came forth westward, with the gate Shallecheth, by the causeway of the going up, ward against ward.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Eastward were six Levites, northward four a day, southward four a day, and toward Asuppim two and two.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />At Parbar westward, four at the causeway, and two at Parbar.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />These are the divisions of the porters among the sons of Kore, and among the sons of Merari.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And of the Levites, Ahijah was over the treasures of the house of God, and over the treasures of the dedicated things.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">dedicated…: Heb. holy things</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />As concerning the sons of Laadan; the sons of the Gershonite Laadan, chief fathers, even of Laadan the Gershonite, were Jehieli.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Laadan: also called, Libni</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Jehieli: also called, Jehiel</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />The sons of Jehieli; Zetham, and Joel his brother, which were over the treasures of the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Of the Amramites, and the Izharites, the Hebronites, and the Uzzielites:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />And Shebuel the son of Gershom, the son of Moses, was ruler of the treasures.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />And his brethren by Eliezer; Rehabiah his son, and Jeshaiah his son, and Joram his son, and Zichri his son, and Shelomith his son.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />Which Shelomith and his brethren were over all the treasures of the dedicated things, which David the king, and the chief fathers, the captains over thousands and hundreds, and the captains of the host, had dedicated.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Out of the spoils won in battles did they dedicate to maintain the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">spoils…: Heb. battles and spoils</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />And all that Samuel the seer, and Saul the son of Kish, and Abner the son of Ner, and Joab the son of Zeruiah, had dedicated; and whosoever had dedicated any thing, it was under the hand of Shelomith, and of his brethren.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Of the Izharites, Chenaniah and his sons were for the outward business over Israel, for officers and judges.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />And of the Hebronites, Hashabiah and his brethren, men of valour, a thousand and seven hundred, were officers among them of Israel on this side Jordan westward in all the business of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and in the service of the king.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">officers…: Heb. over the charge</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />Among the Hebronites was Jeriah the chief, even among the Hebronites, according to the generations of his fathers. In the fortieth year of the reign of David they were sought for, and there were found among them mighty men of valour at Jazer of Gilead.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />And his brethren, men of valour, were two thousand and seven hundred chief fathers, whom king David made rulers over the Reubenites, the Gadites, and the half tribe of Manasseh, for every matter pertaining to God, and affairs of the king.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">affairs: Heb. thing</char></note></para>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now the children of Israel after their number, to wit, the chief fathers and captains of thousands and hundreds, and their officers that served the king in any matter of the courses, which came in and went out month by month throughout all the months of the year, of every course were twenty and four thousand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Over the first course for the first month was Jashobeam the son of Zabdiel: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Of the children of Perez was the chief of all the captains of the host for the first month.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />And over the course of the second month was Dodai an Ahohite, and of his course was Mikloth also the ruler: in his course likewise were twenty and four thousand.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Dodai: also called, Dodo</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />The third captain of the host for the third month was Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, a chief priest: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">chief…: or, principal officer</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />This is that Benaiah, who was mighty among the thirty, and above the thirty: and in his course was Ammizabad his son.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />The fourth captain for the fourth month was Asahel the brother of Joab, and Zebadiah his son after him: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />The fifth captain for the fifth month was Shamhuth the Izrahite: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />The sixth captain for the sixth month was Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />The seventh captain for the seventh month was Helez the Pelonite, of the children of Ephraim: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />The eighth captain for the eighth month was Sibbecai the Hushathite, of the Zarhites: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />The ninth captain for the ninth month was Abi–ezer the Anathothite, of the Benjamites: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />The tenth captain for the tenth month was Maharai the Netophathite, of the Zarhites: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The eleventh captain for the eleventh month was Benaiah the Pirathonite, of the children of Ephraim: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />The twelfth captain for the twelfth month was Heldai the Netophathite, of Othniel: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Heldai: also called, Heled</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Furthermore over the tribes of Israel: the ruler of the Reubenites was Eliezer the son of Zichri: of the Simeonites, Shephatiah the son of Maachah:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Of the Levites, Hashabiah the son of Kemuel: of the Aaronites, Zadok:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Of Judah, Elihu, one of the brethren of David: of Issachar, Omri the son of Michael:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">Elihu: also called, Eliab</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />Of Zebulun, Ishmaiah the son of Obadiah: of Naphtali, Jerimoth the son of Azriel:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />Of the children of Ephraim, Hoshea the son of Azaziah: of the half tribe of Manasseh, Joel the son of Pedaiah:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />Of the half tribe of Manasseh in Gilead, Iddo the son of Zechariah: of Benjamin, Jaasiel the son of Abner:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Of Dan, Azareel the son of Jeroham. These were the princes of the tribes of Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />But David took not the number of them from twenty years old and under: because the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had said he would increase Israel like to the stars of the heavens.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Joab the son of Zeruiah began to number, but he finished not, because there fell wrath for it against Israel; neither was the number put in the account of the chronicles of king David.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">was: Heb. ascended</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />And over the king's treasures was Azmaveth the son of Adiel: and over the storehouses in the fields, in the cities, and in the villages, and in the castles, was Jonathan the son of Uzziah:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />And over them that did the work of the field for tillage of the ground was Ezri the son of Chelub:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />And over the vineyards was Shimei the Ramathite: over the increase of the vineyards for the wine cellars was Zabdi the Shiphmite:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">over the increase…: Heb. over that which was of the vineyards</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />And over the olive trees and the sycomore trees that were in the low plains was Baal–hanan the Gederite: and over the cellars of oil was Joash:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />And over the herds that fed in Sharon was Shitrai the Sharonite: and over the herds that were in the valleys was Shaphat the son of Adlai:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />Over the camels also was Obil the Ishmaelite: and over the asses was Jehdeiah the Meronothite:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />And over the flocks was Jaziz the Hagarite. All these were the rulers of the substance which was king David's.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />Also Jonathan David's uncle was a counsellor, a wise man, and a scribe: and Jehiel the son of Hachmoni was with the king's sons:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">scribe: or, secretary</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">son…: or, Hachmonite</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />And Ahithophel was the king's counsellor: and Hushai the Archite was the king's companion:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />And after Ahithophel was Jehoiada the son of Benaiah, and Abiathar: and the general of the king's army was Joab.</para>
  <chapter number="28" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />And David assembled all the princes of Israel, the princes of the tribes, and the captains of the companies that ministered to the king by course, and the captains over the thousands, and captains over the hundreds, and the stewards over all the substance and possession of the king, and of his sons, with the officers, and with the mighty men, and with all the valiant men, unto Jerusalem.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">possession: or, cattle</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">and of…: or, and his sons</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">officers: or, eunuchs</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Then David the king stood up upon his feet, and said, Hear me, my brethren, and my people: As for me, I had in mine heart to build an house of rest for the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and for the footstool of our God, and had made ready for the building:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />But God said unto me, Thou shalt not build an house for my name, because thou hast been a man of war, and hast shed blood.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">blood: Heb. bloods</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Howbeit the <char style="nd">Lord</char> God of Israel chose me before all the house of my father to be king over Israel for ever: for he hath chosen Judah to be the ruler; and of the house of Judah, the house of my father; and among the sons of my father he liked me to make me king over all Israel:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />And of all my sons, (for the <char style="nd">Lord</char> hath given me many sons,) he hath chosen Solomon my son to sit upon the throne of the kingdom of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> over Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />And he said unto me, Solomon thy son, he shall build my house and my courts: for I have chosen him to be my son, and I will be his father.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Moreover I will establish his kingdom for ever, if he be constant to do my commandments and my judgments, as at this day.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">constant: Heb. strong</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Now therefore in the sight of all Israel the congregation of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and in the audience of our God, keep and seek for all the commandments of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God: that ye may possess this good land, and leave it for an inheritance for your children after you for ever.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />And thou, Solomon my son, know thou the God of thy father, and serve him with a perfect heart and with a willing mind: for the <char style="nd">Lord</char> searcheth all hearts, and understandeth all the imaginations of the thoughts: if thou seek him, he will be found of thee; but if thou forsake him, he will cast thee off for ever.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Take heed now; for the <char style="nd">Lord</char> hath chosen thee to build an house for the sanctuary: be strong, and do it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Then David gave to Solomon his son the pattern of the porch, and of the houses thereof, and of the treasuries thereof, and of the upper chambers thereof, and of the inner parlours thereof, and of the place of the mercy seat,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />And the pattern of all that he had by the spirit, of the courts of the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and of all the chambers round about, of the treasuries of the house of God, and of the treasuries of the dedicated things:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">of all that…: Heb. of all that was with him</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Also for the courses of the priests and the Levites, and for all the work of the service of the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and for all the vessels of service in the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />He gave of gold by weight for things of gold, for all instruments of all manner of service; silver also for all instruments of silver by weight, for all instruments of every kind of service:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Even the weight for the candlesticks of gold, and for their lamps of gold, by weight for every candlestick, and for the lamps thereof: and for the candlesticks of silver by weight, both for the candlestick, and also for the lamps thereof, according to the use of every candlestick.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />And by weight he gave gold for the tables of shewbread, for every table; and likewise silver for the tables of silver:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Also pure gold for the fleshhooks, and the bowls, and the cups: and for the golden basins he gave gold by weight for every basin; and likewise silver by weight for every basin of silver:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />And for the altar of incense refined gold by weight; and gold for the pattern of the chariot of the cherubims, that spread out their wings, and covered the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />All this, said David, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> made me understand in writing by his hand upon me, even all the works of this pattern.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And David said to Solomon his son, Be strong and of good courage, and do it: fear not, nor be dismayed: for the <char style="nd">Lord</char> God, even my God, will be with thee; he will not fail thee, nor forsake thee, until thou hast finished all the work for the service of the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />And, behold, the courses of the priests and the Levites, even they shall be with thee for all the service of the house of God: and there shall be with thee for all manner of workmanship every willing skilful man, for any manner of service: also the princes and all the people will be wholly at thy commandment.</para>
  <chapter number="29" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Furthermore David the king said unto all the congregation, Solomon my son, whom alone God hath chosen, is yet young and tender, and the work is great: for the palace is not for man, but for the <char style="nd">Lord</char> God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Now I have prepared with all my might for the house of my God the gold for things to be made of gold, and the silver for things of silver, and the brass for things of brass, the iron for things of iron, and wood for things of wood; onyx stones, and stones to be set, glistering stones, and of divers colours, and all manner of precious stones, and marble stones in abundance.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Moreover, because I have set my affection to the house of my God, I have of mine own proper good, of gold and silver, which I have given to the house of my God, over and above all that I have prepared for the holy house,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Even three thousand talents of gold, of the gold of Ophir, and seven thousand talents of refined silver, to overlay the walls of the houses withal:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />The gold for things of gold, and the silver for things of silver, and for all manner of work to be made by the hands of artificers. And who then is willing to consecrate his service this day unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char>?<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">consecrate his service: Heb. fill his hand</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Then the chief of the fathers and princes of the tribes of Israel, and the captains of thousands and of hundreds, with the rulers of the king's work, offered willingly,</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />And gave for the service of the house of God of gold five thousand talents and ten thousand drams, and of silver ten thousand talents, and of brass eighteen thousand talents, and one hundred thousand talents of iron.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />And they with whom precious stones were found gave them to the treasure of the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, by the hand of Jehiel the Gershonite.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Then the people rejoiced, for that they offered willingly, because with perfect heart they offered willingly to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>: and David the king also rejoiced with great joy.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Wherefore David blessed the <char style="nd">Lord</char> before all the congregation: and David said, Blessed be thou, <char style="nd">Lord</char> God of Israel our father, for ever and ever.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Thine, O <char style="nd">Lord</char>, is the greatness, and the power, and the glory, and the victory, and the majesty: for all that is in the heaven and in the earth is thine; thine is the kingdom, O <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and thou art exalted as head above all.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Both riches and honour come of thee, and thou reignest over all; and in thine hand is power and might; and in thine hand it is to make great, and to give strength unto all.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Now therefore, our God, we thank thee, and praise thy glorious name.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />But who am I, and what is my people, that we should be able to offer so willingly after this sort? for all things come of thee, and of thine own have we given thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">be able: Heb. retain, or, obtain strength</char></note><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">of thine…: Heb. of thine hand</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />For we are strangers before thee, and sojourners, as were all our fathers: our days on the earth are as a shadow, and there is none abiding.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">abiding: Heb. expectation</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />O <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God, all this store that we have prepared to build thee an house for thine holy name cometh of thine hand, and is all thine own.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />I know also, my God, that thou triest the heart, and hast pleasure in uprightness. As for me, in the uprightness of mine heart I have willingly offered all these things: and now have I seen with joy thy people, which are present here, to offer willingly unto thee.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">present: Heb. found</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />O <char style="nd">Lord</char> God of Abraham, Isaac, and of Israel, our fathers, keep this for ever in the imagination of the thoughts of the heart of thy people, and prepare their heart unto thee:<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">prepare: or, stablish</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />And give unto Solomon my son a perfect heart, to keep thy commandments, thy testimonies, and thy statutes, and to do all these things, and to build the palace, for the which I have made provision.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />And David said to all the congregation, Now bless the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. And all the congregation blessed the <char style="nd">Lord</char> God of their fathers, and bowed down their heads, and worshipped the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and the king.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />And they sacrificed sacrifices unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, and offered burnt offerings unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, on the morrow after that day, even a thousand bullocks, a thousand rams, and a thousand lambs, with their drink offerings, and sacrifices in abundance for all Israel:</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />And did eat and drink before the <char style="nd">Lord</char> on that day with great gladness. And they made Solomon the son of David king the second time, and anointed him unto the <char style="nd">Lord</char> to be the chief governor, and Zadok to be priest.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Then Solomon sat on the throne of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as king instead of David his father, and prospered; and all Israel obeyed him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />And all the princes, and the mighty men, and all the sons likewise of king David, submitted themselves unto Solomon the king.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">submitted…: Heb. gave the hand under Solomon</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />And the <char style="nd">Lord</char> magnified Solomon exceedingly in the sight of all Israel, and bestowed upon him such royal majesty as had not been on any king before him in Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />Thus David the son of Jesse reigned over all Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />And the time that he reigned over Israel was forty years; seven years reigned he in Hebron, and thirty and three years reigned he in Jerusalem.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />And he died in a good old age, full of days, riches, and honour: and Solomon his son reigned in his stead.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Now the acts of David the king, first and last, behold, they are written in the book of Samuel the seer, and in the book of Nathan the prophet, and in the book of Gad the seer,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="ft" closed="false">book: or, history: Heb. words</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />With all his reign and his might, and the times that went over him, and over Israel, and over all the kingdoms of the countries.</para>
</usx>